<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/sensible-eating-the-retour-b7dc25cbb468-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Sensible eating: the retour</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/sensible-eating-the-retour-b7dc25cbb468 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div>
<head>Sensible eating: the retour</head>
<p>I have just remembered that for about six months starting at the end of
August 2012 I used to keep a blog detailing the meals I was eating out during my
frequent trips to France and elsewhere, the pretext being ostensibly to reassure
other members of my family that I was maintaining at least the semblance of
sensible dietary practice. Well, we know how that sort of thing turns out. I
found <ref target="http://labouffe-2012.blogspot.co.uk/">the blog here</ref>,
and it shows lots of what I think can only be called restaurant porn, and no
evidence of calory control whatsoever. So this week, in the interests of
disinterested scientific enquiry, I thought it might be instructive to rerun the
experience some five years later. Spoiler alert: food porn ahead.</p>
<p>The period covered this time runs from Monday 16th Oct , when I checked into
Domitille’s Airbnb flat just down the road from the Ecole Nationale des Chartes
in rue Richelieu, to the following weekend, when I proceeded to the Grand Hotel
de Tours, for a four night stay finishing today, the 26th. In between the eating
I managed to fit in four days of intensive TEI training at the Ecole nationale
des Chartes, and three days ditto at the MSH of the Université de Tours. It’s
hard work this teaching malarkey : you need plenty of eating to keep it
going.</p>
<p>As any fule kno, the ENC is very conveniently located not only for the now
beautifully restored Richelieu reading room of the Bibliothèque Nationale, but
also for the rue Saint Anne, a narrow little street mostly consisting of the
best selection of little Japanese and Korean restaurants in Paris. Which is why
every lunch time sees people heading up and down the street to find one that’s
got a space for them, and every evening sees people forming hungry queues
outside their current favourite. Emmanuel has reasonably reliable views on which
establishment to patronise most days.</p>
<p>
<hi>17</hi>To demonstrate our broad-mindedness, however, we started by lunching
at a new French establishment called “<ref target="http://www.kaitleen.com"
>Kaitleen</ref>”, just down rue des petits champs, remarkable for serving lots
of “English style” (i.e. crunchy) vegetables, and also for really delicious and
freshly made strawberry shortcake. Left to my own devices in the evening, I also
decided to stay French. The <hi rend="italic">rognons de veau sautés</hi>,
followed by a very creditable <hi rend="italic">riz au lait</hi>, provided by
<ref target="https://saotico.com">a rather upscale establishment called Le
Saotico,</ref> hit the spot at a cost of only €33 with wine.</p>
<p>
<hi>18</hi> We reverted to tradition for lunch: Jubey being closed for works, we
sought out a bowl of noodles and meat at the Kadoya. In the evening, after the
post-course beer at le <ref target="http://www.vaudevilleparis.com"
>Vaudeville</ref>, Emmanuel took me for a walk down towards the Marais, to be
more precise to the rue de Vertboiss, where lurks <ref
target="http://www.pramil.fr/">an exceptional French restaurant called
“Pramil</ref>” after its owner, an ex-academic. Though small and unpretentious
in architecture, and modest in menu, this is a table which <hi rend="italic"
>vaut le detour</hi>: top quality cooking at a reasonable price.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*pVdoP0Dj9omLFefboDkllg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Filet de St Pierre at Pramil. Cost 51.5</head>
</figure>
<p>I had a large amount of fillet de St Pierre (a tasty white fish known in
English as <ref
target="https://behind-the-french-menu.blogspot.co.uk/2012/06/searching-for-the-most-popular-fish-in.html"
>John Dory,</ref> I learn) associated with a few aubergines. Nothing pretentious
as you can see but entirely delicious.</p>
<p>
<hi>19</hi> Hooray, my favourite Japanese udon bar, Jubey, is open again. They
don’t have a website though you’ll find the place listed routinely in those
tedious “Top Ten places to eat Noodles in Paris” pages, because they’re too busy
cooking noodles. Down the tiny twisty stairs to the little basement we go, gaze
in wonder at the varieties on offer. It’s the ideal lunch spot: the service is
quick, the food is tasty, there is plenty of scope for choice, within the basic
parameters. And it only costs €22, with tea.</p>
<p>In the evening, again left to my own devices, I succumbed to the lure of the
duck : at <ref target="https://www.lintillac-paris.com/">Domaine de
Lintillac,</ref> a classy duck-themed establishment offering amongst other
things, the <hi rend="italic">Choucroute de Canard</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
>Confit de Canard</hi> was nicer than the <hi rend="italic">Saucisse de chez
nous,</hi> which was nicer than the <hi rend="italic">Magret Fumé</hi>. The
boiled potato and sauerkraut were fine, though not quite what I’d expected.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*jDhe6xVQCvk4yF1Fl-WJ8A.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Choucroute de canard avec son saucisson at Domaine de Lintillac. 26.6 euro
inc pot de cote.</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi>20</hi> I persuaded Emmanuel that we’d like to try Korean for change, so we
lunched at the restau Dokkebi in rue des petits champs, which was fine once I’d
remembered how to cope with metal chop sticks. And in the evening I went for the
celebratory option at a celebrated Parisian <hi rend="italic">bouchon</hi>
called <ref target="http://www.auxlyonnais.com"><hi rend="italic">Aux
Lyonnais</hi></ref>. The decor is <hi rend="italic">typique</hi>, and the food
is plausibly <hi rend="italic">authentique</hi>. Here I had the <hi
rend="italic">salade frisee</hi> (naturally enhanced with <hi rend="italic"
>lardons</hi> and a poached egg), the <hi rend="italic">foie de veau</hi>, and
the <hi rend="italic">pot de figues</hi>, all of which were delicious, as was
the extremely expensive pichet de Chateauneuf du Pape I’d ordered in a moment of
inattention.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*mOWkROzXXSanJgJyFxcivg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Happy diners assembling. Note the corks’ nest.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*9cUAvy4LmyIcbENR0AbuCg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*IbMFVGPOdBnY91QO9sB3iQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*e3g8ryq90ys-WQm4IDwB2A.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Aux Lyonnais, rue St Marc: 101 euro, of which 40 was the pot de
chateauneuf du pape</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi>21</hi> My day off. I walked for miles to the <ref
target="http://museevieromantique.paris.fr">Museum of Romantic Life</ref>, rue
Chaptal in the 9th, formerly home of Georges Sand and currently exhibiting
rather more Redoute than one might wish for. But the permanent collection is
interesting and in the grounds there is a pleasant tree-filled garden, and a
little shed where they serve a decent quiche and salad, which was really all I
felt up to consuming to be honest. And in the evening I said my farewell to St
Annes street, by dining at the only place without a queue at the door, namely a
huge canteen- like establishment called Laï-Laï Ken. This provided a very good
seaweed soup, acceptable beef and onions, with tasty rice, followed by a couple
of steamed red-bean filled dumplings for that tiny hollow.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*LUkmT8a5DBRNN9alzG8Kww.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*xTZnIES-_vWVgm1nG5lQtA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*OmpYAu1fnpdypWQAUk0wGQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Diner at Lai Lai Ken, rue St Anne. 29.5 euro including a beer</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi>22</hi> Off to Tours. I arrived in time for a late light lunch at the <ref
target="http://www.univers-restaurant.fr/tours.html">Brasserie l’Univers</ref>,
where I consumed <hi rend="italic">bavette frites</hi>, and a <hi rend="italic"
>cafe gourmand</hi>.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*o4BEj2fGAgcfN8gWJEIvUg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*hPgZuQn54asuaeWrTxpsrA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head> Traditional lunch: bavette frites, followed by cafe gourmand. Brasserie
l’Univers trots them out for 24.8 euro including a glass of Bourgeuil</head>
</figure>
<p>In the evening, as per tradition, I met up with Toshi, Alexei, and Sandrine
at <ref target="http://www.la-chope.fr">La Chope</ref> for a quality dinner:
salade vertes, St Pierre again, this time just a little one, served on the bone
and with all the fiddly bits, including tasty vegetables. And a bowl of fresh
red fruit laced with fizzy white wine for pud.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*UiB0VITlREfoKl6p2_Bpcw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*-pKSmQ8BITUATiDINtgu1g.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head> La Chope’s take on St Pierre was smaller but just as tasty. Fresh fruit
swimming in bubbly white wine.</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi>23</hi>This year’s lunches at the MSH were held in a large canteen 5 minutes
walk away from the MSH car park, overlooking the river Cher, and next door to
some local EDF office block. They were no worse than other French canteen
lunches and better than some.</p>
<p>In the evening Alexei and I headed for a fairly posh establishment called
<ref target="http://www.16jeanjau.com">Le 16</ref> where we dined with the new
boss of the CESR and Toshi. Formal dinner conversation in French with an
Italian, a Russian, a Japanese, and a Brit seemed a bit odd, but no complaints
about the food. I had the velouté de <hi rend="italic">cèpes et marrons</hi>,
followed by <hi rend="italic">Le cochon torréfié de 7 h au miel et balsamique,
purée grand-mère</hi> aka slow cooked pork with mash, which was much nicer than
it sounds and too filling to permit any dessert.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*azYsaZwN2yCGJSmNsZaEvQ.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>
<hi>24</hi>th : something called <hi rend="italic">rougaille saucisses</hi>
appeared on the canteen lunch menu today, but was some distance away from the
dish I know under that name, and not just because I eat it with chips. In the
evening, Sandrine took me and Toshi out for a much nicer and more relaxed
dinner, at a little place called <ref target="http://www.lepetitpatrimoine.fr"
><hi rend="italic">Le Petit Patrimoine</hi></ref>, on rue Colbert. I had their
take on salad with bits of roast duck, duck pate, and fresh figs, which was both
beautiful and delicious, followed by bits of chicken in a rather strange gloopy
sauce, which was neither. But the company was good.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Ect4Tfgvy-0wG0dqdo6ODg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*uEMgWvdGbMKlcpgwQeZddg.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head> Duck salad at the Little Heritage: much better than chicken nuggets in
peanut sauce.</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi>25</hi>Alas, my last day in Tours. For lunch there was a quite respectable
<hi rend="italic">daube de boeuf</hi>, with the usual <hi rend="italic"
>frites,</hi> and some rather less usual baked fennel.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*tfV3HGhuOAl41sJgziALnA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Quite a decent canteen lunch: note the baked fennel</head>
</figure>
<p> For dinner, left to my own resources, after a long walk, I decided to
revisit the <hi rend="italic">Brasserie du chien jaune</hi> just over the road
from the station and still as good as I said it was back in 2012: it’s been
through at least two changes of proprietor since then, but the 1920s décor is
just the same, and the cooking is more ambitious. Definitely worth a visit.
Here’s the slate :</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*WY_RJ1neuhTSE179dwSR0g.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Menu “magret” at the Yellow Dog. I had each of the second alternatives.
See below. Total including wine 38.9 and worth every centime.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Y1Wh6Y7PJ8swUaqI9hEu4Q.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*7duYkClg8IYd_4SuJxmSww.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*42EjLjtxqAiEZ7AIAozQFw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Duck salad (this time with foie gras as well as bits of duck), gigot et
grenailles (excellent), vacherin (superb mixture of meringue, ice cream, fresh
fruit, nuts, caramel syrup, and mint).</head>
</figure>
<p>So, what have we learned? Firstly that the price of a meal is not entirely
reliable as an indication of its quality. Secondly that the art of the French
<hi rend="italic">restauranteur</hi> is not dead, even in the age of <hi
rend="italic">macdo</hi> and <hi rend="italic">le snacking</hi>. And third, that
I really like eating.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
