<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/a-sicilian-venture-5812f0175dc3-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A Sicilian Venture</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>downloaded from  https://medium.com/@louBurnard/a-sicilian-venture-5812f0175dc3 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head>A Sicilian Venture</head>
<p>Oxford in February being cold and miserable, we decided to run away to Sicily
for a few days this week. The major constraint being not to spend too much money
and not to be away on a Tuesday evening, we left by the very first available
cheap flight to Roma on a Thursday morning, which entailed an overnight stay at
Heathrow, which became less cheap when the cost of bus travel round Heathrow
from T5 to the Hotel and back to T4 is factored in, especially since we decided
we couldn’t face any more bus travel and ordered a taxi for the morning run
instead, thus earning a few precious minutes extra in the comfort of an Ibis
bed. Anyway, we made it in good time for the 0725 departure and the flight was
no more awful than any other fully booked two hour flight, and better than some
since most people on it (including us) were asleep most of the way. And then we
had an hour or so to find our way from one side of Fiumicino to another to make
the connecting flight, which was of course late, but by then we had been
somewhat restored by real Italian coffee and cake. And this was a flight like
they used to be, barely half full and peaceful all the way to Catania.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*QJ231TiNoZX4B0PZExv80A.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Catania’s elefant</head>
</figure>
<p>Ah Italia! It isn’t raining, and the bus is in no hurry to leave. The streets
around Catania station are somewhat down at heel, and the car parking
regulations are (if they exist) routinely flouted, which slightly confuses the
task of getting into our B&amp;B, though not as much as being confronted with
four flights of stairs when we do so, however grand. But the room when we reach
it and stop puffing is nice enough, and the day is still young, so we can go out
and explore a bit. After ten minutes or so, the streets cease to be quite so
grubby and noisy and we arrive eventually at the touristical centre where there
is a grand duomo and a monument with an elephant on it. Not quite as magnificent
as the elephants of Chambery, and made of lava, but still quite impressive.
Outside the duomo there are touristy shops featuring rather dashing sicilian
puppets made of metal, and commemorative objects (notably a bust of <hi
rend="italic">il duce</hi>) made of lava. Inside the duomo, we are confronted
with several very large and remarkably kitsch devotional objects commemorating
the local patron saint, St Agatha. These <hi rend="italic">cerei</hi> feature
wax images of cherubs, lots of golden decoration and several somewhat gruesome
representations of said saint’s 6th century involuntary mastectomy.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*GqQHUBpCz4XBoojfe9IJxg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>St Agatha allegedly saved Catania from total immolation when its friendly
local neighbourhood volcano, Mt Etna, did a number back in the 17th century, and
again more recently, or so I understand from the Latin inscriptions on the duomo
wall, which also sports some rather elaborately restored frescos. A gang of
school children join us in dutifully inspecting said devotional objects and
speculating about how easy or otherwise they must have been to carry around the
town last weekend during St A.’s festival. After all of which it is clearly time
for some refreshment, beyond slabs of toffee encrusted almonds. We do this
twice, in rapid succession, being still somewhat chronologically confused by our
5 am start: first we have a glass of nice sicilian wine with some freshly baked
bruschetta. There’s an Italian cookery programme on the telly, which makes this
more interesting than it might otherwise be. And then we find somewhere ready to
serve us dinner at the ridiculous hour of 7 pm: <hi rend="italic">pasta alla
norma</hi> followed by <hi rend="italic">fritto misto</hi> — the former being a
rather tasty local speciality, and the latter being a mistake, since we had both
forgotten that the <hi rend="italic">fritto</hi> in question are exclusively
inedible sea-dwelling non-fish creatures. But a bottle of local wine helped wash
it down, and we staggered back remarkably cheerful, managed to get up the stairs
again, and so to bed by 10 pm</p>
<p>Next morning, the sun is shining brightly by 9 am which is when we are due to
breakfast, though L wisely elects to stay in bed instead. But by 10 am we are
down at Catania station having a much nicer coffee and bun before boarding a
TRAIN, hoorah, to Siracusa. A train, a proper Italian regionale, with 1970s
interior design, and windows that open, and signs commemorating the celebrated
Sicilian tenor E Pericoloso Sporgersi, and men in smart suits that punch tickets
with aplomb. And the sun continues to shine, even as the train chugs through the
less than scenic suburbs of Catania, and the immense industrial complex of
tankers and refineries further along the coast towards Siracusa. But there are
orange groves, some more thriving than others, and desert tracts and
romantically defenestrated buildings to see as well. A thoroughly satisfying
train journey in fact. We check into a rather grand hotel in Siracusa, rejoicing
in the name of the Grande Albergo Alfeo. It reminds me of the Hotel Duomo in
Pisa <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, not least in that our room is not yet
ready, so we deposit the bags and go for a walk down to the scenic part of town,
i.e. the fish market, the temple of appolo, the splendid duomo square, the
fountain of arethusa etc. And of course, lunch.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*WoSfwHflTBJm_ALrB8dNRw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> The fish market is everything it should be; there are people selling
beautiful sicilian oranges, assorted spices and herbs and nuts, as well as
shouting the virtues of their fish in a traditional manner. We get a free sample
of recently cooked ricotta, and purchase lots of spices. Then we settle on a
trattoria and proceed to eat. I go for pasta with salsiccia and funghi, and L
for some fish-wrapped vegetables. A street cat yowls hopefully but we ignore it
and stuff our faces. There’s just room, eventually, for a genuine sicilian
cassata which is, of course, a sponge cake with lots of ricotta, and nothing to
do with ice cream, as any fule kno. And then we stagger off to look at the sea,
which is crashing noisily against the sunlit promenade where the cats hang out.
All very satisfying, so we do it again, on the other side of Ortigia. A sensible
person would, at this point, probably have gone home to sleep off their lunch,
but I am determined to inspect the Fountain of Arethusa (as advertised by John
Milton), so we plod onwards to same. Though it is not much of a fountain these
days, being largely a large pond, with some papyrus growing in the middle of it,
and a lot of tacky tourist shops around it. Never mind. We walk back past the
fountain of Artemis, which is a proper fountain, though the feet are by now
preventing our souls from being as stirred as they might have been. And so to
our magnificent hotel, which continues to respect tradition by giving us back
our bags but then confiscating our <hi rend="italic">documenti.</hi> And so to a
too much delayed post prandial snooze. For an evening snack, we manage to
consume more pasta (L) and a Roman pizza (me), prepared before our eyes by a
feminist fast food shack down the road, with very unconfortable chairs. This
Italian eating is insidious.</p>
<p>For Saturday, I am resolved that we should do some more tourism. So straight
after breakfast (also magnificent) we hotfoot it back to the station for the
1036 <hi rend="italic">regionale</hi> to Noto. This, an even more elderly and
much smaller version of the train we came on, is just as pleasant to ride,
especially since the sun is still gleaming through the grubby windows. Once out
of urban industrial sprawl, the route takes us through much worked-on
countryside, masses of oranges and lemons, a few almond orchards now in pink
blossom, the occasional cow or sheep. Noto, when we get there, is an unmanned
station, and there are no taxis to take us up the hill to see its cultural
glories, alas. We dutifully follow the two or three other touristic couples up
the hill, passing curious locals remarking to each other in the local quaint
patois words to the effect of “must be spring, the tourists are back”. And quite
a hill it is too. By the time we reach the nice park full of monumental busts
and the splendid gateway onto the main street, now known as Corso Vittore
Emanuele, we are in serious need of coffee.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*f_9uY_AcYl2ej5myJ30TXQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> Another place which that 17th century earthquake knocked about a bit, Noto
was extensively rebuilt in the grand 18th century baroque style, and boasts a
magnificent total of 35 churches, not all of which are along the <hi
rend="italic">corso</hi>, though many are. See further Wikipedia, and indeed
most discerning travel writers of the western world. It’s still a beautiful
sunny day, and the street is full of happy sicilians standing about and
nattering, while they have a chance before the tourists descend en masse. The
buildings are very rococo and the sunlight gives them an added charm, though not
quite enough to mitigate entirely the steepness of the steps once you stray from
the main street in search of a quiet little trattoria, which once found is all
too likely to be shut, since the tourist season really has not yet started. But
persistence is rewarded, and we are soon settling into the delightful Trattoria
Ducezio for some of their “downhome southern cooking” as Mr Google rather
quaintly calls it. I had <hi rend="italic">penne con spada</hi> (also featuring
melanzane and menta) and L had excellent ricotta filled ravioli, slightly marred
by a porky sauce. We then shared a plate of rabbit, which was pure greed, before
staggering very slowly staggering very slowly back down the hill to the station
for the sleepy journey back to the Grande Albergo Alfeo, on an even more ancient
train, along with the other day trippers. Somehow, despite the numbers of
calories expended on walking up and down hills, we don’t feel capable of further
dining, unless you count some fruit and yoghurt. Oh, and well, I confess, I had
to taste a slice of the ice-cream variant <hi rend="italic">cassata</hi> from
one of the local <hi rend="italic">gelaterie</hi> before retiring for the
night.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*QDZP5un34EsMPPZ3S4kTqw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> Sunday dawns still sunny and after a leisurely breakfast we embark on a trip
up the main shopping street in search of more culture, specifically Neopolis,
the celebrated archaeological park of Siracusa. The walk is a bit severe in the
sunshine, but worth the slog, though maybe not quite all of the 10 euro entrance
ticket. Once we have been guided to the right entrance, we are directed to
admire firstly a vast third century BC Greek amphitheatre, and secondly a
massive cave known as Dionysius’ ear. The former is exposed to the midday sun
and somewhat vertiginous; moreover there are no dramatic events in prospect,
unless you count the German tourists. The latter is at the bottom of a huge
quarry behind the theatre, most of which is pleasantly shaded by assorted trees,
with strategically placed benches, hoorah. Inside the ear, you can hear the
cooing of pigeons who live at the top of it, and also of course the operatic
experiments of visiting students, but it is basically a very large hole carved
out of the limestone cliff which supplied (we assume) much of the buildings in
the vicinity. From there we dutifully proceed to admire the remains of a much
more complicated Roman theatre from the 5th century AD. Still no shows in
evidence, though there are informative panels to read, some very ancient
inscriptions, and some cartwheel tracks they couldn’t be bothered to repair back
in the day. Culturally replete, or at least acculturated, we make our way back
to the area set aside for bars and providers of tourist knick-knacks, all of
whom have gone to lunch. There’s also no sign of a bus, so we take a taxi back
to Ortigia to find lunch of our own.</p>
<p>Which is provided by L’Isoletta, a tiny family restaurant near the fish
market: <hi rend="italic">pasta al carciofi</hi> (and unexpectedly shrimps) for
me; pasta with “baby fish” for L. The baby fish are barely visible but quite
tasty. The restaurant fills up with families (it only takes two) rapidly, and I
realise that the time for the Sunday <hi rend="italic">passagiata</hi> is
rapidly approaching. And sure enough the charming little streets of Ortigia are
already filling with happy Siracusan families strolling about in that uniquely
Italian way. We inspect the inside of the duomo, which we didnt have time to do
on our first afternoon; this is mostly notable for being a repurposed Greek
temple, witness the massive pillars holding it up, and the polychrome marble
floor. But the repurposing of the temple of Athena as the church of Santa Lucia
took place quite a while ago, like (it seems) most things in Ortigia. Time also
decrees that we must now retrace our steps, past the remains of the temple of
Apollo, over the bridge, down the Corso Umberto I, back to the Gran Albergo, and
so onward to the railway station, in good time for the 16h15 train back to
Catania, a desultory dinner in a deserted restaurant where some less pretentious
football team is making mincemeat of Bologna Wanderers on the telly, and an
overnight stay in the (perfectly acceptable) Hotel Rigel. Monday morning we’re
back in bus and airplane mode, and holidays are over, for a while.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*O7yBjZtTugJxs9nXdwIaXA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>mount aetna poking its nose through the clouds to say <hi rend="italic"
>arrividerci</hi></head>
</figure>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
