<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/the-black-and-white-challenge-and-me-5f0a2f4780ae-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Black-and-white Challenge and Me</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/the-black-and-white-challenge-and-me-5f0a2f4780ae and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div>
<head>The Black-and-white Challenge and Me</head>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*xRmQT1_CdXPcgWi_FJferg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Day 7: road sign at the junction of Lonsdale Road and National Cycle Route
51 south</head>
</figure>
<p>An operational definition says that a Facebook “Challenge” is when you do
(and record) something or other vaguely unusual but recordable on Facebook, and
then nominate one of your friends to do likewise, usually repeatedly over a
period of time such as a week. The “something or other” might take a spectacular
form such as “film yourself emptying a bucket of cold water over your own head”
or a more artistic one such as the “black-and-white challenge” , in which you
are just required to post a monochrome photo innocent of people, pets, or
explanation. There are doubtless many others, but these two seem to have been
taken up by enough otherwise unconnected people to have achieved the dubious
status of being an “internet meme”: a phenomenon that takes on a life of its own
as different members of the social network pick it up, or notice others picking
it up. This posting is me musing on my experience of the Black and White
Challenge, which I completed yesterday, coincidentally on my birthday.</p>
<p>I first noticed this challenge a couple of months ago, and was challenged
myself just last week. (Full disclosure, I asked a daughter — who had herself
been challenged — to challenge me). I take a lot of photos, but usually not in
black and white, and I liked the idea of being constrained to do something a bit
different, within a predefined arbitrary framework. It’s the Oulipian in me. And
taking black and white photos is quite a different exercise: you have only
shapes, light, and shade to play with, and you have to pick and choose your
subject matter. Which is probably why some people who take (or are forced into)
this challenge tend to fall back on the same rather restricted set of abstract
patterns, bare trees, architectural panoramas, close-ups of domestic interiors,
etc. A Slate hack recently <ref
target="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/technology/2017/10/the_7_days_7_photos_challenge_taking_over_facebook_is_neither_a_challenge.html"
>got very snooty</ref> about this pointing out that <hi rend="italic">The prompt
to eschew color, people, and explanatory text has given participants free rein
to post cringe-worthy “arty” pictures they’d normally have the good sense to be
embarrassed by: their shadow-dipped lattes, their brooding pets, their kids’
tilted-over toys, often framed diagonally to add that extra “I’m doing serious
photography” edge…</hi>but this seems to miss the point: you can’t claim that
the challenge is too simple to be a challenge, and the same time complain that
people aren’t finding it challenging enough. Going monochrome requires you to
see the world in a different way, and it’s not always easy. The same Google
search that threw up the above source (trust me: I do not habitually browse
Slate) also threw up several bloggers who wanted to showcase their results, and
were clearly relishing this opportunity to deploy a little creative ingenuity.
As you might expect, some of them were dire, but <ref
target="https://thoughtsbykim.com/2017/10/17/seven-day-black-and-white-photo-challenge"
>some were quite impressive</ref> . And I am quite pleased with my own efforts
too (see below).</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*sQ25_EzvLv0wlSWUVMEQ5A.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Winter sunshine and shadows outside Joe’s restaurant in Summertown. Too
cold for anyone but desperate smokers though.</head>
</figure>
<p> But the aspect of this challenge that I wasn’t really expecting, or at least
hadn’t thought about much, was the way other people reacted to being nominated.
I decided I would constrain my nominations too, choosing people I now see only
on Facebook and who have not to my knowledge been challenged in this way before.
I alternated genders and aimed for a wide geography. Seven choices doesn’t give
an opportunity to do much more in the name of diversity. Consequently, none of
my nominations aimed at close friends or family members (the latter because they
were all busy challenging each other).</p>
<p>My first nominee flatly refused to participate. My second politely declined.
My third said he might get round to it. My fourth, bless her, said she’d give it
a shot, and has now started. My fifth agreed to do part of the challenge — the
artistic part, but not the social one. My sixth and seventh are (to date)
silent. Does this reluctance say something about people in general, or about the
specific ones I have contacted ? Is it a typical take-up rate ? Of course if
Facebook offered a decent API (and I was clever enough to use it), these are
questions I could answer automatically. But just for the record, let’s manually
compute the following magical number as a measure of the success of any one set
of challenge outcomes : the number of photos delivered + the number of photos
delivered by challengees + the number of persons challenged who both delivered
at least one photo and challenged one further person. We can’t sit around
waiting forever to calculate this number, but today, eight days after I took up
the challenge, my magical number is 7+ 4 + 1 or a paltry 12. Whereas the person
who challenged me seems to have clocked up a stunning 6 + 21 + 3, a magnificent
30. I am standing by all agog for news of other people’s scores.</p>
<p>In conclusion, for the benefit of non-facebookers, I’m including here
carefully curated copies of my seven monochrome moments. I still like all of
them. Let me know if you do too.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*8mt1-ZfqT8Y88Kdn7uEeTA.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Day 1 : Oyster mushrooms on sale at the Summertown Farmers market</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*1p8mM4yirB1U3fic2mD6Kg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Day 2 : First snow fall of the year hits our back garden in La Vergne. The
Dr Seuss ladder on the shed is still intact, but only just.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*qxNP0E7PnE-ODjw-DccD5w.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Day 3 : Experimenting with my phone’s ability to mimic a real camera: this
is in front of the church currently being renovated at Place d’Estienne
d’Orves, Paris</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*AClbZvAWfQV54S6boGRV8w.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Day 4: An apple from my French garden with a rather saucy posterior</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*XaIRWK0RAcpVMP_lDDmrbA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Day 5 : Paperwork piled up on my Oxford desk. Mostly the stuff of unfiled
expense claims.</head>
</figure>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
