<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/popular-follies-19ef82324785-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Popular Follies</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/popular-follies-19ef82324785 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div>
<head>Popular Follies</head>
<p>Back in the 1970s, Peter Pope and I spent a lot of time writing joky stories
and mind-teasers into a red notebook, dedicated to the capture of stoned
babbling. Combined with Peter’s collection of strange print ephemera, a
fascination with the business of cut and paste, and a desire to produce
something amusing to read, this eventually resulted in a magazine (one issue
only) called <hi rend="italic">Popular Follies</hi>, master minded by Peter,
with contributions from me and others. I’ve long been meaning to make a digital
version of it available, since the hundred or so print copies produced are long
since disappeared. The unexpected news of Peter’s death yesterday morning made
me think this might be a commemoration he’d have appreciated, so here it is.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*LZgvqAdqYJoi0brRVepT4w.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Front cover.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*_j4w-ebHJ_auivZIQvq_zQ.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>24 pages of bad vibes. The cartoon at left was Tim’s; the rest of this
spread Peter confected from his archive of printed ephemera</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*sZyjCiUTQfwkUnw9eUJuHw.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Shave the egg and take its hair. The Kierkegaard cartoon was also Tim’s
and continues over the next two pages. The photo shows me and Peter and a
mirror. I wrote “<hi rend="italic">Splot the Mistake”. The remaining good advice
on this spread is all from Peter</hi></head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*wfy4k4xToO2ljlT030n_HA.png"
rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Tell the folks this is the promised land calling. Peter wrote this poetic
tribute to a major component of the soundtrack of life in our cottage in Stanton
St John.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*m8HouBsgkYy0fjXLF9PPlg.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Eternity now! Peter performed the prophetic poem about Mechanical Animals
on his battered olivetti. I don’t know where the vegetarian put-down on the
right comes from.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*u2sOoTfVsYKxzlNwptwivw.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Je suis marxiste: tendance Groucho. At one stage, we planned to call the
magazine “Tendence Groucho” in homage to that celebrated slogan of 68. In the
event, this spread is as close as Popular Follies gets to a political statement,
On the left a nice drawing by Caroline. On the right some cheerful prose by me.
And a photo of John Ruskin.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*dqob5hj1xoKlHHxk-Ko0rw.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Sorry it’s not on our list of places. The picture at left is one I found
in some 19th century journal, not consciously emulating Akbar Del Piombo. The
collection of photos and associated text all come from Peter.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*vahX38VWIqsmx2StUSkJuA.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>After I hadn’t known you for what seems like a long long time: this
constructed history around a collection of postcards is one of the nicest things
in the magazine</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*JzN7qZT8v4SbH3PaI5cRlw.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Kicks for you. More residue from the Red Book, a quote from Groucho Marx,
more lovingly curated ephemera. Tim’s cartoon continues overleaf…</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*RcfF21_AbFB1qVE9papJuw.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Every man his own neighbour. More found art at left; some scientific
speculation at right. The running title on the right is a Firesign Theater
catchphrase.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*t9cYr262t_yHC4o8SeVI5A.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Even the worm in the stone eats herbs. I admit to responsibility both for
the caption at left and the blameless sheep photo at right. Peter wrote
the rest.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Ls_OzTDqplPmMO3XGB9HTQ.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Hold it right there… is another quote from The Firesign Theater. My pease
pudden recipe pays tribute to a Stanton St John speciality. Tim’s cartoon
exhibits his superior draughtsmanship.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*CpoyZd7FxCZXUXR8DmxY1A.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Fast and Bulbous .. is a quote from another favourite album: Trout Mask
Replica. Peter’s take on logic problems at top right.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*bqC4tLOP8FuA5NF8VAVYYQ.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Pack your ermines Mary, we’re getting outta here is probably a tip of the
hat to William S Burroughs. Peter and I argued interminably about the
questionnaire, but I think we got it right in the end. I particularly like the
last sentence of question 7. And the remarks to the typesetter at
the endx.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*sxBTNX_QsIqwTY0vKZxMaA.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Back cover</head>
</figure>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
