<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/a-curious-coincidence-d3f6b7c395d5-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A curious coincidence</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from  https://medium.com/@louBurnard/a-curious-coincidence-d3f6b7c395d5 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head>A curious coincidence</head>
<p>… or welcome to my Karass.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*gvrbaWZ2PZn7ne1lymdKCw.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>
</figure>
<p>So it’s November 1970, and I’m still living in a cottage in Stanton St John
where I am now into the second year of my BPhil, and therefore still getting
paid by the state to read lots of 19th century novels, which is nice. I have had
a bucolic summer doing just that, in the intervals of shifting bales of straw
and looking after cows at Manor Farm, and now it’s time to start doing some
serious work on that little old thesis thingie. But wait! Here’s a letter from
my old friend Lola Pryce, who is busy in London learning to be an architect at
some prestigious institution called the AA.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*k6NfcoUfpoYJBH_PbeWCnQ.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>“We have taken Oxford as our brief, as, you may know, it is having the
first 1906A computer in the country, plus a whole computer research &amp;
operation faculty…”</head>
</figure>
<p> Over the page, she elaborates further on her project:</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*zu8-mF1TWuMgCNUOOXCqcg.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>“… Computers are such charming things themselves; they need, of course,
fantastic servicing — enormous air-conditioning ducts, dust filters, totally
removable false floors capable of standing enormous point loads etc. etc. And
then one considers such things as how to make a totally artificial environment
pleasant; how to make life more bearable for those poor bitches, punch-card
operators; <hi rend="bold">do the engineers share a rest room with the research
computer operators?</hi> (i.e. do the Proles actually share with the
Intellectuals — I mean, it’s a real decision, my god)</head>
</figure>
<p>All very interesting, and good to know that the British class system was
alive and well even in this supposedly futuristic context. In 1970, I knew
nothing of the University’s data processing, and I lost touch with Lola when I
left Oxford for Malawi in 1972. And yet, when I returned to Oxford a couple of
years later in April 1974 and got a proper job as a computer operator, my first
few weeks were spent in the 1906A machine room designed by Lola and her cohorts,
which still (I think) stands behind number 13 Banbury Road, though since
converted to other uses. Coincidence? Or what?</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
