<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../diaryPrint.css" ?>-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>2025</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-01-07">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <!-- <head>2024: still nothing new</head>
 -->
   <!--<figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/2023-timeline.png"
     width="450px" height="500px"/>
    <head>European end of my time line</head>
   </figure>-->
   <p>What to say about the year 2025? Mostly variations on the same theme as other parts of the
    2020s. The same pattern of occasional expeditions to Mauritius or (mostly) France in the
    intervals of medical appointments and family gatherings; the same occasional excursion. I
    continued to pootle around with Victorian dramas, giving rise to <ref
     target="https://foxglove.hypotheses.org/category/tei-xml-praxis/victorian-theatre">occasional
     blog postings</ref>, and even the occasional academic conference. Some highlights are listed
    below. </p>
   <p>
    <label>January</label>On the 10th, I made many jars of marmalade. It's hard, but someone has to.  
    On the 11th we went back to Oxford, overnighting at the Easy Hotel in
    Summertown before joining the throng celebrating Hazel's 80th birthday. Back in Bristol we were
    taken for an outing to Kings Weston House by Pam and Philip: nice architecture, though the cake
    shop was not as fancy as we had been led to believe. On the 24th, I was rather impressed by T. Chalamet's
    performance as the young Bob Dylan in a movie called <ref
     target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Complete_Unknown">"A complete unknown",</ref> showing
    at the luxurious Everyman cinema on Whiteladies Rd. I was so much older then. </p>
   <p>
    <label>February</label> On the 8th we escaped to Mauritius for a month or so, staying in two
    different beach hotels, and a third floor flat in Curepipe. We also experienced a tropical storm
    called Garance, my first such experience: full details are in <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/2025-03-27-mru.html"
     >my holiday report</ref>
   </p>
   <p>
    <label>March</label> Our arrival back in Bristol on the 3rd was fairly horrible, mostly because
    of the journey but also because as we staggered out of the bus station in search of the Uber, L
    realised she had left her phone and kindle on the bus now heading off to the land of Wales. This led to
    much to and fro with the Flixbus website and with assorted insurance companies, but culminated
    in a trip to Newport on the 28th where she was reunited with her gadgets, and I saw some rather
    splendid monuments commemorating the Newport Raising of 1839. We need more chartists. </p>
   <p>
    <label>April</label> For our first French trip of the year, we experimented with a flight from
    Bristol to Bordeaux on the 6th,  staying the night there before taking the 1026 TER to Limoges
    (arr 1248), proceeding via another TER to Gueret which arrived just in time for the 1430 TAD.
    But what we did for the next four weeks in La Vergne before catching the train back to England, I
    have no idea. </p>
   <p> At the start of <label>May</label>, I went to Oxford for a college reunion: a Gaudy lunch at
    Balliol. This was surprisingly enjoyable: the food was good and both Carl Schmidt and Nick
    Shrimpton allowed me to drone on about Lacy at them. People I did not remember at all seemed
    to remember me, which is curiously satisfying; and my, how old we all are. 
    Later in the month, we had an excursion to Bath
    with P&amp;P to see Opera Luna's version of the Mikado, which I enjoyed immensely. And at the very
    end of the month, we tried another route into France, viz train to Portsmouth (the caribbean
    resto opposite the station is actually quite good), and the late afternoon ferry to Ouistreham,
    where we stayed a couple of nights in the Hotel "Le Cosy Riva Bella", enabling us to explore the
   Normandy beach a bit.</p>
   <p>
    <label>June</label> From Ouistreham, we proceeded by bus and train to Coutances, and then by bus
    to La Haye where Jef and Nicole came to meet us. We stayed in a slightly odd Air BNB
    in La Haye, and did some seaside expeditions with Jef, still in his corset. On the 5th, we left
    them at Valognes and took the train to La Souterraine, via (inevitably) Paris, and started our
    proper summer holiday in La Vergne. The grass grew high, there were cherries on the trees and
    lambs in the fields. Evelyne took us out for dinner at the end of the month. </p>
   <p>
    <label>July</label> We spent the whole month in La Vergne, doing nothing in particular. P&amp;P
    came for a 48 hour visit : they tested the new bed (it worked, though the hot water did not);
    they also took us out for L's birthday lunch. There was a brocante around the reservoir, and at
    the end of the month we went out with everyone else to celebrate Evelyne's birthday at the Royal
    Wok (eat as much as you can) before reluctantly returning to Bristol via La Souterraine and
    Paris.</p>
   <p> During <label>August</label> we were on grandparent duty, first in Nottingham for Harvey's
    birthday, and then to Maryland for Daphne's birthday bowling party at Stratford on the 9th. As
    has been their habit, Belinda and family passed through Bristol on their way to Cornwall on the
    16th: we vacated the house to put them up, which gave us an excuse to sample Channings hotel: a
    pretty good breakfast, if not up to German standards. On the 21st P&amp;P took us on another
    agreeable outing, by train to Freshford, along the banks of the Avon to Bradford on Same and
    back by train. And at the end of the month, I flew off to Berlin all on my own in order to
    participate in the <ref target="https://summit.dracor.org/programme-overview">Dracor
     Summit</ref> at the Free University of Berlin. Very exciting. Getting from the airport to the
    campus by U-bahn and S-bahn after dark was also quite exciting. </p>
   <p>
    <label>September</label> I stayed in Berlin until the 5th, relishing the novel experience of being on
    a well-funded European university campus and staying in a posh hotel. Then I took the slow route
    back to La Vergne, via Mannheim, Karlsruhe, Paris, and La Souterraine. On the 20th, after
    another largely uneventful fortnight in La Vergne, I left for Bristol via Paris, again. On the
    27th Kev had a surprise 50th birthday party in a pub in Easton. </p>
   <p>
    <label>October </label> On the 14th I nipped off to Caen, by train, for a meeting of the <ref
     target="https://caesar-project.unicaen.fr/caesar/">CaeSAR Project</ref> scientific council,
    which was fun, though I am still not sure how exactly it will accelerate research. I saw some of
    my Lacy texts being presented by MAX, but only momentarily. I stayed two nights in a very noisy
    hotel over a bar in the centre of Caen, before MrsH was shamed into moving me to a much nicer
    one near the station. Being in France, I was then unable to resist the temptation of the lengthy
    but increasingly familiar train journey, from Caen to La Souterraine, via Tours and Vierzon. It
    takes more than five hours, but so does the alternative so-called high speed route via Paris.
    Then I had another week or so in La Vergne, during which there was much wind and tempest,
    sufficient to uproot one of the two mighty walnut trees in the back garden. It fell on top of
    Patrice's recently erected fence, which is probably why he seemed to take a gloomy delight in
    reducing it to a heap of logs over the next few days. I then retraced my railway steps as far as
    Tours where I yet again taught the ever popular <ref
     target="2025_Programme_Formation_TEI_Initiation_2025_DEF.pdf">"TEI Niveau 1"</ref> from the
    27th to the 29th, before returning once more back to London and Bristol on the 30th. </p>
   <p> From the 6th to the 8th of <label>November</label> I stayed in one of the many cheapish
    minimalist hotels around Kings Cross. The occasion was a <ref
     target="https://rs4vp.org/pictorial-punch-treasures-from-the-archive/">"study day"</ref> hosted
    by the British Library on the 7th, where I met and tried to impress some Victorian Studies
    glitterati. Organised jointly with the Caen Punch Project, the day involved much discussion of
    Punch visuals and some interesting snippets of background history, notably my first encounter
    with Patrick Leary and Henry Silver's diary. BL staff were on strike, but still supplied masses
    of fairly horrid sandwiches. And at the end of the month, I yet again popped over to Caen by
    Eurostar, this time for the MRSH Scientific Committee. But this was my last expedition of the
    year: I did not proceed from there to La Vergne, and was back in Bristol for the 22nd. </p>
   <p> Which was just as well, since on the 5th <label>December</label>, L fell over in mysterious
    circumstances on the way home, fracturing her clavicule, Which meant that almost all amusements
    planned for December had to be cancelled. On the plus side, I got to know the route to and from
    the BRI rather well; the NHS was wonderful; and we were still able to have an extensive Xmas
    lunch with Elizabeth and co, plus a boxing day amusement at Sarah's house with everyone except
    the Nottingham family branch, who did however come to join us for New Years eve.</p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
