<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>What I did in my holidays, 2025</title>
    <author/>
   </titleStmt>

   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Written by OpenOffice revised in oxygen</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <listChange>
    <change>
     <date>2025-05-25T23:07:35.784350255</date>
    </change>
   </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div>
    <head>What I did in my Holidays: A tale of three locations</head>

    <head>Also featuring my adventures with Cyclone Garance</head>

    <div type="div1" rend="P9">
     <head>Getting There</head>
     <p><label>Saturday 8th February 2025.</label> The Uber was on time, though nothing else was.
      The Flix bus to Gatwick, driven by a harassed Italian, left 15 minutes late and got later as
      it made the really dull slog to Heathrow, all terminals, and eventually Gatwick S, where it
      arrived 30 minutes late. Then some real waiting made even longer by am unexplained 90 minute
      delay in departure for our flight, which finally boarded around 21h10 instead of 19h35, and
      then proceeded to sit on the runway for another 30 minutes sorting out some mechanical
      problems. Sigh. Tried fitfully to snooze for the next 12 hours. Some hopes. We arrived Mru two
      hours later than expected, but the taxi is waiting for us somewhere, and so are the two SIMs I
      have sensibly pre-ordered. Off we go for a very long ride across the island to Pereybere. Our
      driver is aged and seems a bit deaf or we are not really awake yet. Our hotel is on the main
      street through Pereybere opposite the bus stop, and a beach restaurant complete today with
      Chinese dragons dancing to celebrate our arrival. Also fire crackers, since it’s Feb 9th and
      therefore somebody's public holiday. Our hotel has a nice atrium, with carp and the room is
      comfortable, though the electricity is a bit dodgy. Mine frites and tasty freshly made
      boulettes from seemingly the only restaurant that’s open today, install SIMs and retired to
      bed to sleep for many hours.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="div1" rend="P9">
     <head>Being there (1)</head>
     <p>The Pereybere Hotel and Spa is directly opposite a nice beach where one may sit under the
      filaos and enjoy the breeze. Occasional excursion by bus to Grande Baie and beyond even to
      Pointe aux Piments. Fairly routine Mauritian luncheons. Nice breakfasts. Dodgy electrics. </p>
     <p><label>Monday 10th. </label> Both sims working, I think. Excellent breakfast at hotel: lots
      of choice though coffee is a bit dubious. We walked to Winners supermarket and bought milk,
      hats, sandals to deal with immediate concerns. Heart problems from accumulated stree I think.
      Rested 20 mins, then went to sat on beach solus, enjoying the breeze in the trees, A late
      overpriced lunch at the japanese resto down the road. Nice coffee and cakes at cakeshop.
      Sitting on a bench you will always make friends. I chatted to a builder from Reunion; L
      chatted to a Malgache lady selling vanilla pods.</p>
     <p><label>Tu, Wed, Thu, Fri, Sat...</label> Most mornings, L got up for pre-breakfast exercises, so
      we arrived late for breakfast and gawped at other guests. Occasionally went on a bus
      excursion, e.g. to a coiffeuse in Grand Baie. We tried most eating places in the street for
      lunch. And slowly relaxed into holiday mood.</p>

    </div>
    <div type="div1" rend="P9">
     <head>Being There (2)</head>
     <p><label>Sun 16 Mar</label>We took an expensive taxi part way across the island to Curepipe, more pfrecisely to The Bobateau Building, so named, I assume, because its ground floor is devoted
      to the sale of fancy model ships. Above this, however, there are several spacious if minimally
      furnished flats joined by lots of wearisom concrete staircases. Our flat was regrettably on the third floor, but with a balcony from which we
      watched fruit bats in the neighbouring fruit trees, and also much traffic, since it is on a
      busy road, formerly known as Sir John Pope Henessy Avenue, but now renamed Daruty de Grandpere
      Avenue, presumably in an outburst of anti-colonial fervour. Extinct volcano Trou aux Cerfs is
      near by, as is the Sir Sewoosagur Ramgoolam Botanical Garden, and a functioning bakery. And
      it's only a short walk to the cosmopolitan delights of downtown Curepipe, notably the
      splendidly eclectic Sik Yuen supermarket, the dead posh boutiques of the Curepipe Arcades
      shopping centre, and of course the market place. We cooked for ourselves a bit once we’d
      located all these, and we also eventually found how to get to Roger's house without getting
      completely lost despite extensive study of Google maps. We did a lot of queuing in banks as is
      traditional (see <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/21days.html">previous
      reports</ref>). We also observed lots of people celebrating Hindu festival <ref
       target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maha_Shivaratri">Maha Shivaratri</ref> in various ways:
      trundling gaily decorated idols on hand carts through the centre of Curepipe, with  pre-recorded
      musical accompaniment; or just putting up virtue-signalling notices wishing us "a pious festival".
      There was quite a gathering overnight in the Botanic Gardens in specially constructed
      decorative shelters from the rain, not to mention free food. All rather jolly. Roger
      celebrated his 80th birthday by inviting us all out to his favourite chinese restaurant for
      dinner, and also laid on lunch at his house for us a couple of times. All in all, though,
      Curepipe is a bit too much like real life to count as a holiday, though I did a fair bit of
      pottering around its curious byways and highways, getting rained on more than strictly
      necessary. </p><p><label>27 March</label>Eventually, as news of the approach of cyclone Garance became daily more
      insistent, we resolved to get out of there and stay somewhere a bit more touristy for our last
      tropical week. Naturally we chose to do this on a  day when all forms of transport were strictly prohibited.
       </p>
    </div>
    <div type="div1" rend="P9">
     <head>Being There (3)</head>
     <p>Our chosen hotel in Mahebourg, where we stayed many years ago (December 2006, to be
      precise) has since acquired a fancy swimming pool as well as a new name (the "Chill Pill", sic) . To get there
      this time, we had to defy cyclone Garance by taking an illegal taxi, but it was worth the
      effort: we were greeted by an excellent biryani served, exceptionally. on account of the
      weather. When Garance calmed down a bit, we watched boats in the bay and enjoyed being
      hedonistic tourists again. I splashed about in the pool with fellow guests from Quebec and
      from California. Roger, Alain, Olive and Roger’s current garage boy Sebastian came to visit
      one day, and we drank beers, though alas not many. Quantum mutatus ab illo. </p>

    </div>
    <div type="div1" rend="P14">
     <head>All about the Tropical Depression</head>
     <p>For those with neither knowledge nor access to Google, a tropical cyclone is a large area of
      atmospheric craziness in which the wind blows at a high speed of 3 or 4 hundred km per hour
      but in a circular motion, causing havoc in areas beneath. This area changes as the cyclone
      moves along a path usually correctly predicted by clever data modelling techniques. Like other
      scary things, once identified, a cyclone is allocated a girl’s name by the meteorological
      authority on whose beat they are first detected. Garance seems to have originated near
      Madagascar, about 500 km NW of Mauritius (see map) but moved south over the next 36 hours,
      missing Mauritius by a whisker, but passing directly over Reunion island, where she caused the
      deaths of four foolish reunionnais who had presumably ignored governmental injunctions to stay
      indoors. In Mauritius, Curepipe was mostly cloudy and rainy as usual, but even so a truly
      spectacular tropical storm built up over the 48 hours during which Garance passed us by. There
      were sudden gusts of wind which made the trees buckle, and squalls of rain more dramatic than
      usual. Then there was a lowering sky and a government warning to stay indoors and on no
      account go to sea. The airport closed. All the shops (except bakers) closed as well. Taxi
      drivers were reluctant to set out on uninsured journeys. </p>
     <p>Nevertheless, we managed to get the promise of a ride from someone working for “Yugo” a
      Mauritian Uber-clone. And so on 27th March, cyclone warning level 3 in force, we shut up our
      unloved Curepipe residence in the Bobato Building and went up and down its horrible staircase
      numerous times to transfer or dispose of our chattels. And were then driven with exemplary
      skill along 90% empty motorways, and past a silent airport, to a seaside bolt hole in
      Mahebourg on the other side of the island. The winds continued to blow and the waves were
      fierce, breaking over the hotel sea wall in fact. Occasional thunder storms erupted to mark
      Garance’s displeasure at our insouciance, followed of course by lots of torrential rain,
      rendering almost impossible a simple walk up the road to the cash machine, round the corner
      from the taximen’s mosque. And then as abruptly as she had come, Garance evaporated into the
      deep south of the Indian ocean. The water reservoirs of Mauritius glugged up the storm waters
      thankfully, and after a bit of cloud and breeze, the sun came out again and we tourists
      sported ourselves once more in hotel pools and in markets both super and traditional, across
      the region. It remains windy today but the sky is clear and the temperature well over 26.
      Shame to leave really, but BA2064 is expecting us, on 2nd March...</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
