<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="boyle">
<head>Camp Conflicts </head>
<bibl>Descent of Man by T. Coraghessan Boyle. (Gollancz, 1980)</bibl>
<p>
There is a facile nastiness about many stories in this small collection which
can be intended only hypothetically to outrage. In truth, of course, we are all
far too urbane to be moved by such hackneyed situations as the anthropologist's
wife having it away with an ape, the skies raining first blood and then shit on
n houseful of happy hippies, an astronaut first farting and then masturbating in
zero gravity, to say nothing of the various spiders ("as big as a two egg
omelette") which turn up with surprising regularity within these pages. Faced
with the high (low?) camp of an eating contest described in a sickening amalgam
of American menu-ese and Harry Carpenter at his most poetic, the correct
reaction is all too predictable: my, my, Mr Boyle is indeed a "master of black
humour" and "genially disillusioned about the human condition" — it says so,
right here on the blurb. (Even for a blurb writer, even in these godless days,
that juxtaposition of disillusionment and geniality might perhaps have given
some occasion for hesitation, but let it pass). Such stuff is best dealt with in
a rigorously scientific manner, as it is evidently concocted. What oppositions
then are mediated by these tales? Hell, of course, we have those good old bogies
of modern American writing - dirt, blood, vomit etc. versus plastic forks,
deodorants etc (Descent of man, Blood fall, Green Hell, Earth—Moon); we have
-curse them for their intractable otherness- Women versus Us Chaps (A women’s
restaurant, John Barleycorn Lives, Drowning); we have The Media versus Reality —
a very one—sided affair with Reality hardly getting a look in (Heart of a
champion, Dada, De rerum natura, Second swimming). In this last category
particularly mock bathos (deflation) slides with ironic frequency into the
genuine article (sinking) so that the response is a genuine groan. The
juxtaposition of General Idi Amin Dada with the posturing of contemporary New
York dadaists might have been funny as a passing thought, but I do not think
anyone now finds General Amin amusing. Equally, The Second Swimming might have
been bearable as a Monty Python one-liner; as it is, a Chairman Mao who plans to
have "wieners with Grey Poupon mustard for breakfast" and exhorts his barber to
"buff the pate" is merely silly. The same sub-Perelman smartness mars an
otherwise exemplary evocation of comic book Norsemen; when their leader sums up
the newly—discovered Newfoundland with the crisp and novel aphorism "That
place'll never amount to a hill of beans" this reader at least is not as
convulsed as might have been desired. Stylistically I would place Mr Boyle
amongst the Creative Writing school of modern prose masters. His text
corruscates equally with verbless sentences, flat similes and brand names, set
in a timeless continuum of present indicatives. Two stories deserve exception
from this blanket condemnation however, both (I think) at least partially
intended to parody greater masters of the form. Quetzacoatl Lite (though marred
by the same sort of silliness as Horsemen) recalls Borges or Nabokov in its
gallant attempt at conveying the inner workings of an obsessive collector, while
John Barleycorn is dead is oddly reminiscent of the later Kipling in its hearty
celebration of the great practical joke. By and large however, the closest Mr
Boyle comes to expressing an opinion is in the pseudo-Vonnegutese of The
extinction tales. "What's a species here, a species there? This is where
extinction becomes sublime." Sublime extinction? What is the world coming to?

[3 june]
</p></div>
