<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="conway">
<head>[Review published in ALLC Bulletin 1980]</head>
<bibl>Richard Conway and James Archer, <title>Programming for Poets: a Gentle
Introduction using FORTRAN with WATFIV</title> (Cambridge, Mass:
Winthrop Publishers, 1978)</bibl>


<p>One has the impression reading this book that the authors
would really rather have written quite a different one. Their
goal, set out explicitly in the preface, is not to help the
reader to write his own programs, but 'to achieve an
understanding of the programming process'. No one would quarrel
with their assertion that 'computing has a special
responsibility to explain itself to the layman', nor with the
good intentions apparent in their attempts to demystify that
omnipresent bogey-thing the computer. Nevertheless,
misconceptions and prejudice are rarely removed by half-truths
and over-simplifications: on the contrary. It is quite true
(even obvious) that computer error should be blamed on the
programmer more often than the machine, that computer held
databanks present opportunities for abuse of civil liberties
unparalleled in history, that problems which cannot be stated
algorithmically (probably) cannot be solved by computation and
that machine translation is not as easy as it looks. Whether
such startling aperçus form an adequate basis for a proper
understanding of what computer programming is and where it is
going is more debatable.
</p>
<p>Character manipulation in FORTRAN has been compared to
shelling peas in boxing gloves; a simile which nicely conveys
the frustrations of using the wrong tool for the job, if not
exactly the nature of the difficulties. Apologists for the
language fall into two irreconcileable camps - the
extensionists, who point to the existence of various dialects of
the language more or less well-suited to tasks for which FORTRAN
was never intended, and the classicists, whose argument is
essentially that ANSI FORTRAN is and always will be the nearest
thing we have to a programming lingua franca. Some apologists
(including, I fear, the present authors) try to have a foot in
both camps, which clearly will not do. The language used
throughout this book is a subset of FORTRAN IV, as implemented
by the WATFIV compiler. The merits and demerits of this
particular one apart, it seems somewhat unfair to present it to
the novice as at all typical of the sort of FORTRAN compiler he
is likely to encounter in his local computing centre. Some of
the characteristics of the subset used can be applauded -
explicit declaration of all variables, for example; others seem
eccentric - particularly the relegation of any consideration of
the nature and purpose of subroutines to a page in the appendix,
along with such essential elements of the programming art as how
to operate an IBM 026 keypunch (two pages).</p>
<p>The first section of the book takes the novice carefully through
such essential concepts as variables, loops, conditionals,
substrings, and arrays (here confusingly called lists). Because the goal
here is to explain everything, some distracting details peculiar to
WATFIV (e.g. the representation of quote characters quoted
literals) or to FORTRAN (e.g. the construction of DO loops) are
given prominence, but the basic pedagogic method is sound and
could profitably be used in any introductory programming course. The
remainder of the book, in which the more elaborate programs are
presented, is inevitably more sketchy. By choosing the simplest
algorithm, rather than the most appropriate, they run the risk of
setting budding programmers some very bad examples. The chapters on
concordance programs, statistical programs, and information
retrieval, for example, all use methods which no one would consider
appropriate in the real world. The authors are not unaware of this, and
caution the student to that effect, but this is no excuse for not
having done the job properly to start with. Typical of the
superficiality of this approach is the random number generator
presented without comment on page 196. Disregarding the misprint in the
code (which is guaranteed to blow up the most tolerant of compilers),
the function is presented with no explanation of how it works - in
particular with no warning that it will only work on machines which
store integers as 32-bit words!
</p>
<p>This book contains much that is praiseworthy. It covers a lot of
ground, is understandable and well written. It cannot however be
recommended to anyone who really wants to learn how to program, nor
even to anyone who wants to know what programming really is. The
preface glosses the use of the word 'poets' in the title as arising
from the practice of dedicating 'the least technical
introductory version of a subject "to poets" '. I hope someone more
gifted than I will be inspired to rebuff this slur on the intelligence
of the followers of Apollo.</p>
<trailer>L.D. Burnard
University of Oxford
</trailer></div>

