<div source="#r8009TLS" facs="pages:1980-emerson.jpg" xml:id="emerson" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<head>Set authors</head>
<head>By L.D. Burnard</head>
<bibl>SALLY EMERSON :<title> Second Sight</title>240pp. Michael Joseph. £6.50. 0 7181 1965 7 </bibl>
<p> Jennifer’s mum Sarah, is no better then she should be. Her dad, Edward, tends to wear socks that
don’t match. This is because he is a successful author and donnish, while she runs a fashionable
restaurant and is sluttish. They met, we are told twice, at Oxford, where she attended a secretarial
college and he (presumably) the other sort. Such miscegenation can obviously come to no good. The
child of their union. whose transition from O-levels to A-levels this novel documents is a
withdrawn, shy adolescent given to fantasy and equally hopeless at games and at chatting up boys.
Her fantasies centre on <q>dear Rebecca</q>, a somewhat Wordsworthian contemporary killed in a road
accident, on Aphra Behn, the subject of her father’s latest book, here treated as a sort of <hi>Ur</hi>-
Germaine Greer, and on that well- known mainstay of female adolescence P. B. Shelley. These three
imagined presences serve Jennifer as faithfully as many lesser children are served by their teddy
bears; at first idolized, then used as touchstones (for self, female, male respectively), they
ﬁnally dwindle in stature to be finally discarded at the appropriate stage in her developing
understanding of Life and Love. </p>
<p> With the aid of the friendly old spiritualist gentleman across the square and her own psychic
powers, Jennifer plans a grand display in which her private trinity will materialize before her
astounded father and demonstrate her power <q>to defeat time and decay and death</q>, but curiously
little of this design is achieved. In the sordid world of grown-ups two sub-plots are hatching—one a
murder story, one a love story. Linking the two is a personable young architect called Paul,
apparently the same age as Jennifer but also her mother’s lover. Paul has as disastrous an effect on
all the ladies with whom he comes into contact as did the young Shelley, and, not to labour the
analogies— which with an author as intelligent as Ms Emerson are particularly demure - is also just
as much of a rotter. This novel is hardly a who-dunnit, but it would spoil what suspense does exist
to reveal either the details of his caddishness or its unexpected—indeed barely credible
—consequences in the lives of Jennifer and her parents. Suffice it to note the irony illustrated in
the resolution of the novel: that a fantasy fulfilled is no longer a fantasy. </p>
<p> The murder itself is somewhat gratuitous as murders go —much discussed but little realised. It
does, however, serve as a means of introducing a pleasantly satirical portrait of a greasily
succcessful barrister and his oppressed wife, the Pumblechook pomposity of his dialogue as neatly
caught as her nervous glove-twitching and obsessive house-hunting. </p>
<p> The novel id set somewhere in fashinoable Westmister where taxis are taken as freely as lovers
and whisky and Chablis flow at dusk and dinner respectively. But more insistent than these details
are those of the city itself: the reality of trees, of historic buildings, of swans in public parks,
in comparison with the flotsam and jetsam of humanity swirling around them. Sally Emerson also has a
fondness for pithy similes: <q>He peered at Jennifer's glass of water with an air of trepidation, like
a car examining a saucer of milk laid down by a stranger.</q> Perhaps because so much of the novel is
seen through Jennifer's sharp gaze, it is unusually rich in observations of colour and costume
(almost obsessively in the case of costume) and of nuances of mood and emotion, particularly those
of adolescence. By comparison the introspections of the other characters seem rather lifeless. The
novel has not anything new to tell us about youth and age, love and selfishness, dreams and reality.
But it is done with such calm authority and delicate wit that one hopes Sally Emerson's next will
display her evident talent at work with more demanding subject matter. </p>
</div>
