<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="farringdon">
    <head>FARRINGDON, MICHAEL AND FARRINGDON, JILL <title>A computer-aided study of the prose style
            of Henry Fielding and its support for his translation of the Military History of Charles
            XII.</title> [In Advances in computer-aided literacy and linguistic research D.E. Ager,
        F.E. Knowles, and Joan Smith (eds). Dept of Modern Languages, Univ of Aston, Birmingham. UK,
        1979, 95 -105. See main entry CR 20. 11 (Nov 1979), 35.349.]</head>
    <p> This modest study of some patterns of usage characteristic of Fielding‘s prose relies on no
        statistical model more esoteric than common sense and makes no claims to universal
        appllcnability. As such it is a welcome breath of fresh air in the somewhat heated
        atmosphere of statistical stylistics. In his own lifetime Fielding's style was thought
        eccentric enough to he worth parodying. and this study demonstrates that many of the
        features parodied are indeed more frequent in Fielding than in a small group of contemporary
        “control" texts. Modern critics have been less successful in identifying the quintessentialy
        Fieldingesque usage when they have relied on impressionistic data rather than on
        computer-generated concordances. The Farringdons identify several phrases or constructions.
        not in themsleves particularly unusual or topic-dependent which are preferred to near
        synonymous phrases consistently more often throughout the Fielding texts than in the
        "control“ texts. With no underlying statistical model of word-distribution however. they
        make no attempt to assess the significance of these differences. The paper closes with an
        examination of an anonymous translation. attributed on external evidence to Fielding, in
        which the value of these “Fielding-usages“ is further demonstrated. Different phrases in the
        original French are all translated by the same “preferred usage." The authors conclude that
        the translation can conﬁdently be attributed to Fielding. However their argument would
        perhaps be more persuasive it some steps had been taken to compensate their observed
        frequencies for sample-bias. The genuine Fielding texts examined total over three times as
        many words as the "control“ sample. which must at least partially invalidate anv argument
        based on frequency alone. </p>
    <trailer> L. D. Burnard. Oxford. UK</trailer>
</div>
