<div source="#r8008TLS" 
    facs="pages:1980-cochrane.jpg" xml:id="cochrane" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<head>Growing up in Ulster</head>
<byline>By Louis Burnard </byline>
<bibl>IAN COCHRANE: <title>F for Ferg</title> 117 pp.
Gollancz. £5.95. 0 575 02862 9 </bibl>
<p> Readers of Ian Cochrane's last novel, Ladybird in a Loony Bin (1978), may be a little
disappointed to find that in this, his latest, he has returned as if obsessivelv to the subject
matter and milieu of his first three successes. Has the man but one tale in him (they may testily
enquire)—are we to get nothing from him but the joys and miseries of growing pains in Ulster,
shaded by poverty and madness? A novelist is allowed to retell his unspeakable youth in his first
novel, and maybe even his second, but surely by his fifth he should have found something new to
say? </p>
<p> Even such readers will, however, concede that Mr Cochrane's skill has not changed but rather
strengthened over the years; it is (if possible) more energetic in its apprehension of living
detail, more exact in its mirroring of the cadencies of dialogue, more witty in its unexpected
juxtaposition of tense and mood, more affecting in its presentation of innocence. To capture the
distinctive ﬂavour of a culturally deprived vernacular is no mean feat; to give it a cutting edge
and vitality as Cochrane does is something else again. It is a power which more than makes up for a
certain perfunctoriness in the plot. </p>
<p> Ferg is for Fergus who is new to the village, and the manager's son. As if that were not enough
he wears a red waistcoat with gold buttons and it suspected of being a Norwegian fruit merchant.
Doggedly attempting to integrate himself with the peasantry, he is prone to such remarks as “There
is something natural about you. You don’t have to think. You use instincts. You’re real." This novel
charts with remorseless precision Fergus's painful induction to the youthful sports of chasing
girls, rioting in the dole queue and hanging around street corners. It also charts without
mawkishness the maturing of its narrator, Johnny, who differs from other Cochranesque narrators
chiefly in that he achieves an understanding of compassion for himself rather than learning through
the example of others. There is no deus ex machina comparable to the policeman at the end of
<title>Ladybird in a Loony Bin</title>; there are no painfully nice next-door neighbours as in <title>Gone in the Head</title>;
there is no tower of strength like the teacher in <title>A Streak of Madness</title>. </p>
<p>This gives this novel a seriousness lacking in earlier ones, a seriousness demonstrated also by
the comparative lack of incidental comic detail. Characters such as the village Poet, and incidents
such as the village dance at which Fergus is tricked into undressing himself, are more sparingly
described than might have been anticipated. It is as if the author were deliberately restraining his
imagination, particularly in the novel's closing pages. There is nothing of the solemn social
documentary in it, thank heavens, yet this novel gives a more honest account of that Northern
Ireland we hear of occasionally — the one where 15 per cent of the population subsists on the dole —
than many others more ostensibly serious or less ostensibly comic. </p>
</div>
