<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="urquhart">
<head>Trauchle in the but and ben </head>
<bibl>A diver in China seas by Fred Urquhart. (Quartet, 1980, #6.50)</bibl>
<p>
Fred Urquhart has produced four novels and countless short stories since 1936,
as well as having edited such volumes as Great True Escape Stories and a cartoon
biography of Winston Churchill. His tales, of which this is the latest volume,
have been broadcast on what I suspect he would call the wireless and translated
into several European languages. The former achievement, if not the latter,
seems peculiarly apposite for a writer so irretrievably wedded as he to the use
of Scots dialect. As a mere sassenach, I must confess that I find a trifle
indigestible such sentences as "Harry was unemployed at the time and there
wasn’t room in our pokey wee but and ban for both him and me" or "Elspeth
McDOugall was finding life a bit of a trauchle" when encountered in cold print,
which indigestion is further compounded in this volume by an occasional confusion of
narrative voices. About half of the stories are told in the first person, where
dialect seems appropriate, but of the remainder only one or two employ a neutral
narrator. ’A camp follower’ for example is only sporadically told through the
eyes of its heroine, a luckless Scots lassie trammelled up in the Napoleonic
wars. Its diction wobbles uncertainly between Mrs Oliphant ("They would comfort
each other for youth’s eternal longing and loneliness on the banks of springy
turf beneath Salisbury Crags") and Robbie Burns ("Willem was a big sonsy
fine-looking lad ... He was a likeable cratur’, cheery and gallus"), before
plumping finally for Georgette Heyer with the arrival on the scene of one
Francisco Goya, just in time to save our heroine from the garotte. ("Even though
he’d painted her without a stitch on, Senor Goya had aye behaved like a perfect
gentleman"). This sort of purple-streaked tartan is quite rare in the other
tales, I am glad to say, but there remain several in which a carefully
established dialect narrator fights for control of the tale with a bland
characterless one. The narrator of ’Like arrows in the hands of God’ for example
might initially be taken for one of the gossips at Mrs Rintoul’s, but is also
allowed to be privy to Jessie’s mind.
</p><p>
Several of the stories turn, like this one, on the relation between mistress and
maidservant and are concerned with that peculiarly concentrated spitefulness of
which elderly ladies are often both victim and agent. The main characters are
nearly all women of a certain age - Urquhart’s men are invariably typecast as
bullying fathers, sentimental lovers or conceited boys - and the narratives
nearly all chronicle a remorseless decline. A favourite theme is a modern
variant on the Ubi sunt which might be called the Generation Gap Game.
’Nostalgia for a Waltz Dream’, for example, begins with a slanging match between
Mrs Nance McQueen and her daughter brought on by rock and roll, and then shifts
by way of flashback (a favourite Urquhart device) to slanging matches between
Nance and her father brought on by silent movies. Back in the present, Nance
muses "If only Jean would be a sensible lassie and give up all this rockin’ and
rollin’ dirt and go to the pictures instead". But the opposition is unbalanced,
for the tale ends with what the narrator describes as "the moaning of a glottal-stopped moron rendering
a rock ’n’ roll number". This partisanship spoils what is for me (perhaps
because I like rock and roll and silent movies) its point - the structurally
identical role the two play in the parent-child relation. But what should bring
Nance and her daughter together, Urquhart prefers to make separate them. A much
slighter tale, ’Auld Mother Claus’ similarily turns on the mutual dislike of
grandmother and grandchildren, but is more successful in its dialogue, while the
three generations in ’Dusty Springtime’ are juxtaposed in a more profitable way,
with the grand daughter’s prim disapproval of her grandmother’s eye for the
"laddies", one of whom happens to be the mother’s current "beau".
</p><p>
Urquhart’s real interest seems to be the passing of time, not surprisingly in an
octogenarian. "Now that I feel death’s cauld hand crawling over me every night I
keep turning my mind to the corpses I’ve seen in my day" the narrator of the
title story in this collection begins; there is a dour delight evident
throughout in the detailing of the little miseries of bourgeois family life as
its participants gradually decline from insistant respectability to unspeakable
senility. There are no Joycean epiphanies here. Instead life is a long process
of grim survival. Thus in the longest tale, ’Princess McDonald’, the
inconsequential details - the hours and wages of the Princess’s occupations, her
favourite songs and music hall stars, her fur coats- are the only relief in her
drab descent. Having married a Canadian she spends a long life moving restlessly
between Canada and Scotland, becoming that most pitiable of beings, a tourist.
The tale has a sureness of diction and a wealth of circumstantial detail that
carry conviction, if not enthusiasm; equally impressive, though in a different
way, is the first story in this collection ’Pilgrimages to the old Manse’. This
I take to be mildly satirical of those notorious literary ladies of Auld Reekie,
whose tones are exactly mirrored in the narrator’s. "My poor husband, who
practically never opens a book, except a third rate adventure story, and who
thinks Raymond Chandler is high brow". The poor husband is also a Baronet while
she is a "jumped-up wee keelie who’d got too big for her boots". The idolised
author to whose Manse the pilgrimages are made, turns out to have been "a silly
woman without a thought in her head" and her admired works the product of her
maid servant. In a sense, I suppose, that is vindication enough for the use of
dialect throughout the book.

</p></div>
