<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="schafer">
<head>
Jurgen Schafer, <title>Documentation in the OED. Shakespeare and Nashe as
Test Cases</title> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980).
</head>
<p>There is a deceptively modest air about this book which should not be
allowed to detract from its significance. Its chief aim is to
determine the reliability of the Oxford English Dictionary (hereafter
OED) as a description of the history of the English language. Its
method is to examine the factors causing the evident disparity between
the vocabularies of Shakespeare and Nashe as recorded in the OED and
as derived from more modern sources (Spevack's concordance in the case
of Shakespeare, McKerrow's edition in the case of Nashe). An attempt
is made to estimate the degree of error present in the dating of
lemmata in the OED and also the variation in the type of error
present. In this task, Professor Schafer sets an example which
scholars in quite different fields would do well to emulate, both in
the thoroughness of his analysis and the pellucid and undaunting
manner in which the numerical side of his case is presented.
</p>
<p>Rather more than half of the book is taken up with lists of
antedatings, (that is, words found in works searched by the OED's
editors which are dated earlier than the date assigned the words in
the published dictionary) found by Schafer's assiduous research team
in the works of Shakespeare, Nashe, Malory, and Wyatt. It is not clear
to me quite what audience these lists are intended for; of far more
use to the reader of the remainder of the book are the summary
statistical tables which precede them. The whole force of Schafer's
argument is, after all, that quantification of variability is more
significant than its specification.
</p>
<p>This study attempts to detect patterns of variability and to
postulate causes for them rather than simply to cite endless
variations (as is too often the tendency of historical
linguists). Thus, having established a measure of'authorial
reliability' (the ratio between the number of first usages recorded
for a given author in the OED and the sum of that number and the
number of antedatings for the same author), Schafer is careful to
discuss such related matters as the degree of antedating involved, the
alphabetic distribution of antedatings, their corpus frequency or even
their syntactic category. It seems that 30 percent of the QED's
lemmata are 50 or more years misdated, while 7 percent — a mere 16,000
words — are over a century out. It is fascinating to discover that over
two-thirds of these antedatings occur in the first half of the
Dictionary, reflecting the gradual improvements in techniques and
tools available during the course of its production. Schafer has no
explanation however for the OED's editors' apparent tendency to
overlook participial adjectives other than what in a pleasing phrase
he calls the 'morphological inconspicuousness' of such words.
</p>
<p>Most significant is the relationship between the reliability rate
and the size of the corpus available for searching.  The early editors
of the OED appear to have had a conscious policy of extracting every
word from major authors, but being more selective from minor
writers. It seems that the common wisdom, which attributes an
extraordinary linguistic creativity to the Shakespearian period, is at
least partly a consequence of the lemmatisation policy of the OED's
first editors, itself to some extent conditioned by the greater
availability of texts from that period.
</p>
<p>The purpose of this book is not of course to claim that
diachronic analyses based directly on the OED are worthless.  Rather
it sets out to establish sampling techniques and other methods of
analysis by which that great treasure house can be used more
effectively, to identify its limitations and correct its
deficiencies. As Schafer concludes, despite recent advances in
computer-based lexicography, <q>in the area of historical documentation
we can expect nothing in the foreseeable future as comprehensive or as
accurate</q>.
</p>
<trailer>L.D. Burnard
Oxford University Computing Service
</trailer></div>






