<div facs="pages:1983-burnham.jpg" xml:id="burnham" source="#r8311TLS" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<head> Into the dreaded database </head>
<byline> L. D. Burnard </byline>
<bibl>DAVID BURNHAM The Rise of the Computer State: A Chilling Account of the Computer‘s Threat to
Society 273pp. Weidenfeld and Nicolson. £10.95. 0 207 7x30: 5</bibl>
<p> Every time an American policeman makes an arrest, the luckless offender's details are
immortalized in the FBI‘s distributed database. Every time an American citizen makes a telephone
call, uses a credit card or even (soon) transfers money from one bank account to another. a new
record is added to some other database. Every time he or she becomes embroiled with a government
agency, be it the Inland Revenue Service, the Social Security Administration, the Department of
Labor or whoever, a database somewhere records the fact. Should this upset us? </p>
<p> Bureaucracies have always collected data obsessively. and no doubt always will. But the coming
of the computer has changed both the scope of the data collected and the ease with which they may be
processed almost beyond recognition. In Dickens‘s Circumlocution Office the grand principle was
<q>How not to do it</q>; now that magnetic tape and disc replace red tape and paper. satirists begin
to fear that it may in fact be done all too easily. The computer sold to us as a liberator from
toil. may become the instrument of oppression. giving the prying administrators and officious busy
bodies of the Welfare State rather more access to our private affairs than we anticipated. </p>
<p> But this threat needs either more careful analysis or more effective presentation than David
Burnham gives it here if it is to be perceived as a real threat and not just as the pro- duct of a
liberal paranoia. Even so. the book is a gold mine of anecdotal information guaranteed to break the
ice at Civil Rights gatherings. A company called TRW, for example, now offers a service to thousands
of American credit companies whereby, in return for contribut- ing records of their own customers‘
transactions, clients can check those of all TRW‘s other clients This seems a neat way of ensuring
that a bad debt incurred in Illinois can't disappear when its perpetrator moves to Arkan- sas, but
it is less impressive if the Illinois records are inaccurate or not up to date. Accord- ing to
Burnham. TRW receive annually over 350,000 complaints about the accuracy of the information they
supply; only a third of these complaints ever lead to a change in the database largely because of
the expense of validat- ing the huge amounts of data involved. Even the criminal records
administered by the FBI have a similar margin of error. for similar reasons. So inaccurate are they
in fact that apparently the police no longer use them - instead the dubious data are sold to
prospective employers checking up on candidates for interview. </p>
<p> Burnham, an investigative journalist who won his spurs uncovering police corruption for the
<title>New York Times</title>, is quick to stress the possibilities such databases offer for misuse.
He is particularly concerned about the surveillance activities of America‘s National Security
Agency. and with good cause now that executive orders from President Reagan have apparently extended
the purview of this institution to include the whole American people. Ever since the Enigma machine,
computers and military intelligence have existed in an uneasy symbiosis, the development of the one
both determined by and dependent upon the needs and capabilities of the other. The NSA apparently
uses computers on a grander scale than any other single institution on earth. One indication of the
range of its operations is the quantity of waste paper it produces. According to Burnham, anyone
hoping to sell the NSA a suitably secure shredder ten years ago had to be able to cope with over
thirty-six tons of classified waste every working day. </p>
<p> Aside from anecdote. the book attempts to discuss something called <q>Values</q>. It may or may
not be the case that the widespread use of systems analysis is detrimental to proper health care; it
certainly is the case that there is a parallel between a society's culture (its way of looking at
itself) and its technology (its way of looking at what is not itself) though this is not quite what
Burnham has in mind when he bemoans the narrowing of possibilities, the heart- lessness of machines
and what he considers the indecency of modelling human activity in mechanistic terms. There is
nothing here about the beneﬁts that accrue from the availability of information to a benevolent and
skilled administration; perhaps. after Watergate, Amer- icans no longer believe in benevolent
Administrations. There is nothing here (apart from a token gesture to the importance of epidemiology
in identifying the causes of cancer) about the uses of computer databases in research. There is
nothing on computer fraud. which probably poses a far greater threat to society than any amount of
NSA cloak-and-dagger stuff. Equally, the book underplays the extent to which the computer is
becoming demythologized. </p>
<p> Burnham is at his best when sticking to the facts, and when, for example. he is charting the
tangled path by which this or that piece of legislation has succeeded or failed on Capitol Hill. his
prose has a grim fascination all of its own. We may not like it. but it rings true in a way that his
imaginative passages (mercifully confined to one acutely embarrassing chapter called <q>A
Future</q>) do not. </p>
</div>
