<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="large">
<head><title>The devil's circuitry</title>
TLS <date>14 Dec 1984 </date>,p
1444 </head>
<bibl>Peter Large <title>The Micro Revolution Revisited </title> 0-8476-7361-8; </bibl>
<bibl>Michael Shallis <title>The Silicon Idol: the micro revolution and its social
implications</title> 0-19-215877-5</bibl>  
           
<p>In the last 25 years the computer has been transformed from a mysterious
piece of scientific apparatus attended by serious men in white coats
into a suitable gift for precocious eight year olds.  It has achieved
the status of a consumer durable, becoming a mark of social standing
without which no decent home is complete.  Unlike the washing machine or
the home video however it has also completely transformed the working
environment and even (for those who still have any) the nature of work
itself.  Its indiscriminate reorganisation of every aspect of economic
activity has not come about overnight, nor yet is it complete, but the
rate of change is increasing.
</p>
<p>For Peter Large who, as technology correspondent for the Guardian must
be -as it were- in touch with the leading edge, the home computer is
only the most conspicuous part of a grand transformation scene in which
the rewiring of the UK (the massive replacement of our communications
systems which all you punters in British Telecom have just funded), the
spread of automation, the growth of corporate databases and the
development of the cashless society all have starring roles.  It is not
just manufacturing industry which is presented with the simple choice
"automate or liquidate"; non-manufacturing industry is now undergoing
even greater turmoil, as word processors drain typing pools, databases
relocate filing clerks and expert systems render consultants redundant.
</p>
<p>Although the impetus behind these changes is primarily the same old
commercial imperative to do more of the same better and faster, their
combined effect, it is asserted, will together prove to be qualititative
rather than quantitative.  We are poised on the brink of a third
industrial revolution (if revolutions have brinks), in which the old
dialectics of labour and capital, of productivity and consumerism will
lose their significance.  A new utopianism, or an old despair, grips
apparently sane commentators as their imaginations attempt to grapple
with the microchip: it will bring about the end of civilisation as we
know it; it will bring about a land of milk and honey produced by small
collectives in which no one has to work unless they want to; it will
create a new disaffected peasantry only controllable by means of an
inhuman totalitarianism.  This rash of prediction is not a new
phenomenon; Marinetti and the futurists were making similarily wide of
the mark apocalyptic prophecies for technology before the Great War -
which proved to be a far more comprehensive agent of social change than
the motor car.
</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the headiness of little knowledge which encourages the
wilder extrapolations of the futurologists.  Sober reflection gives no
reason to suppose that the indisputably amazing advances in the
development of the micro processor will necessarily be parallelled by
teequivalent advances in its supporting technology.  Most computers still
communicate with us by means of an expensive and inefficient luminous
screen and a keyboard which was designed over a century ago to be
ergonomically inefficient, so that the "typewriter" (as its operator was
then called) could not go too fast for the machine's delicate innards.
More user-friendly methods of communication are still a long way off,
despite the current availability (at a price) of 'pucks', 'mice' and
touch-sensitive screens.  Speech recognition systems, into which vast
amounts of research money are currently being poured, may prove to be as
elusive in this decade as automatic translation of natural language was
in the last, and for similar reasons.  An allied object for scepticism,
at least amongst the currently computer literate, is the blithe
assumption that computer literacy can, or even should, be acquired as
simply and as easily as the ordinary sort.
</p>
<p>These two reservations do not appear to have occurred to either Michael
Shallis or Peter Large; their books have little else in common.  Large's
analysis is clearly aimed at a receptive audience which is like him,
decently agnostic, mildly satirical, technologically aware and sensibly
concerned about social issues.  Shallis, who teaches at Oxford's
Department of External Studies, is rather less sure of his audience.
The defensive note struck in his preface ("any critic of technology is
liable to be labelled a Luddite and I would not be surprised if the term
was used about myself") recurs.  The Luddites however were driven to
their futile activities by technological changes that affected their
lives directly and immediately; Mr Shallis appears to be motivated more
by an altruistic desire to save the rest of us from spiritual decay,
having already purified himself by banishing television, washing machine
and even electric toaster from his own home.
</p>
<p>There is more than a hint of the lay preacher in several of his
strictures: "To reduce intelligence to mere reason is ...  degrading and
unwholesome", "The computer was born with 'bad blood'", "Information
technology ...  is the invention of the devil". Not surprisingly, his
greatest scorn is reserved for those loonies of the artificial
intelligentsia who persist in finding (or modelling) fairies at the
bottom of the research lab: "It seems to me that before computers have
religious or ethical codes built into them, the computer scientists
might adopt some of their own to direct their purposes in a suitably
moral way."
</p>
<p>Ironically, Mr Shallis appears to earn his living by teaching people how
to use this diabolical device; indeed, doing it rather well, to judge by
the two chapters of straightforward technical explication included here.
Rather less satisfactory is his fondness for Large Truths (for example
that the history of technology is one of increasing abstraction from
reality) which tend to obscure as much as they illuminate.  The bogeyman
of scientific Reductionism takes a terrible pasting in these pages, as
does the principle of scientific neutrality and the idea that the
"so-called Protestant work ethic" (a favourite phrase) can be replaced
overnight.  For Shallis, because the telephone offers only a disembodied
voice, it can provide only an unsatisfactory surrogate for human
communication; systems which impose only such methods of "interfacing"
people are therefore "imperialistic".  Whether a messenger bearing a
cleft stick would be more acceptable is not clear. His doubts about
large computer systems are not without value: they do indeed malfunction
and do indeed require proper controls and careful validation; this does
not however make them intrinsically useless or evil.  
</p>
<p>Despite an engaging dottiness (there are apparently "many cases of
people's psychological state adversely affecting the performance of a
computer system") , despite the patent meretriciousness of some of his
targets (the remainder being straw men or lost causes), despite even his
earnestness, Shallis remains curiously unpersuasive, perhaps more
because of his wooden prose than his puritanism. 
</p>
<p>By contrast, Large, as a professional journalist is an adept of the new
technology.  His book is a composite of short paragraphs, pithy sayings,
useful statistics, non-technical explanation, occasional anecdote,
trends to note, memorabilia, objects of grave concern.  Its words were
clearly not composed but processed.  No important new development is
left un- summarised, no cause for concern deprived of equal time.  It is
bang up to date; the present volume being only the first of what will
presumably continue to be regular revisions.  And yet reading it as a
book is a remarkably unsatisfying activity.  It is meant to be "blipped"
— Toffler's expressive coinage for what will become the characteristic
mode of human information processing once Shallis' nightmares have
become reality.  </p>
</div>  
 
 
 
 
 
