<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="turkle"><head>
Sherry Turkle <title>The second self: computers and the human 
spirit</title> (Simon &amp; Schuster, 1984, 0 671 46848 0)
</head>
<p>Just as the 'typewriter' was once its operator rather than a machine, 
so a 'computer' was once a person skilled in computation, rather than 
the mechanical or electronic contrivance used for that purpose.  The 
semantic shift whereby agency itself was transferred from the person 
to the person's tools perhaps typifies the unease evident in this and 
other books which attempt to assess roles assigned to the computer in 
society. For Professor Turkle, such assessments should be made with 
great caution. The characteristic role she identifies for the machine 
is as a "constructed object", a "Rorschach, a projective screen for 
other concerns". It presents us with a "second self", an electronic 
mirror by which we may determine exactly what we are about. Children, 
according to this thesis, when exposed to 'Speak and spell' or 
similar toys use them as a catspaw for the great question of childish 
metaphysics "What makes a thing alive?". Students, similarly, use 
computers primarily as tools in the great question of adolescent 
metaphysics "What am I?"
</p>
<p>Turkle identifies three paradigmatic ways of "relating to computers": 
the metaphysical ("Is this thing alive?"), the masterful ("How can I 
conquer this thing?") and the identifying ("This thing is like me"). 
She asserts, repeatedly, that the existence of these three modes of 
response is both an important discovery  in  its own right and also 
valuable as a diagnostic aid: an individual's ratings on this 
triple-pronged scale  provide a window into his or her personality 
and "cognitive style" (whatever that might be).
</p>
<p>Her book certainly demonstrates the usefulness of these three modes 
in analysing the individual cases she describes, though their 
generality is hardly thereby demonstrated. One might  anticipate 
these three modes of reaction to almost any stimulus on the part of 
children; perhaps computers differ from, say, rabbits, dolls or 
bicycles only in the complexities of obtaining (and maintaining) the 
stimulus in the first place. Children also wonder whether stuffed 
toys are alive, after all; they often use their toys to define a 
position in society and even identify with them in ways hard to 
distinguish from those which Turkle claims to be characteristic of 
their response to the machine. Equally, one can only speculate as to 
the extent to which her division of children into "hard" and "soft" 
masters on the basis of their programming styles would retain its 
validity in a learning environment where the declarative and 
non-procedural methods of logic programming had prevailed over the 
obscure functionalism of Logo and Basic.
</p>
<p>The obsessiveness with which afficianados play arcade style games is 
not perhaps quite the same as the obsessiveness of the collector of 
railway engine numbers, but while the first obsession seems 
qualitatively different from the second, it is hard to see in what 
exactly that difference consists; certainly Professor Turkle does not 
attempt to explain it. A lengthy methodological appendix to the book 
provides one possible explanation for this. As in her previous 
<hi>Psychoanalytic politics</hi>, Turkle sees herself as being  "like 
the anthropologist who lives in an isolated village in a far-off 
place". Her interpretations are presented with the patina of 
neutrality and objectivity, but this does not make them any the less 
subjective. Unlike the ethnologist however, Turkle's method of 
proceeding wilfully ignores the background knowledge of the cultural 
context within which her subjects live and move, a background 
knowledge which she (unlike "real" ethnologists such as Margaret 
Mead) cannot escape sharing with them. For one well-educated 
middle-class white American academic to regard the <hi>zeitgeist</hi> of 
another as totally alien, because it is expressed in cybernetic terms 
rather than (say) theological ones, is merely silly.
</p>
<p>This is a shame, given Turkle's evident skill and insight when 
pinpointing the beliefs and fears underlying individual responses to 
the machine. Substantial chunks of transcripted interview make up a 
significant part of the book, but these are orchestrated by skilful 
and (from my lay viewpoint) penetrating psychological analysis. What 
is lacking is any understanding of the broader cultural context 
within which these individual reactions are articulated. This is 
particularly evident when she turns to adult computer users.
</p>
<p>The section in which she describes the "first generation" of home 
computer users fails to convince precisely because of its failure to 
point out those attributes which these early computer "buffs" shared 
with other hobbyists; the following section on MIT hackers similarly 
fails because of its apparent lack of understanding for what it is 
that distinguishes computer science students from computing 
professionals on the one hand and what it is that they share with 
other students on the other.
</p>
<p>With the best will in the world, no one could describe the Computer 
Science Department of the Massachussetts Institute of Technology, 
august and inspiring though that institution indubitably is, as 
typical of the community of computer users, without doing gross 
violence to the normal sense of the words "typical" or "community". 
The ethnology of the "hacker" which Turkle appears to regard as 
typical of the computer culture really differs from the ethnology of 
the "beatnik" or the "hippy" only in such minor details as the type 
of narcotics preferred. As one reads her rather solemn description of 
MIT initiation rites and the mystique of the Hack (as revealed in an 
acutely embarassing parody of <hi>Star Wars</hi> once circulated over 
ARPANET), the figure of the anthropological fieldworker  earnestly 
noting ingeniously provided misinformation comes dangerously close to 
the surface of the subtext.
</p>
<p>There is an interesting book to be written about the way in which the 
sixties' obsession with Tolkienish fantasy was transmuted into sword, 
sorcery, dungeons and dragons, but regrettably this is not it. That 
same unwritten book might go a long way to explaining why the 
characteristic mode of imaginative expression for the dedicated 
computer user is science fiction fantasy, in which all the richly 
awkward rugosities of human personality are ironed out into the 
crudely fantastical. It is to Professor Turkle's credit that she 
notes the frame of mind in which so limited a view of artistic 
activity obtains, and relates it to the characteristic rule-oriented 
frame of reference currently needed for computer programming. As an 
exposition of the <hi>gestalt</hi> within which the computer user 
operates it is however less than satisfactory.
</p>
<p>Conspicuously not interviewed by Turkle is any representative of the 
burgeoning class of young upwardly-mobile professional computer 
users: the tribes of analysts and programmers and data management 
consultants who are actually (to mix some rather painful metaphors) 
in touch with the leading edge of the state of the art. This seems a 
curious omission, the rectification of which would have gone a long 
way to balancing the one-sidedness of this book. Concerning itself as 
it does exclusively with people for whom the computer is essentially 
a toy rather than a means of livelihood, it necessarily contain many 
rather shallow responses, made to bear more significance than they 
warrant. By contrast, a book such as Tracy Kidder's <title>Soul of a new 
machine</title> which concerns itself with events of real significance 
within the computing community, is consequently a much more effective 
nailing-down of the ethnology of Silicon Valley than any amount of 
scholary survey and interview.
</p>
<p>For her next book, I would recommend Professor Turkle to examine the 
opinions of some arbitrary collection of people who have never used 
computers. These opinions will almost certainly conform to one of 
three potent paradigms, represented mythologically in the tales of 
Prometheus, Pygmalion and Frankenstein respectively. According to the 
Promethean paradigm, the computer extends our intellectual faculties 
just as technology extends our physical capabilities. It makes us as 
gods, paradoxically without impugning our humanity. On the contrary, 
our mastery of the computer is seen as the apotheosis of what it is 
to be human. This school of thought finds depressingly few adherents, 
except perhaps in IBM. Far more seductive, in these Godless days, is 
the Pygmalion paradigm, according to which the computer is a type of 
perfection to which mere bundles of neurones and amino acids can 
never hope to aspire. This is of course merely the inverse of the 
Frankenstein view of the case, in which the wretched machine is 
everything that humanity is not and its ultimate triumph a denial of 
every human aspiration.
</p>
<p>Like the present book, this one would have an enviable 
unassailibility. As a panoramic record of the various sorts of 
nonsense people might use to delude themselves with, its objectivity 
will be unimpeachable and its descriptive validity self evident. 
Whether or not such a book tells us anything useful about society as 
a whole will also very much depend on the representativeness of the 
punters whose views have been canvassed.
</p>
 
<trailer> 
Lou Burnard, Oxford University Computing Service
</trailer></div>
