<!--
! 2 july
 
 
Dear Mike
 
There follows the first of my two book reviews for University Computing.
I hope it is neither too late nor too savage. The second will follow
within a week or so.
 
Best wishes,
Lou


-->

<div xmlns="http://www.teic.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="avison">
<!--Published in <title>University Computing</title> 8, p. 159 <idno
                  type="issn">0265-4385</idno><date>1986</date> -->
<head>
D.E. Avison <title>Information Systems Development: a database approach</title>
</head>
 
<p>This text provides an introduction to basic concepts in information
systems design. It is clearly aimed at students of business studies or
similarly non-technical courses where a nodding acquaintance with such
topics as SSADM, 3NF or 4GLs is deemed necessary. It might also be
useful in a fairly low-powered or introductory computer science course.
The heart of the book is an orthodox and competent presentation of data
analysis methods using both Entity-Relationship modelling and a
simplified version of Codd's relational calculus. Other chapters cover
related topics such as 'business analysis', logical schema design
according to hierarchic, network or relational dogma, and some rather
skimpy descriptions of how these are actually implemented by IMS, IDMS,
dB2, ADABAS et al. All of this is adequate for an introductory text, but
in no way superior to the more thorough expositions already available in
standard text books (e.g. Date, Robinson).   
</p>
<p>The book attempts a more mobile target in its discussion of current
fashions in structured systems analysis methodologies. This being a
field in which jargon is everything, much of the discussion is little
more than padding to surround explanations of such phrases as  <term>Integrated
Programming Support Environment</term>, <term>analyst's workbench</term>,
<term>report generator</term>,  <term>structured walk through</term>, 
<term>prototyping</term>,  <term>functional description</term>,
<term>stepwise refinement</term>, <term>dataflow diagrams</term> etc. 
A keen student might get as good an understanding of most of these
simply by reading the computer trade press for a week or two.
Conspicuous by its absence in the chapter on systems design is any
mention of Jackson structuring techniques: surely a more reliable (and
more productive) systems design tool than  <term>structured english</term>
which gets several references.   </p>
<p>
Superficial chapters on data storage techniques and on Data Dictionary
systems together with an astonishingly inadequate chapter on micro-based
DBMS, distributed databases and database machines are also included:
apparently with little purpose other than to bring the book up to the
required length. On database machines, Avison's description of ICL's
CAFS is simply wrong, while to describe the IBM System 38 as a database
machine because it has 'micro-coded database instructions' (unspecified)
seems a little dubious. Distributed database systems get four pages (two
of which are pictures) and micro dbms five. A text book should either
discuss these issues properly or remain silent on them. 
</p>
<p>  The book is well produced and illustrated and its basic content is
sound. There is also a good bibliography, which students might be better
advised to choose from than to read the book itself. Avison writes  with
a contempt for the English language which should not go unremarked,
particularly in a book aimed at the educational market.   <q>Like most
texts, however,</q>  he remarks
<q>IMS will be equated with the database system</q> (he means <q>As
do most texts, mine will treat IMS as a database system</q>  — I
think). Or again,  <q>However there are severe limitations to retain
flexibility unless the database is not very complex.</q>  Publishers
surely have a duty to protect the public from sentences such as these,
even if their authors have abnegated it.   
</p>
</div>
