<!--
There follows the original text of my review of Mind Wheel, just to keep
you innerested. The thing itself, plus the review as published (which 
turns out to be subtly different) are in the post...
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pinsky">
<head>Byt and myth</head>
<bibl><title>MIND WHEEL An Electronic Novel (TM)</title>: by Robert Pinsky (Author) Steve Hales 
(Programmer) and William Mataga (Programmer). A Synapse and Broderbund 
Production. (Synapse Software Corporation, 1984) $39.00</bibl>

 
<p>On the face of things, the Electronic Novel (Trade Mark) should be
just the ticket for those practioners of the higher criticism who seek
to overthrow authority by re-building the sense of a text as it is
read. A significant amount of the Electronic Novel really is
constructed by the reader, who by typing at the computer keyboard
actually creates the story (for yes, oh dear yes, it does tell a
story) encounter by encounter, dialogue by dialogue. But there is
something illusory, something stanley-fishy, about this freedom. You
are free to disregard the overall purpose of the exercise, the
pre-text as it were; you can play it simply as a sight-seeing
exercise; you can marvel at the varyingly inept ways in which a
computer program can be made to torment the English language. But
these froward reactions will be rewarded only by boredom.
</p>
<p>Electronic Novel (Trade Mark) is but Adventure Game writ large. In
the adventure game, even this up-market version of it, plot is
everything, and the plot is that same old atavistic heroic quest for
something-or-other, liberally laced with backwards-chained
reasoning. To get the girl, Perseus had to conquer the Kraken; to
conquer the Kraken, he had to behead the Medusa; to behead the Medusa
he needed the advice of the three witches. In the same way, the
electronic adventurer, like some experimental rodent, must run a maze
of dark hints and false tracks, responding appropriately and in the
correct sequence to stochastically mutated stimuli.  To get up the
staircase, you must placate the weeping soldier. Nothing will do this
except a helmet full of rainwater from outside the castle gates; a
good joke, or even a Babe Ruth candy bar, will not suffice. If you set
foot outside the castle gates (having solved the riddle written over
them), you will be arrested by a lizard-like officer and rot away
behind barbed wire, unless you have previously acquired some suitable
magical talisman. To get the talisman, you must fight the thug instead
of sneaking out of the backstage door when he isn't looking. On the
other hand, if you climb the tree inside the prison camp and if you
still have your Babe Ruth candy bar, eating it might just cause you to
grow wings and escape.  If, having discovered all this, you decide
you'd rather not go up the staircase at all, you will rapidly exhaust
the possibilities of this electronic text, in rather the same way as
if early in Act I you had decided that on the whole Uncle Claudius was
quite a decent old stick.
</p>
<p>According to the lavishly illustrated printed prolegomena which
accompanies the floppy disk, "Mindwheel" came to its author during
fasting and meditation in Eastern Montana. Its original form, written
in a frenzy on the walls and ceiling of his cell, was reproduced and
edited from "large-format AccuLens photographs taken at the Greville
Meditative Order headquarters", (a photograph of the latter, though
not the former, is provided) but it took several years before suitably
innovative programmers could be found capable of implementing "the
grand scheme of those three days and nights of convulsive
inspiration". It certainly is several years since the Adventure Game
first became the favourite late night pastime of anyone with access to
MIT's computer systems, but its basic form has survived the
micro-computer revolution more or less unscathed.  The participant
still wanders around compulsively gathering up objects of dubious
utility, still encounters implausible conditions and still suffers no
worse fate than having to begin all over again. The sophistication
with which computers can be made to approximate realistic dialogue has
advanced a little, though this program is no more difficult to confuse
than any other. (Words not in its vocabulary are politely rejected
with a message apologising for their absence; as the adventure is
supposedly being performed via a computer terminal, such
computer-style 'error messages' as appear are in any case
appropriate).
</p>
<p>The originality of Mindwheel, such as it is, lies rather in the
richness and complexity of its imagery, a far cry from the usual
dungeons and dragons. The four "minds", passage through which forms
the plot of the adventure, are those of an assassinated rock star, a
poet, a military dictator and a mysterious female scientist. Each mind
is realised as a different environment, populated by varyingly helpful
or antagonistic characters and the usual collection of objects; there
is also a kind of background flow of randomly selected sentences
appropriate to each locale. Some objects and at least one character,
an endearingly helpful frog, can be carried from one environment to
another. Words and phrases have a magic of their own; riddles have to
be answered, and hints interpreted, while at one stage a poem (from
Pinsky's 1984 publication "History of My Heart") has to be
completed. Themes and images are combined to an unusual extent: the
name of the rock group is "Tyranny and the Senses"; the frozen wastes
of the Generalissimo's prison camp are behind a door which is opened
by the word "Tyranny"; escape from them involves freeing a frozen
fountain and a soldier turned to stone from the waist down, and so
forth. What little resonance remained in the sword and sorcery
sub-Tolkeinish world of most adventure games having long since been
hyped flat, Pinsky has wisely gone to the springs of his own
subconscious to create new mythical worlds. Whether the compulsion to
get to the goal, common to all adventure games, is so strong as to
blind the user to the richness of verbal texture, inventiveness of
incident and the overall unity of this adventure very much depends on
the individual adventurer.
</p>
</div>

