<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="stein">
<head>A passion for control</head>
<bibl>Dorothy Stein: <title>Ada: A life and a legacy.</title> MIT Pr., 1986.</bibl>
 
<p>The set of persons after whom computer languages have been named is not a
large one and includes some very odd bedfellows: Blaise Pascal, William of
Occam and Ada Byron, Countess of Lovelace all have this, if nothing else,
in common. When the American Defense Department decided to honour the
memory of Byron's daughter by naming its newly-designed general purpose
programming language after her, it was presumably motivated more by the
myth that has grown up around this unfortunate lady than by the fact that
ADA actually sounds like an acronym, (as indeed do PASCAL and OCCAM). 
Even in her own lifetime, Ada was surrounded by myth. Her mother, Byron's
estranged wife and a woman of truly Dickensian awfulness, was obsessed by
the  manufacture and control of her public image; her daughter's
personality could not hope to escape manipulation as intense as that of
any modern politician or media personality. Consequently, Ada's chief
legacy is a dense tissue of intrigue, gossip and supposition,  which this
fascinating book patiently unweaves and explicates, using as its raw
material two main sources, firstly the archive of original letters and
papers so carefully preserved and, we must assume, largely doctored by
Lady Byron and her descendants to support her view of the case; secondly
the papers of Charles Babbage and those few others of Ada's friends and
confidants capable of resisting the demands of Ada's family lawyers. By
thus going back to primary sources, Stein is able to debunk more myths
than one. 
</p>
<p>Ada Byron was not quite two years old when first brought to public
attention in the third canto of <hi>Childe Harold's Pilgrimage</hi>, where
separation from her is presented as yet another instance of the terrible
cost of being Lord Byron, <hi>poete maudit</hi>. Her mother's reaction to this
celebrity was to shelter the child from all knowledge of her father for as
long as possible, and to treat her childhood ailments with a regime which
seems eccentric even for those leech-ridden days. Ada's childhood appears
to have been dominated by lengthy periods of debility; Stein argues in a
somewhat speculative appendix that she may have suffered from porphyria,
although the psychosomatic explanation also presented is surely more
persuasive. Needless to say, with adolescence the glamour of being Byron's
daughter could no longer be resisted, neither by Ada herself nor by others
(Disraeli's <title>Venetia</title> (1837)  for example is a wildly misleading novel
about this aspect of her personality); nor, with marriage, could her
mother's tutelage be maintained. Visiting Newstead Abbey, Ada expressed
the wish to be buried with her father there, and although it must have
annoyed her husband almost as much as her mother, in the event her request
was honoured. Stein uncovers much evidence that Ada had, within the limits
allowed, qualities as romantic and headstrong as might have been expected
from Byron's daughter. As well as an early infatuation with a tutor (no
more than might be expected from anyone similarly placed in time and
social position), Stein uncovers evidence of an adulterous affair with the
shadowy John Crosse, an experimental scientist of somewhat dubious social
standing. Equally, Ada's weakness for betting on horses, and the desperate
shifts to which her incompetence at it lead her, provide as scandalous a
backdrop to her painful death as any silver fork novellist might desire. 
</p>
<p>The Byronic mythos was also Ada's chief attraction for her first
biographer. Doris Langley Moore's book,  revealingly sub-titled <title>Byron's
Legitimate Daughter</title> (1977), continually moved Ada off centre stage in
favour of this or that Byronic association. Moore's (entirely just)
distaste for Lady Byron also lead her to give that unspeakable harridan a
misleadingly dominant role in Ada's life. For much of her short life, Ada
was barely on speaking terms with her mother, and although the latter
re-established her hegomony by influence over Ada's husband, Stein gives
ample evidence of Ada's independence of will, until, in her last year, she
was too weakened by disease to resist the domination of the woman whose
virtues Byron had compared (unfavourably) to "thine 'incomparable oil',
Macassar!". 
</p>
<p>Stein's Kings Charles's head, if she has one, is more contemporary. For
Moore, as surely for Ada's contemporaries, Lady Lovelace's apparently
passionate enthusiasm for mathematics and science was an interesting and
quirky, if un-lady-like, hobby; for Stein perhaps, for some of her readers
surely, it marks her as one of the great might-have-beens, denied the
fruition of her talents by a represssive patriarchy. For evidence of the
new Ada mythos, any popular introduction to the electronic computer may be
consulted: somewhere in chapter one there will be a paragraph or two on
the history of the subject, in which Charles Babbage's Engines will
naturally appear, closely followed by the ghost of Lady Lovelace, 
supposedly with Babbage one of the very few who understood the true nature
and purpose of the unbuilt Analytical Engine, occasionally reputed
Babbage's mistress, always billed as the world's first programmer. 
</p>
<p>Certainly, like her mother, Ada had a passion for mathematics.  (Stein
drily supposes that the subject was first recommended to her in
adolescence as an alternative to "objectionable thoughts"). However
Stein's close analysis of Ada's surviving correspondence with such
notables as Augustus de Morgan, Julia Sutherland and Babbage himself 
shows her to have had stunningly little aptitude for the subject, being
unable (for example) to understand the simple principle by which terms
from one of a pair of simultaneous equations may be substituted in the
other. In translating from French L.F. Menabrea's <title>Memoir</title> on Babbage's
Analytical Engine, she followed a printer's error in the original which
made mathematical nonsense, apparently blindly. The published <hi>Notes</hi> to
this translation, on which her reputation as computer programmer <hi>avant
la lettre</hi> must rest, were written very much under the guidance of
Babbage himself. For him, the publication was a golden opportunity to
renew his case for further funding, at a time when he was suffering from
government neglect remarkably similar to that suffered by Daniel Doyce at
the hand of the Circumlocution Office. As well as the occasion, the
general tenor of Ada's <hi>Notes</hi> is also often mis-represented: today, the
separation of the analytical engine into units supporting store, mill, and
input and output functions can only prefigure the programmability of the
modern computer. Ada however made this point only in passing and in order
to stress the difference between the proposed engine and the existing
difference engines. For Ada, and presumably also for Babbage, the truly
remarkable feature of the analytical engine was its separation of data
from process, and its consequent generality of applicability, . Stein
demonstrates that (in the <title>Notes</title> as a whole) the thought underlying
this distinction derives more from Manchester school economics translated
to mechanics than from the sort of imaginative leap which now seems so
remarkable in Ada's much quoted comparison "the Analytic Engine <hi>weaves
algebraic patterns</hi> just as the Jacquard-loom weaves flowers and leaves".
</p>
<p>Ada's brilliant mathematical career was launched (and terminated) with the
publication of her translation of Menabrea and its  <hi>Notes</hi> in 1843.
Babbage was to pay her generous tribute in his autobiography, but this was
written a decade after her death when the memory of the scandal that
surrounded it and of his subsequent quarrel with the Lovelace family was
presumably sharper than the truth of their working relationship some
twenty years earlier.  At that time, her vague offer of further
collaboration had been refused, firmly but politely. They had also
quarrelled over a proposed preface summarising Babbage's funding
difficulties, of which the Notes profess a somewhat ostentatious
ignorance; Ada's delusions of grandeur cannot have greatly endeared her to
the eminently practical Babbage either. In 1844, she abandoned mathematics
for music, then for science and mesmerism. As to her mother, so to Faraday
and others she wrote lengthy self-glorifying letters describing herself as
"the Deborah, the Elijah of Science", but no further prophecies were
vouchsafed her. 
</p>
<p>The last ten years of her life seem oddly empty. Her husband, the
long-suffering Count of Lovelace, took up a brief literary career; over
two years he published nine articles on suitably respectable issues of the
day, such as the Suffrage,  Malthus and  Animal Husbandry on all of which
he argued a solidly respectable point of view. In one of these, a review
of Gasparin's <title>Course of Agriculture</title>, the need to grapple with the
statistical problems of relating climate and crop size lead to a
collaboration with his wife, and further consultations with Babbage and
Sir John Herschel. Ada eventually contributed some Notes to the published
Review containing a number of unexplained and probably inexplicable
formulae; these form her only other published work.  Her disastrous
passion for the turf dates also from this last decade of her life; Stein
demonstrates persuasively both the absence of any involvement with Babbage
in this and also that the Countess was at least as often the duper as the
dupe in her gambling adventures. However, hard evidence for this, as for
her liaison with Crosse, is necessarily scarce, since these were precisely
the two subjects which lead to her mother's resuming control of Ada's
public image, during her needlessly protracted and painful death from a
cervical cancer in 1860. 
</p>
<p>Dorothy Stein is not primarily a  historian (at one point she remarks of
historians that they are "a sentimental lot"), but a psychologist with a
respectable understanding of physics and computer programming. As such she
is as much interested in explicating the people around Ada as determining
what their actions may or may not have been. Where Moore catalogues (say)
the interminable misdeeds of Lady Byron rather in the manner of the
village gossip, (pausing as it were only for the occasional "Well!" and
"Did you ever?" from the reader), Stein seeks motivation and psychological
patterns : "Her passion was for control, not care... Motherhood succeeded
wifehood as the name of her propensity for self-justification, only to be
replaced by grandmotherhood". To set against this sensitivity for the
human and the universal, it must be noted that Stein is far weaker than
Moore in her sense of period, occasionally and irrelevantly remarking in a
shocked tone on her protagonists' extraordinary insensitivity to the
plight of the working man in the 1840s, making very heavy weather of the
financial basis of the Byrons' marriage, and solemnly remarking on the
absence of antibiotics in the early 19th century.  Some rather more
aggressive sub-editing (which would also have removed several typos)
should have been invested in this altogether unusual and impressive book. 
</p>
</div> 
 
