<div source="#r8607TLS"  xml:id="campbell" facs="pages:1986-campbell.jpg" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
<head>More and more addressable</head>
<byline>Lou Burnard</byline>
<bibl>Duncan Campbell and Steve Connor: <title>On the Record. Surveillance, Computers and Privacy - The
Inside Story.</title> 348pp. Michael Joseph. Paperback. £7.95 0719125762
</bibl><!--, published in the TLS, 25 July 1986, p. 813--> 
<p>If ever there was a ridiculous mouse born of a mountain it is the
Data  Protection Act, which finally became law in July 1984 after nearly
a quarter century of prevarication in Whitehall, although what is rather
 grandly termed the <soCalled>appointed day</soCalled> for implementation of all of its 
provisions is not due until next winter. It has taken Parliament one
departmental committee report, one Royal Commission, two draft bills,
three Private Members' bills, three White Papers and numerous official
consultations to reach the point of enacting principles close to the
letter if not the spirit of such contentious pronouncements as Article 8
of the European Convention on Human Rights. Indeed, it is widely
believed that only the signing of the Council of Europe's <title>Convention
for the Protection of Individuals with regard to Automatic Processing of
Data</title> in 1981 finally forced Whitehall's hand; a fact perhaps
worth putting into the balance the next time that Strasbourg's
Eurocracies are being belaboured in the public prints.   
</p>
<p>That the present government, not notorious for its concern for
liberal causes, may go down in history as the one under which the
concept of a right to privacy of information was finally enshrined in
legislation is almost as pleasing an irony as the fact that Mrs
Thatcher's administration was forced to espouse this wettest of causes
by simple commercial pressures. As the 1982 White Paper in which the
current legislation was first proposed makes clear, its primary purpose
is to protect the United Kingdom's trading interests in Europe, which
might well be compromised by the inability to transfer information
across European frontiers consequent on a failure to ratify the
Convention.   
</p>
<p>Whatever its parentage, perhaps the kindest judgement on the Act
with which we now have to live is that at least it means well. However
honourable its intentions, its weaknesses are rapidly becoming
notorious. Its provisions cover only data held in machine-readable form:
one simple way of evading the need to register a database you wish to
keep secret is thus simply to print it all out, delete the online copy
and invest in a good filing cabinet. The mechanism by which
<soCalled>subject access</soCalled> (that is, access to one's own
records) is to be implemented is vague in the extreme; there is no right
to have inaccurate data corrected or removed, even where action is taken
through the courts.  The powers of the Data Protection Registry itself
are scarcely less well defined: violations of the Act must be stumbled
upon to be detected, and what will happen when these are brought before
the courts is anyone's guess. So far the chief sufferers from the Act
appear to have been agencies such as Citizens' Advice Bureaux,
reportedly unable to cope with the extra work of registering all their
files of innocuous but protected information by the deadline earlier
this month.    
</p>
<p>The Act has also been much criticised for the number and variety of
exemptions from its provisions. An unconditional exemption applies to
data <q>required to be exempt for the purpose of safeguarding national
security.</q> Subject access is denied to a whole range of data,
including police or taxation records as might be predicted, but also
those of other statutory bodies more or less at the whim of the
Secretary of State, many of which are precisely those government
departments and agencies whose information gathering activities give all
upright citizens most cause for concern: - the security forces, the
Inland Revenue, the DHSS, the Customs and Immigration authorities, the
television and vehicle licensing authorities. But perhaps the most
alarming aspect of this <q>load of holes joined together</q> (as the
BMA is said to have called the bill) is that certain bodies, themselves
exempt from the Act's  regulatory provisions, are at liberty to force
other (regulated) data holders to disclose information for
non-registered purposes, without anyone being any the wiser. There is
thus a sense in which this Act requires all sheep to be ready to report
promptly to their local wolf.  
</p>
<p>This book is more than a detailed critique of the Data Protection
Act however. It documents, dispassionately and with every appearance of
accuracy, the sheer scope and intricacy of the vast accumulations of
information currently at the disposal of our masters, and makes some
informed speculations about their probable future. A web of databanks
lies concealed behind such unlovely acronyms as LOP, NICS, NUBS, JUVOS,
OCTA, COP, CODA, DCI, OPCS, IVAN, INDECS, MIRIAM, PNC  and CEDRIC; in
describing these and other systems, Campbell and Connor also provide
evidence of the extent to which their integration  into a gargantuan
apparatus of surveillance and control may soon be upon us. One does not
need to subscribe to any form of conspiracy theory to see a disturbing
inevitability in the process; it is a natural consequence of the
availability of better technology, in retrospect an almost Darwinian
process. The problems of integrating the disparate data files of a
commercial organisation is one which exercised the best brains of the
computing industry during the early sixties; the database concept, in
which a computer system deliberately aims to model the entire
information structure of an organisation, is the fruit of that exercise.
Within a commercial context, it is obviously appropriate. Whether the
state's information needs should be modelled in exactly the same way as
those of General Motors is more dubious.   
</p>
<p>Throughout the administrative infrastructure clerks and filing
cabinets have already been replaced by online terminals and
sophisticated database systems; what is recorded and for what purpose
necessarily change more slowly. It would be the height of naivety to
expect concern for the rights of the individual amongst the
administrators and guardians of our society if those rights are
threatened by a process which they perceive as simply helping them to do
their job better. On the contrary, we can expect whatever currently
characterises their mode of operation to be intensified. In whatever
sphere it is applied, the computer invariably brings the ability to do
more of the same thing, and faster; very rarely does it bring about a
radical reshaping of the enterprise to which it is applied.  
</p>
<p>Consequently, we should not be surprised to find the DHSS readier to
apply their new computers to the task of identifying  <soCalled>scroungers</soCalled>
than that of identifying those to whom benefits are due, though both are
technically equally feasible. Neither should we be surprised to find
that the Police National Computer (PNC), originally intended to hold
details of missing cars and persons, is also used as a repository for
suppositious gossip, circumstantial evidence  and speculation: (the
technical term is <term>intelligence</term>). What after all would we 
expect the Inland Revenue to do with a magnificent invention like ICL's
Content Addressable File Store (CAFS) but apply it to the task of
finding out people's National Insurance numbers, given only parts of
their names and addresses, the better to collate information from
sources (such as banks) which cannot specify a NINO with those (such as
their own records) which must?  Once the Home Office's list of
undesirable immigrants has grown to such a length as to prevent its
being memorized by even the most vigilant of immigration officers the
only effective way of policing our frontiers will be to introduce
machine readable passports (due in 1987) and use a computer (it is
called INDECS) to finger those flagged in the Home Office's database.  
</p>
<p>Moreover, once such systems are in place, their expansion seems
inevitable. Once INDECS is operational, the additional cost of logging
every entrance and every exit of any suitably interesting subject is
trivial. Once  the Inland Revenue has identified your National Insurance
number, (the closest thing currently to a Universal Personal Indicator
(UPI)), it would cost very little more to recover your employment
records, your health records, details of the area in which you live, and
of all the telephone calls you made to Dublin last month. Given that
such information will be held in machine readable form somewhere, given
that it is easier to keep it than to throw it away, given both the
tremendous increases in ease of communication between otherwise
unrelated computers, the technical means of implementing the omniscient
computer of science (and other) fiction are already present. The
database systems of the sixties already resemble the saurian manual
systems they replaced in their inflexibility and cumbersomeness. The
advent of really efficient free text searching systems and of deductive
or "expert" rule-based systems at the front end of the next generation
of computer systems will be complemented by developments such as CD-
ROM, which allows several gigabytes of data to be stored in a compact
disc accessible from a desk-top computer. Before technophoria overwhelms
us all, we would do well to remember that however morally neutral
informational technology itself may be, its applications (like those of
any other technology) need constant policing.</p>
<p>    Campbell and Connor, as good crusading journalists, are not
concerned with philosophical issues. The nature of technology is not on
their agenda, simply its effects and its applications. Their book is
primarily a pre-emptive register of data banks, including many which are
unlikely to come within the purview of the Data Registrar himself. Its
secondary purpose is to make the case against all such information
monoliths, a case that needs to be re-stated, perhaps a little more
explicitly for the benefit of those well-heeled citizens who feel they
have "nothing to hide". The case does not rest on anecdotes, though
there are plenty of these to be found, but on a recognition of the fact
that errors of judgement and observation, harmless in themselves, can
become lethal when given the spurious authenticity of a computer. The
authors also do the Data Protection Act the signal honour of taking it
seriously, itemising those few areas in which it may have some
significant effect on safeguarding civil liberties.   
</p>
<p>Despite its catchpenny title, this book is neither anecdotal nor
journalistically sensational. It is, as they say, solidly researched.
With its aid, the next time that you "come to notice" of the Police,
perhaps by reporting a crime, or by parking your car round the corner
from some political demonstration, you will at least know under what
category you are likely to achieve immortality, and in what company you
will be registered. 
</p>
</div>
