<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="grundy">
<head>
<bibl><title>Proceedings of the Fourth British National Conference on Databases</title>,
edited by A. F. Grundy (Cambridge University Press, 1985). Price
£25.00 h/b; ISBN 0 521 32020; 229 pp.
</bibl></head>
<p>The annual BNCOD conference is rapidly becoming an indispensable
fixture; it remains the only regular forum for presentation of British
research **ID the fundamentals of database systems, and as such is to be
valued. The papers in this volume reflect a tendency for the
conference to concentrate on theoretical issues at the expense of more
practical matters, though this is not in itself a criticism.
</p>
<p>Two invited papers, from Schmidt, on higher level relational objects,
and Pelagatti, on synthesizing relational and network models, typify
the growing awareness of the limitations of the relational model,
though Pelagatti's has little new to contribute. The BCS/CODASYL
Database Administration (DBAWG) presents a new and characteristically
thorough Access Control system, grasping a nettle which most
standardization bodies have been reluctant to consider. Borges reviews
existing discussions of the problems of concurrency control. Jiang and
Lavington breathe new life into the binary relationship model by
extending it to represent qualified knowledge, a necessary extension
for the long-awaited Manchester Intelligent File Store.  Feldman and
Fitzgerald present a novel graphic formalism for modelling actions, a
part of information systems analysis which has always tended to be
neglected. Atkinson and Stocker et al   report on the continued quest
for that holy grail, the Abstract Conceptual Schema, and its
associated mapping problems. Hitchcock et al. give a preliminary
report on the Aspect 'toolkit' approach to the definition of
*pses. Two short papers deal with user interface problems: Deen et
al. describe (yet another) new relational database management system
called PRECI/C, of interest perhaps in a teaching environment, while
Newman and Sethi report some fieldwork into the effectiveness of
various style of interactive help systems.
</p>
<p>Only two papers deal explicitly with particular application areas:
Moore on the problems of maintaining integrity in a large real-time
distributed database system for use in naval command and control
provides ample food for thought for anyone seriously contemplating
Star Wars research, while Jeffery attempts to synthesize some
traditional DBMS and office automation systems into a single
information system' using a fairly simple three level model.
</p>
<p>The book as a whole is well produced (conspicuously better than
earlier ones in the series) and, as a snapshot of the current
preoccupations of some British computer science departments, could not
be bettered. Whether it has any wider usefulness is more debatable.
</p>
<trailer>L. Burnard University of Oxford</trailer>
</div>

