<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="naylor">
<head>
<title>The PC Compendium. Volume 1</title>, by C. Naylor (Wiley for Sigma Press, 1987). Price £12.95 p/b. ISBN 1-85058-097-1; 330 pp.
</head>

<p>This volume collects together 34 specimens of the sort of cheap 
and cheerful hack journalism with which regular browsers of the 
micro trade press will be all too familiar. It is hard to see 
any possible justification for the republication of such material 
in book form, other than that candidly avowed in the preface,
of selling it all over again — repeatedly indeed, since there 
is a considerable amount of repetition in the volume. Naylor 
has done very little in the way of editing his PC-Week columns 
to avoid repetition and nothing at all about his style. The latter 
has a distinctive but rather irritating mid-Atlantic chattiness 
, a sort of determined chumminess  in which set phrases such 
as "Days of Yore" get capitalized, and British and American argots 
occasionally collide (as in "a right old collection of garbage"). 
</p>
<p>Sentences and paragraphs start abruptly, sometimes even lacking 
verbs. He has a mildly endearingly E.J.Thribb-like manner of 
starting paragraphs with the single word clause "So:" In small 
doses, and in weekly journalism, such an approach is pleasant 
enough, but in any quantity it becomes wearisome; this book (alas) 
is only volume one of a projected series.
</p>
<p>The subject matter includes some rather complicated ways of extending 
the (admittedly  primitive) facilities of MS-DOS by means of 
(God save the mark) a variety of BASIC programs, the sourcecode 
for which is reprinted at the end of the book and is also available 
on floppy diskette for the real enthusiast.   It is hard to see 
any long term interest in these, except perhaps in the nostalgia 
market, where they will provide vivid testimony  to the manner 
of nonsense endured during the early days of the micro-revolution. 
There are also a number of elementary introductions to various 
areas of micro computing which have become fashionable over the 
last few years, such as expert systems on which Naylor has also 
written a (comparatively) sensible book. Such articles at their 
best are, like an Oxford education, a very good way of acquiring 
just enough knowledge to sound as if you know what you are talking 
about.  
</p>
<p>The book also features one of those terminally unfunny joke glossaries 
which seem to wander around  large offices like lost souls and 
a minimal index which enabled me to check that Naylor really 
does think a decibel is so called because it contains ten bels,
but not to find again the page on which he talks of a "hyperbolus" 
— presumably some sort of very efficient medecine.
</p></div>
