<!--
From:	VAX::ARCHIVE      10-FEB-1988 16:01
To:	LOU
Subj:	
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="friedmann">
<head><title>The Little <hi>LISPer</hi></title>, by D.P. Friedmann and M Felleisen (MIT Press,
1987). Price £9.95 p/b. ISBN 0-262-56038-0; 186 pp.
</head> 
<p>It is hard to believe that the first edition of this classic 
introduction to the wonders of recursive list processing first 
appeared over a decade ago. In this new and expanded version,
nothing of the freshness and wit of the original has been lost,
while  the  ingenuity with which exposition and drill are combined 
by its catechitical form is no less impressive.  Above all,  
the authors' enthusiasm for their subject remains no less infectious. 
What is new in this volume, is a broadening of purpose: where 
the first edition was primarily a self-teaching manual for the 
then-modish LISP language, this new edition (coming into a sadder 
and wiser world) has a larger purpose: to use the Ten Commandments 
and Five Laws of Lisp as a vehicle for the teaching of recursive 
techniques and their value in general-purpose problem-solving. 
As an aim, this cannot be faulted. The value of LISP as a programming 
language remains debatable (and hotly-debated); its elegance 
and simplicity as an embodiment of some fairly crucial notions 
of computer science surely much less so. 
</p>
<p>In its first incarnation, this book did a great deal to broaden 
the appeal of the language. It really was possible (as the original 
preface suggested you should) to sit down by the refrigerator,
slog your way through the book and feel your mind being modified. 
The importance of the refrigerator as mother / sustenance figure 
in American culture is not entirely irrelevant in the present 
context, for this book's curious obsession with food cannot be 
ignored, if only because of its effectiveness as a way of gaining 
that complicity between instructor and instructed on which a 
good teacher always depends. At the end of the first chapter,
for example, with the notions of ATOM, LIST, CAR, CDR, NULL and 
EQ firmly under our belt, we are advised to make a "peanut butter 
and jelly sandwich" - and provided with a blank page on which 
to spill the jelly (anglicé, jam).  At the end of the seventh 
chapter, there is a (fairly reliable) recipe for making that 
staple of American cuisine, the chocolate chip cooky, unusual 
only in that it is written in LISP.  
</p>
<p>As the preface warns, this book should not be read by those seriously 
interested in dieting. Nor is it particularly suited as a classroom 
text in either logic or LISP programming. But  as a painless 
- even pleasant - form of mental exercise for those left feeling 
flabby and out of condition by the more formal ways of grappling 
with recursive principles, this book is a tonic heartily to be 
recommended. At least some of the healthy state of logic programming 
today must be due to the enthusiasm which the first Little Lisper 
kindled in a past generation of students; the effects of this 
new edition on a new generation will be all the more interesting 
to watch for.
</p></div>

