<!--
Here's the one that went missing (JANET didnt lose it, I forgot to
transfer it from the MAC)
-->

<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="simon">
<head>John J. Simon Jnr :<title> From sand to circuits and other inquiries. </title>
Harvard University Office for Information technology 1986  0-674-32573
</head>

<p>This book collects together and expands on a number of survey-type
articles published in the Harvard <title>Information Technology Newsletter</title>
over the last few years. Half the pieces are dated 1983, which means
that the art whose state they purport to capture has since moved on,
in some cases quite a considerable distance. The chapter on xerography
for example is almost entirely innocent of any reference to
laserprinters, while that entitled 'The author- computer-ttypesetter
interface' boasts one (1) sentence on generalised markup and nothing
at all on postscript. There is a chapter dealing with interactive
video ('The record with a view') but nothing at all on optical storage
systems (CD or WORM).
</p>
<p>There are introductions to the basic principles of most 'information
technologies', and to the mathematical principles underlying binary
logic and imaging systems, together with a discursive chapture on the
industrial and social effects of 'disvestiture' in the US
telecommunications industry (for those with short memories, this is a
polite term for the breaking up of Old Ma Bell's cartel), and several
gee-whizz pages on the growth of computing facilities in US colleges
and universities, the computerisation of library systems etc. The most
recent article (1986) is also the longest: it is a fifty page essay on
the history of artifical intelligence winsomely titled "A long and
winding road". It is derived almost entirely (as indeed is the rest of
the book) from secondary sources, by a process of digestion and
paraphrase, the end result of which is a sort of mindless pap somehow
contriving to be both bland and indigestible.
</p>
<p>This book contains little that could not more easily amd more reliably
be found in any reputable encyclopaedia or comparable reference
work. It might perhaps be useful for students who lack the self
confidence or skill to approach such books directly, or for those
content to operate exclusively at a 'Readers Digest' level of
intellectual activity.
</p>
<trailer>
L. Burnard, University of Oxford
</trailer>
</div>

