<!--
From:	VAX::ARCHIVE      "Oxford Text Archive" 12-DEC-1989 10:27:42.90
To:	LOU
CC:	ARCHIVE
Subj:	

-->
<div xml:id="doheny" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<head><title>Effective Documentation: What we have learned from research</title>.
Edited by Stephen Doheny-Farina. MIT Press, 1988. 354 pp. 
33-75 </head>

<p>It's a comforting thought that something can be learned from
research, even if only how to produce more `effective'
documentation. The papers in this compendium come, for the
most part, from a twilight zone inhabited by `professional
communicators and teachers of communication', whose thankless
task it is to produce those unread manuals and unscanned
online help systems on which we all depend. It arises out of a
perceived gap between the communicators and those engaged in
`communication research', for the most part a hybrid crew of
social scientists, behaviourists and human factors
researchers. Communication is too important to be carried out
by rule of thumb, is the unstated message: its effectiveness
can and should be calibrated by the same sort of statistical
testing procedures as are used in market research. In this way
a new rhetoric, based on sound quantitative procedures, can be
defined. There are detailed discussions of experimental method
(how to set up double-blind experiments, the importance of
proper statistical controls etc.) which would be of use to
anyone embarking on any sort of behavioural research, and
several presentations of applications of this technique as a
means of establishing incontrovertibly in what circumstances a
particular method of presentation is better or worse for
certain purposes. If you want to find research results proving
(or disproving) that windows icons and mice provide better
ways of controlling screen editors than command lines, this
volume and its extensive bibliographies will help. If you are
concerned with stylistic issues, you will find supporting
arguments here for both the view that users of manuals want to
know about topics in depth, and its opposite. Less dubiously,
you will find much support for the (surely by now self
evident) view that people learn better by `doing' than by
rote, or that online and printed presentations of text require
different techniques. The unstated concern that
`communicators' should be regarded as professionals too also
finds expression in a number of papers devoted to the
effective management of the documentation process, and a plea
for its integration with the more glamorous side of software
development. The introduction claims that the book is "one of
a small but earnest group of research-based resources" for
these unsung heroes of the documentation section: small it
isn't, but earnest it certainly is.</p>
</div>



