<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ennals">
<head>RICHARD ENNALS and JEAN-CLAUDE GARDIN, eds. <title>Interpretation in the
humanities: perspectives from artificial intelligence</title>.
(Library and information research report 71, ISSN 02673-
1709; 71) Boston Spa: British Library Board, 1990. xv, 367
pp. £25. ISBN 0-7123-3186-7.
</head>

<p>This is a very unusual book, deriving from a rather unusual
occasion, though of a type which, it is to be hoped, recent
successfully completed engineering works beneath the Channel
will increasingly facilitate. It represents a genuinely
collaborative effort, involving practitioners of disciplines
as seemingly far apart as literary theory, prosopography,
philosophy, computer science and law, and cultural habits as
distinct as Anglo-saxon empiricism and Gallic theory. Its
subject is what should be at the heart of all the
humanities: interpretation, that hermeneutical process which
distinguishes true scholarship from academic scribbling. As
a means of throwing some light on just what that process
might involve, each of the contributors to this volume
addresses the question of <q>computability</q>, that is, the
extent to which the process of interpretation in a given
field can be re-expressed in computational terms, without
losing sight of creativity, that quasi-mystical process by
which cognition and understanding come about. To what extent
can literary, historical, philosophical or legal analyses be
simulated in formal terms? Is there an inherent
contradiction between the attempts which expert systems make
to formalise the interpretative process and the stress which
most of the humanities have traditionally placed on
multiplicity of meaning, on the importance of ambiguity? </p>
<p>
The volume contains fifteen papers, four of them in French,
with an English abstract, and the remainder in English, with
a French abstract, together with a brief epilogue by the two
editors. The papers derive from a Workshop jointly funded by
the British Library and the French Government department
responsible for museums and libraries (the Direction des
Bibliothèques, des Musées et de l'Information Scientifique),
organised by Dr May Katzen of the British Library's Office
for Humanities Communication and held at Cawthorpe House in
September 1988. Much of the keen intellectual pleasure the
invited participants must have derived from this latter day
symposium, as well as perhaps some of their occasional
mutual bafflement, is well preserved in the edited texts,
each of which deserves more careful and detailed analysis
than this brief review can give them.  </p>
<p>
The volume begins with an introductory section, in which
Margaret Boden presents an accessible but inevitably
somewhat skimpy presentation of the nature and goals of
Artificial Intelligence itself, Jean-Claude Gardin (whose
distinguished aegis hangs over much of the volume) considers
its applicability to the human sciences, and Richard Ennals
places its insights in a historiographical context. Gardin's
paper asks awkward questions in a characteristically
charming way:  what defensible basis can be found for
privileging (i.e. funding) some sorts of interpretation by
some kinds of people over others?  Referring to Shennan's
paper in the same volume, which argues that archaeological
interpretations would be better based on formal reasoning
than on the interpretive constructs of archaeologists, since
the latter are inevitably influenced by their own
culturally-determined interests, Gardin sketches an account
of his own <q>logicist</q> approach to this fundamental
epistemological problem, including several useful references
for further reading. He concludes with an incongruously
Thatcherite attack on the notion of <q>professionalism</q> as a
means of validating scientific interpretation -- perhaps a
result of the striking absence of the <q>cult of the amateur</q>
in his own culture. Ennals rehearses a similar argument in
favour of formal reasoning, which for him is what good
historians have already been doing unawares (rather as M.
Jourdain had been speaking French), if they have taken to
heart the lessons of Collingwood, Wittgenstein and other
theoreticians of language. His major concern is with <q>cross-
cultural</q> fertilisation of ideas, (not only across the
channel but also across disciplines), and with a view of
interpretation as code-breaking: as such, he risks
exemplifying the well-meaning amateur, as witness also his
quirky fascination with the ways of Westminster. </p> 
<p>
The second part of the book consists of a number of well-
focused papers on applications of Artificial Intelligence
techniques in three specific subject areas: archaeology,
history and letters. </p>
<p>
The papers of Stephen Shennan, Henri-Paul Francfort and John
Wilcock present good accounts of the achievements so far of
the <q>logicist</q> approach in archaeology, Wilcock's overview
being particularly accessible for the novice. The section on
history contains a bravura performance in which Jim Doran
assesses the ability of <q>distributed artificial
intelligence</q> to represent the complex semiotic models
developed by Todorov in his magisterial <q>Conquest of
America</q>; perhaps surprisingly, both semiotics and AI are
shown to profit from this unlikely encounter, which is also
certainly one of the most intellectually impressive in the
book. Kevin Schurer's piece on possible applications of AI
in historical demography seems initially rather pedestrian
and inconsequential by comparison. Nevertheless, it is
quietly subversive of some of the other articles in this
work in its opposition to logical positivism and its stress
on the practicalities of computing in history today, and
repays careful study. </p>
<p>
David Miall's paper discusses reader response theory, the
basic notions of which also seem somewhat removed from
logicist modelling. Noting that what characterizes a
literary text is its ability <q>simultaneously to establish a
norm and to subvert it</q>; Miall uses statistical techniques
borrowed from behavioural science to measure the <q>affect</q> of
such texts rather than any underlying formal model.  Some
more orthodox applications for AI are briefly described in
the same section by Danielle Bourcier, who considers their
very real potential in simplifying and making more effective
local administration and law.</p>
<p>
The final section of the book contains five comparatively
technical papers drawn from the disciplines which in some
sense underlie artificial intelligence -- linguistics,
logic, computer science and philosophy. Michel Charolles is
not well served by the three page summary of his 33 page
original, which includes a good summary of the emergence and
history of discourse analysis, even handed criticism of the
notions of text grammars and a discussion of why logicist
analysis has nothing to offer it. This must be read in the
original French, if only for the sake of the example
sentences; it provides a persuasive instance of a kind of
interpretation (the establishment of coherence in a
discourse) which does not seem to be susceptible to
formalisation by logicist rules. Jean Fargues fleshes out
the introduction to AI provided by Margaret Boden, with some
more specific discussion of its application in work towards
language-understanding systems. Peter Stockinger provides a
more detailed discussion of logicist analysis, from the
perspective of formal logic. Judith Richards argues,
briefly, for the importance of the so-called <q>strong</q> AI
approach, and the possibility of rediscovering its radical
potential which the direct modelling of human reasoning (or
<q>qualitative simulation</q>) offers. Finally, in one of the
longest, most thoughtful and thought provoking pieces of the
volume, Pierre Jacob gives a philosophical perspective on
the issue of what exactly <q>interpretation</q> is,
distinguishing at the linguistic level interpretation as
grammatical decoding from the kind of process defined by
Grice as <q>implicature</q>. This second kind of interpretation
is then related to cognition and intentionality, as a
prelude to a discussion of the distinction between
interpretation and explanation, specifically scientific
explanation.</p>
<p>
A useful concluding summary by the two editors underlines
the overall effect of this unusual collection: from whatever
theoretical or pragmatic standpoint one approaches it, both
computability and creativity are necessary <q>engines of
knowledge</q> in both the arts and the sciences. This volume
provides a vivid testimony to the effectiveness of
conjoining rather than opposing them. </p>
<trailer>
                                                 LOU BURNARD
                         Oxford University Computing Service
</trailer>
</div>


