<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lancs">
<head>I. Lancashire and W. McCarty <title>The Humanities Computing
Yearbook</title>. Clarendon Press, oxford, 1988.ISBN O-19-824442-
8.396pp.£4O.
</head>

<p>In 1989 it is no longer possible to question the desirability,
still less the existence, of 'humanities computing' as an academic
discipline. At centres throughout the world new posts are being
funded, as new journals flourish and new generations of students find
new skills are expected of them. The computer wielding linguist,
historian or textual critic is no longer pardonably eccentric; his/her
method has been canonised. It was only a matter of time before that
canon should be authoritatively documented, and this volume represents
the first and, to date, most successful attempt at that process. True,
there have been many no less worthy attempts to summarise
comprehensively the state of this particular art (for example, Hockey
and Oakman in 198O or Hughes in 1987) but these were all deliberately
evangelical works, whose authors were perhaps a little parochial in
their enthusiasms, a little uncritical in their acceptance of all
things computational. As much hy its format as hy its provenance, this
volume asserts that 'humanities computing' no longer needs to
proselytise, is no 1onger a coterie pursuit, and hence need not fear
rigorous examination or selfcriticism. It also clearly marks out a
turf and an agenda which may not perhaps exactly coincide with others'
definitions either of 'humanities' or of 'computing'.
</p>
<p>'Computing' (asserts the preface) 'is the "how-to" of
any discipline made obvious', hefore going on to specify
three 'kinds of methodology' for which computing seems
appropriate. These are storage and information retrieval;
statistical description; and linguistico-semantic analysis.
The relevance and success of computing methods in at least
the first two categories is not controversial, though the
acceptability of (for example) computer-based content
analysis, propositional logic or even computer simulation as
a means of adequately describing the reading of texts is
rather more debatable. It could he argued that computing
methodologies in fact distort the true nature of a
discipline, hy focusing attention in only those areas
easily susceptible of computerisation, which are not
necessarily those central to it. That is not a concern of
the editors of this volume, for whom the discipline is only
and exactly those aspects of it in which available computing
methods can he shown to he productive. For the rest, one
suspects, they feel like Jowett that 'what I don't know
isn't knowledge'.
</p>
<p>Some readers may he surprised to discover that 'the
humanities' include art history hut not art or design;
philosophy, hut not law, politics or economics; and 'folklore
studies' hut not ethnology or anthropology. The amount of
space and the number of subdivisions allocated to what
remains is also indicative of a very strong bias to
linguistics, literature and history at the expense of music
or archaeology. The editors claim no more for their taxonomy
than that it follows from their 'fieldwork' in assessing
what 'our colleagues have done and are currently doing' and
from their own view that 'most computational work is
methodological'; one might reasonably ask how they define
their colleagues.
</p>
<p>The volume is large, containing nearly 4OO closely —
and very well — typeset pages. Most of its bulk is taken up hy
a mixture of helpfully annotated bibliographic citations and
brief details of available software or similar resources,
grouped by topic or discipline. For the most part (though by
no means exclusively) the bibliographic citations are to
articles published in interdisciplinary journals and
conference proceedings, rather than from mainstream
discipline-specific journals, which (presumably) the editors
assume are already accessible to this volume's likely
readership. Since one highly desirable effect of the maturity
of 'humanities computing' must be its acceptance by the mainstream,
one must question the wisdom (if not the practicality) of
this assumption. Brief notes are attached to about
threequarters of the citations — an exceptionally helpful
feature of this volume. The software and other resources
cited form a very mixed bag, ranging all the way from 'a
generator of science fiction written in BASIC level 11 for a
Radio Shack TRS-8O' up to detailed reports on the INGRES
database management system. In most cases, developers,
suppliers and references to fuller published descriptions are
given. Inevitably many of these were out of date on the
book's publication, if not before, such is the rate of change
within the industry; nevertheless, the range and diversity of
software now available is well indicated, and has the
same sort of cumulatively dizzying effect as did the Software
Fair from which this part of the Yearbook had its origins.
If you want to know where you might find hieroglyphic fonts
for the Apple Macintosh, a Modula-2 compiler for MS-DOS, or
just a variety of Writers Tools for teaching 'composition
skills', this is the place to look.
</p>
<p>There are also about sixty extended descriptions of
software or resources felt to be of sufficiently general
interest or major importance within particular fields. In
such cases any editor must tread gingerly the boundary
between advertising hype and detailed evaluation; the
selection of which software deserves such trentment is also
invariably contentious. Thus, for example, in the Historical
Studies section the only product so singled out is the prize-
winning 'Would be Gentleman', a historical simulation of
seventeenth-century French social mobility; less
eccentrically, in the section on Classics, the Thesaurus
Linguae Graecae rates detailed attention as (however) do
three assorted micro-based systems for drilling Latin grammar
into computer-wise students.
</p>
<p>The book's twenty-eight unevenly-sized major sections
are arranged alphabetically. Some sections are highly
discipline-specific, while others are on topics of general
interest. By far the largest section (8Opp.) is that on
Languages and Literature, closely followed by two other
related sections Text Analysis (33pp.) and Computational
Linguistics (31pp.). Sections primarily of relevance to those
with a linguistic or literary bent amount to about over half
of the total. Sections of general interest (Hardware and
Software Resources, Database systems, Bibliographic
resources, People and Places, Programming Languages and
Statistics) together amount to about a quarter. That leaves a
total of about 5O pages for the also-rans, chief of which is
Historical Studies (15pp.), followed by Philosophy (lOpp.),
Music (6pp.) Archaeology (Spp.), Art History (3pp.), with
Drama and Folklore getting a page each. Where a
particular reference might be considered either of
general interest or discipline specific, the latter generally
takes priority. Thus Manfred Thaller's Kleio database system
is discussed in the Historical Studies section rather than
the database section; on the other hand, the Toronto old
English Dictionary is discussed in the general section on
lexicography rather than the section on old English.
</p>
<p>Medieval Studies get a section on their own, whereas
the study of all other historical periods is subdivided by
place, from I5.1 Austria to 15.15 Yugoslavia. Apart from
being of little use to one searching guidance on, say,
computer-aided work done in historiography, demography or
urban history per se, this method of division gives a false
impression of the coverage in this section, which is
reasonably thorough, if not as complete as more specialised
bibliographies such as those published hy the Cologne Centre
for Historical Social Rescarch; although the journal
Historical Social Research is cited in the reference
hibliography at the start of the volume, it does not seem to
have been as well abstracted as (for example) the
publications of the Association for History and Computing,
even in the section on German History. Equally conspicuous by
their absence are Historical Methods and the Journal of
Interdisciplinary Studies. Computational historians need to
confront the epistemological issues raised in such journals
and by such major works as Barzun's Clio and the Doctors or
Fogel &amp; Engelman's Road to the Past, neither of which is
mentioned here. Supplemented in this way, and preferably
reorganised chronologically rather than topologically,
this section would provide an excellent set of pointers to
the current state of historical comptlting, at once thorough-
going and non-partisan.
</p>
<p>The book's taxonomic eccentricities would not matter,
of course, it it were adequately cross-referenced or indexed.
Regrettably however there is no overall alphahetical index,
even to authors cited. There is a 16-page reference
bibliography, in itself an impressive catalogue of resources,
and an alphabetical index of software and software
developers, rather marred by some niggling inconsistencies in
such matters as abbreviations and cross-references. OCP is
indexed under OCP with a cross-reference from 'Oxford
Concordance Program', but TLG is indexed under 'Thesaurus
Linguae Graccae' only. There are two columns of references to
universities, alphabetised under'University of. . .' (which
is silly), and while Project Pallas is cross-referenced from
that for Exeter, the entry for DISH stands proud of any
association with the University of Glasgow.
</p>
<p>The most significant shortcoming of the Yearbook is
the lack of any single alphabetical list of authors or
projects cited. In its absence, the reader must guess into
which section likely citations will have been placed,
and then search the alphabetical lists of references and
resources in that section for useful items. This means that
it is easier to find, say, all the software published by
Microsoft than all the articles written by, say, Martindale
(except where he is cited as developer of software) — which
surely cannot be right. It provides needless aggravation
for those who do not share the editors' view of the
structure of their field, or are simply unaware of the name
used for it. In this volume, for example, 'Second language
instruction' is a distinct field from 'English as a second
language', while 'Creative Writing' is concerned with
interactive fiction and poetry generation, not to be confused
with the 'Text Generation' which is a subclass of
Computational Linguistics, nor in any way associated with
'Editing and Publishing'. Of course, establishing a subject
classification for an emergent discipline is no trivial task
and the editors deserve every credit for having attempted it
(I find particularly felicitous their having reserved a
section called'Visionary Devices'under'Computing Resources');
however, until there is general agreement on the boundaries
and internal divisions of the Yearbook, the absence of a
proper index looks suspiciously like preemptive action,
fossilising the potential of this new discipline at the point
of take-off.
</p>
<p>Nevertheless, this volume is to be heartily recommended. There is no
comparable publication, either in depth and breadth of coverage or
overall accuracy. As a snapshot of the current ferment of activity in
scholarly applications of information technology, and within its
selfimposed limits, it has no equal and no research library is
complete without it.
</p><trailer>
Lou Burnard Oxford University Computing Service
</trailer></div>