<!--
From:	OXVAX::LOU          "Lou Burnard" 14-JAN-1991 10:12:27.91
To:	CBS%UK.AC.CARDIFF.COMPUTING-MATHS::RALPH
CC:	LOU
Subj:	RE: Book Review

Review to go under heading Computing Milieux.
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tzonis">
<head>
Hermes and the Golden Thinking Machine, by A. Tzonis
(MIT Press, 1990). 
Price #14.95 h/b; ISBN 0262200767; ix+284 pp.
</head>
<p>This book is almost as irritating as it is possible for a first
novel to be, without actually being printed on poison ivy. It
purports to be a novel of ideas, purporting to be a detective
story, in which the protagonist, despite a state of the art
laptop and a conveniently eager protegee, fails apparently to
solve a mysterious crime. There is much atmospheric rendition of
various unsavoury and variably pretentious intellectual
characters drawn from the murky world of archaeology and
antiquarianism, and quite a bit of purple prose describing the
weather of contemporary Athens. The hero begins the novel
apparently suffering from jetlag, and never seems to fully
recover from it, which, together with his overwhelming world-
weariness and sense of his own intellectual superiority does
little to encourage the reader into making the imaginative leap
necessary for even a `wonderful send up of deconstructionism'
such as the blurb proclaims the work to be. There is a great deal
of indubitably clever talk about the nature of mental processes,
about epistemological concerns, about the capabilities and
limitations of artificial hermeneutics (the hero's name is
Hermes, geddit?), as well as a few bloody murders. Some useful
diagrams introduce us to various AI formalisms and there is a
bibliography, largely of secondary sources from which partially
digested ideas concerning computer models of cognition, vision
analysis, semantic nets and frames, analogical reasoning and
interpretation appear to have been taken. All this, however, is
not enough to make a novel, or even to poke fun at the notion of
the novel itself, in the absence of narrative. Plots there are,
in abundance, but they collapse into self contradiction as soon
as they are seized on.  At the centre of the book, both
physically and conceptually is a confrontation between two views
of literature - as a hermeneutic exercise or "zero-knowledge
game" and as a way of representing intelligence in action. The
writer would probably wish to be identified with the latter point
of view; regrettably this reader at least places him in the
former camp. </p>
<trailer>
Lou Burnard
Oxford University Computing Service
</trailer>
</div>