<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Blogging</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>AMOW</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-11-14">First draft started</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="2021-11">
            <head>November 2021</head>
            <list type="gloss">

               <label>Tuesday 2nd</label>
               <item>Take 14h train from TM to Stratford International via Paddington and Kings
                  Cross; check in to cheesy Premier Inn at Stratford International. Get distracted
                  by interesting exotic upmarket food shops in that end of Westfield shopping
                  centre, where I buy some proper rye bread for Al and Betty, also some diwali
                  sweets ditto. Then stroll to their gaff in goodish time to pick up first Coco from
                  nursery and then Daphne from after school club, which is all very pleasant and
                  domestic. Likewise an evening at the Kayes. Back to my hotel box by 1030. And so
                  to bed.</item>
               <label>Wednesday 3rd</label>
               <item>Breakfast reasonable but I am too anxious to enjoy it. Catch packed commuter
                  train at 0945 to St Pancras, and then Off we go, 2 hours ahead of departure time,
                  for the 1230 eurostar to Paris. Much queuing, but it all goes quite smoothly,
                  since everyone is expecting it and we have oodles of time to waste. Journey to
                  Paris just as unremarkable as it should be. I am seated at the very end of the
                  train in carriage number 1, which means I have to walk for MILES when we pull into
                  gare du nord, but no matter. Then by metro 4 to Montparnasse. Plenty of time to
                  pop into c&amp;A to buy some enormous but warming pyjamas, which will be needed
                  soon. Plenty of time for the 1726 tgv to Tours, a journey without incident. Check
                  in to the familiar comforts of the Grand Hotel, where everything is just as it
                  should be. La Chope is closed, so we dine at the Brasserie de l'Univers, which is
                  absolutely packed, but the food is good (magret de canard) Or maybe it's packed
                  because the food is good. </item>
               <label>Thursday 4th</label>
               <item>Up at 0730, out of the hotel, grab a creme et un croissant at the Dakota bar en
                  route to CESR, arriving in plenty of time for my 0900 Introductory talks. Lunch
                  for all has been booked at a large establishment in the picturesque old town
                  square, currently packed with tourists of course. The service is slow and
                  begrudging, even though Sandrine had forewarned them. The food is unremarkable: I
                  wanted fish, which only came in the form of some scraps of salmon on an industrial
                  pizza. As compensation, dinner at the bistrot du marche with Elena et al was
                  delicious, after which she gives me a lift home and much cahier gossip.</item>
               <label>Friday 5th</label>
               <item>Up at 0730 again, meme jeu, since today is my teach-nearly-all-day day (see
                  timetable). Lunch was in the same depressing place, but the service was express.
                  In the evening we dined en masse upstairs at La Piazza, which was pleasant, though
                  mass dining experiences are always a bit of a strain. </item>

               <label>Saturday 6th</label>
               <item>Up at 0730 AGAIN, sigh, but this is the last day, and I don't have to do any
                  teaching, just mop up after the others. Lunch as usual. Too tired to go out for
                  dinner with Alexei though I probably shoulda. Bought a scarf from Mistigriff
                  (6.99) cf every other shop I looked in at 30 or 40... Tried to get into the Yellow
                  dog (no room), so fell back on La Maison Berbere which served a really charming
                  couscous and mint tea. </item>

               <label>Sunday 7th</label>
               <item>A leisurely breakfast at the Grand Hotel, tho the scrambled eggs are long past
                  their best by the time I get to them. Sit in the lobby with laptop for an hour or
                  so, overhearing lady booking three successive visits up till April. Apparently the
                  GH sees iself primarily as a conference venue, since their competition is all the
                  snazzy new hotels down the road like the Mercure have stolen the commercial trade.
                  And so to the 1222 departure for Poitiers, stopping at countless improbably named
                  hamlets, like Villeperdue, which it clearly isnt, and Futurescope, which it is to
                  be hoped it isn't. And at Poitiers, an easy 14 minute change for Limoges onto
                  another little TER full of polite students and schoolkids. And here we are in
                  Limoges, trying to get to the B &amp; B hotel, which is not as easy as you might
                  think. It's about 50 metres as the crow fies, but crows can fly better than me.
                  The staircase which once led down from the station front entrance to the road
                  where the hotels are is decidedly hard to find and when you do, it is officially
                  sealed off and condemned, unsurprisingly, since it is falling apart. The way to
                  get down there is of course not to start from here, but from the side exit from
                  the station, through the bus station, across the car park. Of course. And I am
                  then faced with an extremely unfriendly automat to do the checkin process since no
                  human being is on reception duty. (They did turn up later, but were slightly less
                  friendly than the robot). Set off in search of food, since I forgot to bring any
                  lunch and it's now getting on for four pm. In Limoges, on a drizzly Sunday
                  afternoon, lifted slightly by a beautiful and unexpected art nouveau palace half
                  way up one of the many hills which characterize this urban architecture, which
                  seems to be holding some sort of local artist exposition. As I slog on up the
                  hill, I find several places offering drink or fancy cakes but nothing like food
                  unless I want to wait till six pm, which I do not. I press on and eventually reach
                  the Cafe de Paris, which being a simulation of a real Parisian brasserie, is ready
                  to serve real food almost any time of day. Hoorah. Burger Maison and frites and a
                  glass of rouge for me thanks. After which I feel much better, and stroll all the
                  way back down the hill to the B&amp;B box without further incident. </item>
               <label>Monday 8th</label>
               <item>Breakfast at the Hotel B &amp; B is minimal, like the hotel, but only costs
                  6.50. Do what I can to get my money's worth, then walk out across the carpack and
                  up into the station, then down again to platform J where my little two carriage
                  TER is waiting for the first journey of the day, to Gueret via Saint Sulplice.
                  Quite a few other passengers. At gueret, I trundle my bag successfully to the
                  Centre 23 Frais, which is of course closed because it's Monday. Grumble a bit and
                  schlep suitcase on into town centre to do a minimalist shopping at Monoprix (milk,
                  butter, ham, bread, a few veg). Then coffee at the Moderne before the trusty TAD
                  arrives. Hello house! Hello sun! Hello grass that needs cutting... Concentrate my
                  efforts on initially on getting a fire going and making a comfortable clean bed to
                  sleep on. </item>
               <label>Tuesday 9th</label>
               <item>Walk into Bussiere to get some more food from JeanLuc, not that he has much it
                  being Tuesday. Also Benoit is shut. Never mind it's still sunny. My amazon
                  delivery arrives while I am walking back, so when I get home I can use new saw to
                  make some more firewood very satisfying. </item>
               <label>Wednesday 10th</label>
               <item>Woken infeasibly early (i.e. 0830) by UPS man delivering recycled printer. Walk
                  into Bussiere AGAIN, this time getting some fresh veg from the lady who sets up
                  her stall outside the church on Wednesdays. Locally grown proper veg. very cheap
                  and a nice chat. Also get pills for itchy legs from Pharmacie, steak from JeanLuc,
                  and a chicken leg from the butchers. Benoit is open for lunch, but it will take 20
                  minutes to heat up his fish fryer, so I settle for a bavette and frites instead.
                  No other customers to speak of, but it's early. Back home I have another go at
                  getting my bill into Chorus Pro, and also realise the extent of my folly in not
                  having purchased any toner for printer. Of course it's not included. And of course
                  it's no use ordering it now, because tomorrow is a jour ferie so no-one will
                  deliver it before Monday.</item>
               <label>Thursday 11th</label>
               <item>A public holiday. Chorus Pro disdainfully rejects my first attempt at a bill,
                  but does not deign to explain why. Spend an hour or two trying to submit a version
                  of the bill it will accept (i.e. with no TVA). Console self with lunch of sausage
                  and lentils, delicious, and the sun is shining enough to sit outside and eat it.
                  TV aerial conked out in the middle of Asterix movie, curses. </item>
               <label>Friday 12th</label>
               <item>Rose at 10. Coffee machine unco-operative, seemingly because when I tried to
                  decoke it yesterday I left it running with no water for too long. Curses. Fall
                  back on the bialetti machine. Hacked some more overgrowth off the shed to
                  encourage the vine. Sorted out firewood a bit. Lunch on pasta with sauce of ham,
                  leaves, tomato, rather nice. Bother. Shawn appeared and gave me a barrowful of
                  logs he had nicked from the place he works. Very satisfactory. We arranged to meet
                  for beer later on, and I gave him a jar from my small stock of home made bramble
                  jelly. Around 1745 I set off to walk to Bussiere, through the dark but with my
                  trusty phone torch to show the way. Very peaceful walk with no boggarts or
                  surprises. At Benoit's Shawn and Lisa drinking quietly in corner with someone
                  called ?Don, a musician. Two beers and a chat. Shawn holds me personally
                  responsible for the evils of the internet. Lisa is not going to work for Deidre,
                  no thanks. After a bit realise I am drunk, which is nice. Lisa then drives us
                  home, so to bed by 11. </item>
               <label>Saturday 13th</label>
               <item>Stayed in bed till 10. It's raining. Breakfast in my warm corner after checking
                  that it's too wet to do anything outside today. Cleaned up kitchen a bit. Did some
                  laundry. Worried about the chauffe eau. But the coffee machine has fixed itself.
                  Spend most of the morning writing an XSLT stylesheet for @catoMinor whoever that
                  is. They want to convert a biblStruct as output by Thing to simple text. formatted
                  according to some project specific rules which are not all actually feasible,
                  because not detectable from the markup. By the time I've got it working, it's
                  lunch time, late lunch time. I am having my steak today and (whisper it not in
                  Gath) some proper chips, as well as the rest of the green leaves. To complete the
                  weekend's decadence, a glass of wine. Watch another Public Eye, and then start
                  this blog, since it's still warm in my typing corner.</item>
               <label>Sunday 14th</label>
               <item>Stayed in bed till ten. Why not. Read some more Cahier witterings. Put my
                  chicken leg in the kitchen to roast and go out for a virtuous stroll round the
                  lake, since it's not actually raining and I havem't done this yet. Lake is
                  deserted : fishing season closed at the end of October. Trees and mist looks like
                  a parody of autumn. Go and check on Deidre's wood store, since she is nagging
                  Lilette to nag me to give her some: predictably she has more logs than I do. Back
                  home in time to slightly overcooked chicken and enjoy it with a glass of wine. The
                  chauffe eau seems to be behaving itself better, and (once I have reinitialised
                  everything) so is the telly. Settle down therefore beside my roaring log fire to
                  enjoy North by Northwest, on Arte-tv. Or rather, "La mort aux trousses": Cary
                  Grant speaking French is all part of the fun. In bed just before midnight,
                  reflecting that I seem to thrive on this simple routine, of minimal breakfast,
                  adequate lunch with much veg, and porridge and prunes for a bedtime snack. I even
                  wrote a paragraph or two of introductory talk. </item>
               <label>Monday 15th</label>
               <item>The day begins gray and drizzly and doesn't get any better. I do my duty,
                  tidying up, consuming everything that can be consumed and throwing the rest away.
                  I even sweep the floor, but draw the line at moving the carpet which I claim is a
                  two person job. After lunch of courgette-based fritata, I find myself numerous
                  mindless organisational tasks, like copying files from the raspberry to a stick so
                  I don't lose them, writing emails, booking tickets for the next few stages of this
                  odyssey, etc. but cannot screw myself up to do any proper work. Shawn arrives
                  about 16h50 which is a little tight for the 17h28 departure from La Souterraine,
                  but we get there with a few minutes to spare. Lots of people on board, every one
                  of them masked. And so, on to Paris, a journey I haven't done in quite a while.
                  The Intercite train is no better or worse than it has always been... as likewise
                  the long haul on ligne 5 to Gare de l'Est where I am overnighting at the Ibis on
                  St Laurent street. All checked in, I forego the free drink in favour of a stroll
                  round the block to an expected surprise pleasure i.e. the Batifol, which almost is
                  a "pleasure mythique", being an impressively reconstructed genuine Paris bistro,
                  with friendly and enthusiastic staff, who find me a quiet table to enjoy my cheesy
                  pasta dish and a glass of Bourgogne Aligote before I waddle back to bed. Hoorah. </item>
               <label>Tuesday 16th</label>
               <item>Standard Ibis (France) breakfast i.e. boil-your-own egg in lukewarm water,
                  drinkable coffee, industrial baked goods. But nice jam. Go up and down three
                  flights of hotel stairs to check the state of my health: not good. Undeterred, I
                  set off up the familiar rue Magenta, buying decent bread en route, amd resisting
                  the atavistic urge to pop into the Marche St Quentin. For a 1315 eurostar, they
                  say you need to get there by 11.15, which seems mad, but if you believe them at
                  least the checkin process is less tedious and comparatively quick. I get through
                  two passport checks by machine and two by human beings in under 15 minutes, so I
                  have time to queue for a second breakfast sandwich from M. Paul. Then a long wait
                  during which I tinker with Cahier data, and eventually off we go. The usually
                  uneventful Eurostar on this occasion was forced to slow down and stop in the
                  middle of nowhere (well, Normandy) allegedly by sangliers on the track. It set off
                  again ten minutes later, presumably as a result of intervention by Obelix, but we
                  still arrived 15 minutes late, much too late for me to catch the 1502 train to
                  Bristol. My belief that this didn't matter and I could just hop on the next one
                  was put to a severe test by various GWR functionaries and ticket gates (I will
                  spare the details) but justice eventually prevailed, thanks to Andy in the
                  ticket office at Temple Meads and I returned home having only paid 10 quid to
                  upgrade my cheapo ticket, rather than having to buy an entirely new one (36 quid).
               </item><label>Wednesday 17th</label><item>My diary is uncertain as to whether we are going to Nottingham today or tomorrow. The traintickets say it's today, the hotel booking says tomorrow. Belinda sends us a text promising venison burgers tomorrow which seems decisive. I proceed to spend most of the day catching up on my Cahier work,trying to get Vodafone to stop billing me for the broadband I disconnected in September, and of course getting my useless train tickets refunded. The last of these turned out to be a coupleof clicks on the website, while the second was a total nightmare, involving hours of waiting in call centre hell, three different mutually incomprehensible agents, each with only limited abilities to actually do what I want done. The first took a decided turn for the better when Elisabeth pointed out that the program has been changed. And of course when I actually focussed long enough to produce some draft remarks.
               </item><label></label><item></item>
               <label></label><item></item>
               <label></label><item></item>
               
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>

   </text>
</TEI>
