<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="Report-1983-11-30">
 <pb facs="https://github.com/lb42/Works/tree/master/Reports/Pages/img456.jpg"/>
   <head type="report">Visit Report</head>
   <head type="location"> Strand Palace Hotel, London</head>
   <head type="event">ICLCUA CAFS SIG Open
Meeting</head>
   <head type="when"> 30 November 1983</head>
   <head type="report"> ALSO PRESENT P Salotti</head>
   <p>This was
that rare occasion, a CUA -sponsored meeting at which no-one was after
ICL's blood With characteristic low cunning the company first put up
an odious marketing person to draw such offensive remarks as the
audience could muster (chiefly "What about TP?" and "When?") and then
lob them over to Hamish Carmichael to be dealt with after lunch Mr
Gershon (for it was he) is much addicted to the use of ACL (Audible
Capital Letters) and so we were repeatedly told that CAFS-ISP was now
offering a real End User Capability at a Highly Competitive Price; he
also kept referring to it as the Product of the Decayed" which can t
be right, even if Vic Maller has left the companyAs regards price
however, it is depressing to learn that we could (now) buy a whole DSC
complete with CAFS for the cost of the add-on DFC CAFS module i.e
£35k.</p>
   <p>The next speaker was Roger Hare, an equally paradigmatic
Man from West Gorton, who acquitted himself well in the extremely
boring task of detailing the history of the CAFS-ISP field trials,
including such minutiae as the number of bugs and the dates each was
cleared Instructively, we were told that there had been over two
hundred (sic) bugs in Querymaster (variously abbreviated throughout
the day as QM, QRYM and QYRM) and about half a dozen each for VME
8.10, IDMS350, DDS650; one (one) hardware failure had required a
change in the CAFS microcode Of the nine field trial sites, one (one)
had gone live - the day before the meeting by an odd coincidenceAll
had had ample evidence to justify the performance claims previously
made for the systemSeveral technical queries were also handled by this
speaker, mostly to do with the impact of CAFS searches on concurrent
TP systems, which is predictably pretty dire.</p>
   <p>Lastly before
lunch, Peter Drake of Southern Water spoke briefly about the working
party on high level interfaces to CAFS, in which we are also
involvedHe did little more than outline the history of the group,
express gratitude for ICL's helpfulness in setting it up and promise
that the Report would be finished by January.</p>
   <p>The lunch was high
on protein, but low on flavour and I spent half of it in the pub with
some policemen I learned from S.George (QMC) that their CAFS would be
used if at all as a means of supercharging existing IDMS databases,
that they were very worried about concurrency problems and that
installing VME release 8 was a pig I also ingratiated myself with one
Ian Turner, whose title is Marketing Innovation Manager within UKD
Marketing and who is, significantly, a Kidsgrove Man This means that
he is willing not just to countenance but even actively to support the
"Death to the Dictionary" heresy This maintains that CAFS should be
accessed via the low level RSI rather than via the baroque orthodoxies
of Bracknell Man Consequently we are now on the list for field trials
of PSAM, RCI, RSI, Textmaster and ANONP (another non-nameable
product).</p>
   <p>After lunch we were given a tantalisingly brief
account of progress on the Inland Revenue's COP (Computerised PAYE)
system The purpose of this is not just to catch up with Paul
Griffiths, but also to provide a national facility for each tax office
to be able to translate names and addresses into National Insurance
numbers Eventually it will use 47 2966s with 18,000 DRS terminals
accessing about 250 FDS 640s (Laughter) The first of its 47 regional
systems went live in October The interesting aspect for us is that
they use a purpose-written interface to the ISAM RAM, using the RSI,
thus giving the lie to Bracknell Man's assertion that everything must
be done via the Dictionary.</p>
   <p>The next speaker, from Nottingham
Borough Council, had enjoyed his lunch rather too much to make any
very intelligible criticisms of Querymaster, particularly as nearly
everything he complained of was a direct consequence of trying to use
a 1960-style database of flat files as if it was an IDMS system and
also of behaving as if CME was a real operating system instead of a
transition aidAnother speaker from Southern Water (which is the one
site to have gone live with CAFS) gave an impressive account of their
field trial experiencesThey had used QM (QRYM or QYRM) on a 105 Mb
database and even in this cumbrous software environment could report
vast performance improvements.</p>
   <p>Finally, two ICL speakers Andrew
Hutt (on behalf of Bracknell Man) and Hamish Carmichael (on behalf of
the human race) summarised the state of play. Hutt asserted that QM
without CAFS could search 250 records a second, and 4000 with it
Carmichael, who is much better at PR, proved that a 2966 with CAFS
could read at one mile an hour as follows.  The upper limit for one 2966
is six CAFS units, giving you a total maximum database size of 121
gigabytes, i.e roughly the equivalent of 5 miles of library
shelves. This would, he claimed, take about half an hour cpu to scan the
lot. Hutt said how happy he was that at last ICL had made CAFS an
integral part of the company's development plans; Carmichael said how
happy he was that further developments were already underway at
Kidsgrove (i.e not Bracknell) and even non ICL software houses. This
oblique reference to ANONP clearly augurs well for our early
involvement with the RSI, an impression confirmed by Turner's interest
in our proposed packaging of an SPSS interface using PSAM.</p>
</div>
