<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Digital Technology: Its Role in Humanities Research Research</title>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Originally published as a blog entry at <ref
            target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/users/louburnard">| arts-humanities.net: Digital
            Humanities and Arts</ref> on <date when="2008-10-14T12:35:00">Tue, 14/10/2008 -12:35
          </date></p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020023">TEI version for archive</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>

    <body>-->
<div xml:id="Report-2008-10-14" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <head>Digital Technology: Its Role in Humanities Research Research</head>

      <p>David Shepherd of Sheffield's Humanities Research Institute welcomed a respectable number
        (I counted about thirty at the start, and more people drifted in during the morning; the
        registration list has 48) people to this second workshop organized by the fledgling Network
        of Expert Centres in Arts and humanities. He stressed that the object was to increase
        awareness of and participation in the network by those who were not, in his phrase, the
        usual suspects. He also expressed skepticism about the existence of digital humanities as a
        discipline distinct from the humanities proper.</p>
      <p>The first session, chaired by Michael Pidd, showcased some impressive achievements. Bob
        Shoemaker discussed the Old Bailey Online (<ref target="http://www.oldbaileyonline.org/"
          >www.oldbaileyonline.org</ref>) project, and its successor, Plebeian Lives, very much from
        the point of view of the historian: how far had the availability of such resources changed
        the discipline? Earlier studies had necessarily focussed on individual sources, and were
        thus limited to the perspective of those institutions responsible for them. A significant
        consequence of large scale digitization of related sources of many kinds might be the
        opportunity to see individuals distinct from the institutional processes through whose
        records they pass; we might thus learn how marginalised or criminal elements played these
        institutions off against each other, as well as identifying the factors which shaped the
        development of modern social policies. He suggested that 18th Century London was probably
        the most digitized time and place on the globe (a claim later queried by Alastair Dunning);
        he also stated a major theme of the day: the problems and opportunities afforded by the
        possibility of linking different records derived from this wealth of disparate resources.
        And remarked that the traditional model of web publication is now outmoded: maybe resources
        of the scale now contemplated can be more effectively sustained by crowd-sourcing and Google
        advertising.</p>
      <p>Michael Meredith, an HRI researcher, demonstrated the delights of Virtual Vellum (see <ref
          target="http://www.ahessc.ac.uk/virtual-vellum"
          >http://www.ahessc.ac.uk/virtual-vellum</ref>) This e-science demonstrator has developed
        some open source imaging software in use for a number of collaborative manuscript
        digitization projects. Once you've seen a Froissart manuscript shipped across the access
        grid and displayed on the entire back wall of the
        <lb/> HRI with the clarity of detail this system supports, you won't want to use anything
        less. Honest. I was blown away. He tried to address the theme of the day by assuring us that
        everything he did was driven by
        <lb/> the needs of the researcher, but I don't think anyone was really convinced. This was
        just technology so cool we needed Stephen Fry to do it justice.</p>
      <p>Ian Gregory from Lancaster gave a more persuasive pitch for Geographical Information
        Systems (GIS) as the lynchpin of cross-resource integration, again with some very nice
        examples demonstrating how GIS
        <lb/> maps do more than simply present data in a nice and visually digestible form; they can
        also draw attention to anomalies that need explanation, and thus question established
        orthodoxies in historical
        <lb/> or literary explanation. He gave several quick examples (I wanted more), including
        some comparative work on the lakeland tours of Gray and Coleridge (see <ref
          target="http://www.lancs.ac.uk/mappingthelakes">www.lancs.ac.uk/mappingthelakes</ref>)</p>
      <p>Some specific points I picked up during a lively pre-lunch discussion were:</p>
      <list type="unordered">
        <item>can any ordinary computer cope with these images? (Yes, but you get what you pay
          for...)</item>
        <item>is cross searching of different resources really so important? (Yes it is, and we
          should ask librarians for help in doing it)</item>
        <item>do we really need any more digital resources? shouldn't we be doing more with the ones
          we have? (No-one answered that one, except by implication: Yes, and yes)</item>
        <item>do you need to be a GIS expert to use it? (No: look at Google Earth)</item>
        <item>shouldn't digital technologists and scholars be working together rather than in some
          kind of master/slave relationship? (Yes, obviously; it's just hard to achieve the right
          balance of expertise)</item>
        <item>how will we manage rights in a web2 world (See JISC-funded web2rights project)</item>
        <item>will these solutions for sustainability, of resources, and of tools really work? (who
          knows: David Robey asserted gloomily that open source is not a magic bullet)</item>
      </list>
      <p>After lunch, during which (as is traditional) I met for the first time some people from
        Oxford working on an interesting Oxford project, we were presented with two more rigorously
        infrastructural presentations. First up was Martin Lewis, who gave a well-rehearsed and
        rather eloquent pitch for the strategic and political importance of the UKRDS -- a
        feasibility study for a new National Data Service which HEFCE has funded (see <ref
          target="http://www.ukrds.ac.uk/">www.ukrds.ac.uk</ref>). The word "cyberinfrastructure" is
        new and some of the other jargon has also changed, but otherwise this didn't seem to differ
        that much from the pitch that Harold Short and I used to launch the AHDS back in the late
        stone age. It was useful, but unsurprising, to know that the OSI had "bottled out" of
        producing a road map for setting up an e-infrastructure for the UK despite the availability
        of numerous OSI-commissioned reports defining exactly what that might seek to accomplish.
        Let us hope that this feasibility study is more successful: we shall know at their launch
        conference in February next year.</p>
      <p>Alastair Dunning then presented an overview of relevant JISC initiatives with his customary
        attention to detail; the fact that JISC is now the major funder of digitization efforts in
        the arts and humanities may also have focussed people's attention. Although no more large
        scale digitization programmes were discernible on the horizon, he suggested that there was
        scope for innovative projects in data mining (the so-called million books challenge), in
        enhancing usability by developing better metadata and by better marketing of existing
        resources, and above all in making them interoperate better. Humphry Southall's Vision of
        Britain site (<ref target="http://www.visionofbritain.org.uk/"
          >http://www.visionofbritain.org.uk</ref>) was mentioned again as an example of joined-up
        thinking and outreach to the wider community. What kind of framework do we need to emulate
        that for the research community, and how is that community actually using these resources?
        We need a more complex technical infrastructure, supporting expertise and skills as well as
        multiple platforms. And dont forget e-learning! digital resources are loved by teachers and
        learners alike; their use typically raises important methodological issues; and the relevant
        government department thinks the UK should be a global leader in this area. So it might
        stump up cash, who knows.</p>
      <p>Discussion after this was less lively, perhaps because I am not alone in finding the word
        "cyberinfrastructure" oddly soporific. Here's a random selection of the points I noted:</p>
      <list type="unordered">
        <item>does anyone really have a coherent policy about which resources should be digitized?
          JISC pays attention to focus groups and potential users, and especially to special
          collections librarians, but there doesn't seem to be any grand plan anywhere. Maybe we
          don't need one.</item>
        <item>the RDS seems to be make a sharp distinction between "data sets" (which are its
          business) and "e-publications" (which are not). Some might argue that today's publication
          (or orphaned website) is tomorrow's dataset.</item>
        <item>Intute is past its sell-by. (I did my best to refute this rather surprising
          claim)</item>
        <item>EEBO has completely transformed the study of the "early modern period"; would there
          ever be anything comparable for the medieval period. (Err, probably not)</item>
        <item>Should librarians be driving the UK's digitization programme? (I suspect they are,
          actually, but there weren't many present to confirm or deny this)</item>
      </list>
      <p>In the final session of the day, Sylvia Adamson, a professor from Sheffield's school of
        English, rather bravely took the floor to feed back her impressions of the
        humanities/digitizers divide. A self-proclaimed technological dinosaur, she has considerable
        experience of cross-disciplinary wars in her own research field, which straddles the
        traditional "lit" and "lang" divide. She suggested that the way forward might be to engage
        non-believers on their own turf and in their own terms, rather than promoting further
        schism, citing her own case as an example of "what you're up against". Maybe the Network
        should facilitate a reservoir of expert speakers who could be fielded in appropriate
        discipline-specific research seminars to spread the good word. Other speakers agreed, though
        one noted that the real problem was that "our literary-based colleagues" remain much more
        focussed on product than on process, and were thus hard to interest in the research benefits
        of integrating digital resources. As for the "digital orphans" it was suggested that care
        for these was traditionally a job for the library.</p>
</div>