<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <!-- 
  <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
          <title>Digital Community Building a  la
            Francaise</title>
          <author>Lou Burnard</author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
          <p>Originally published as a blog entry at <ref
            target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/users/louburnard"> arts-humanities.net: Digital
            Humanities and Arts</ref> on <date when="2008-10-20T21:28:00"> Mon, 20/10/2008 -
              21:28</date></p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
          <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
        <change when="20200223">TEI version for archive</change>
      </revisionDesc>
      
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <body> -->
  
  
<div xml:id="Report-2008-10-20" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" >
  <head>Digital Community Building a la Francaise</head>
   <p>I find myself once more in France. The food, the weather, the
wine, the cheese, are all pretty good, and so is the discussion of
digital humanities. Today I gave an invited plenary to kick off a
week long event on digitization in the humanities, funded by the
CNRS through the TGE Adonis, and organised by three of the French
Centres of Expertise which I mentioned in an earlier posting here.
You can read all about the event on its wiki pages at <ref target="http://www.cn2sv.fr/ecole-sources-num">http://www.cn2sv.fr/ecole-sources-num</ref>,
if you read French; here I will only very briefly summarize some
interesting aspects that struck me, as the sole non-French person
present. First off, I was very impressed by the community-building
aspects of the way this event has been organised: the idea seems to
be to bring together experts in very different kinds of digital
resource (spoken, visual, textual, manuscripts...), provide them
with brief accounts of best and current practice, and to foment
debate and interchange of views. There is a training aspect,
naturally (the event is billed as a summer school, of sorts), but
above all it is an opportunity to form contacts and discuss some
more profound issues of how exactly the humanities should react to,
contribute to, and profit from mass digitization. The participants
come from a large number of research institutions, small and large,
as far as I can tell all funded by the CNRS, and have in common an
active engagement with the procedures, and demonstrate an
impressive range of skills and knowledge in this very lare area.
There are plenty of webheads and technical people, but also some
genuine scholars. The event is organised as three distinct courses
(one on oral data, one on visual, and the third on written
materials), each course comprising three workshop sessions, but
organized in such a way that each participant can participate in
two different courses, since each session is repeated. There is a
formal feedback session at the end of each day, which gives ad hoc
groupings of participants the opportunity to report back on the key
issues that have emerged for them. An interesting approach, in my
view, though the proof of the pudding will be in the days to
come... Today, Yannick Maignien gave an excellent overview of the
goals of the TGE Adonis project and I wittered on about the history
of "humanities computing". The whole
is taking place in sybaritic surroundings, with excellent wifi, and
other creature comforts. Vive la France!</p>
        </div>
      