<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Community building en France -- la suite</title>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Originally published as a blog entry at <ref
            target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/users/louburnard">| arts-humanities.net: Digital
            Humanities and Arts</ref> on <date when="2008-10-27T09:56:00"> on Mon, 27/10/2008 -
            09:56 </date></p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="20200223">TEI version for archive</change>
    </revisionDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <!--<item><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/project">Projects</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/ictguides/methods">Methods</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/tools">Tools</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/library">Library</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/noc">Centres</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/community">Community</ref></item>
<item><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/news">News</ref></item>
</list><!-\- /header -\-><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/">Home</ref><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/blog">Blogs</ref><ref target="http://ahnet2-dev.cch.kcl.ac.uk/blog/louburnard">lou.burnard's
blog</ref><div>-->
      <head>Community building en France -- la suite</head>

      <p>Days two and three of the <ref target="http://www.cn2sv.fr/ecole-sources-num/">Ecole
          Thematique</ref> I attended in Frejus last week (regrettably I had to leave on day four,
        thus missing the afternoon excursion to the seaside) were rich with matter. Each day began
        at nine sharp with a "state of the art" plenary presentation, which was followed by parallel
        sessions focussing on one of the three kinds of media in question -- manuscript materials,
        oral texts, or images. Although there was a natural tendency for each expert speaker to make
        their presentation fairly "one way", and in some cases also over-ran their allotted time
        rather drastically, there was a conscientious effort to provoke debate and discussion from
        the floor. A reasonably long lunch hour (and some excellent French food) also kept morale
        high and engaged. At the end of the day, participants summarized briefly the chief points of
        the communications they had witnessed; this seemed an idea worth stealing. (It would also be
        nice, but less practical, to steal the chef and the kitchen)</p>
      <p>The wiki of the Ecole includes all the presentations, so I won't try to summarize them
        here, other than to note the range of topics addressed. In the plenaries, Christophe Jacobs
        was provocative on the "vulgarisation" facilitated by digital resources and its implications
        for modes of teaching and research while Catherine Morel was exhaustive and authoritative on
        the varieties of XML metadata. In the first session on written materials I attended, Paul
        Bertrand (IRHT) and Florence Clavaud (Ecole des Chartes) introduced us to the theory and
        practice of their digital cartulary (cartulR) in some detail. TELMA is both their
        collaboration and an open source "plateforme" for TEI corpora they are are jointly
        developing; they seem to be relying chiefly however on an EAD-based cataloguing system
        called Pleiade. There was some discussion about the problems they had encountered using
        Exist to handle large scale textual resources, and whether or not to switch over to using
        Philologic; and more about familiar problems of data entry. After lunch (rack of lamb; did I
        mention the food already?) I went to the first session on visual material and learned about
        a wonderful digital archive containing images of Lamarck's original specimen collection, and
        the complete papers of Ampere (currently being painstakingly transcribed by retired EDF
        functionaries), but was chiefly treated to a demonstration by Robert Vergnieux of some
        applications of GIS in classical archaeology notably a virtual Circus Maximus. For the third
        workshop session of the day, I returned to the text course for a decidedly pragmatic
        presentation from Thierry from the webmaster's perspective: how should resource builders
        ensure their labours are citeable, what standards are relevant, etc.</p>
      <p>On the second day I attended an excellent workshop session from the CRDO's Michel Jacobson,
        giving just enough detail about the relevant standards in the world of metadata for spoken
        rsources (DCMI, OLAC, IMDI, etc.) for me to feel that this time I really do understand how
        OAI-PMH works and how to interface it with a bunch of TEI headers. No, really. His colleague
        Richard Walters gave a similarly thorough overview of the technical and theoretical issues
        involved in making and deploying transcriptions of oral materials: I wrote down as a
        usefully quotable comment his statement on the thornier theoretical issues: "I have no
        opinion but I want consistency".</p>
      <p>After lunch on day two, we had brief introductions to some basic questions about the notion
        of interoperability, and to XML and friends. These were a little too short to cover
        everything, and soon ran out of time. There was a French take on that old favourite "how to
        make a TEI document with Oxygen and Roma", which was a lot of fun, not only for me but also
        for the participants, who all seemed to enjoy the experience of getting their hands dirty
        with some real tagging at last. (The session I attended was also enlivened by some
        accidental damage to the curtain rails by an over-excited Paul Bertrand). Those attending
        the practical session on using Pleiade which went on in parallel didn't seem to be having as
        much fun, but maybe I'm biassed. At the end of the day Michel Jacobsen gave a magisterial
        overview of what OAIS is, and how they are using it in the CRDO. This also managed to hold
        my attention.</p>
      <p>I'm not sure how to translate "ecole thematique": "special-interest summer-school" doesn't
        quite do it justice. But in any case, this was clearly a new experience for many of those
        participating, not just for me. The organisers had done their best to escape from
        traditional French pedagogic models, and to bring into being a new kind of interdisciplinary
        context appropriate to the very diverse resources concerned. They also worked hard at
        ensuring we were not sold short on their varied technical expertise -- no sign of any
        vulgarisation there. Of course, some things didn't work as well as they might have (the
        timetabling was occasionally chaotic for example, and I think people might have enjoyed more
        practical work than it permitted); but this was an excellent experiment which I hope the
        organisers will be encouraged to repeat in a year or two. In the meantime. it will be very
        interesting to see how the wiki develops...</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
