<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2010-07-molesworth">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Molesworth: the early years</title>
<author>louburnard</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Self-published (WordPress)</publisher>
<idno type="URL"
>https://louburnard.wordpress.com/2010/07/26/molesworth-the-early-years/</idno>
<date when="2010-07-26">2010-07-26</date>
<availability>
<p>Originally published on WordPress.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from WordPress WXR export.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="category">
<term>humanities</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="tag">
<term>1940s</term>
<term>Literary History</term>
<term>Molesworth</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="post">
<head>Molesworth: the early years</head>
<p>Like most people brought up in the 1950s, I have always had a soft spot for
the work of <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nigel_Molesworth">Nigel
Molesworth,</ref> self styled goriller of 3b, whose outpourings about life at St
Custards struck a chord for anyone who's ever been a small boy in a large
institution run in what he suspects to be a not entirely disinterested or
benevolent manner. I had also always assumed (without thinking much about it)
that the four books by Geoffrey Willans and Ronald Searle published between 1953
and Willans' untimely decease in 1958 constituted, as the compendium volume is
entitled,  "the Compleet Molesworth" (published 1959, and reprinted to universal
acclaim -- except<ref
target="http://www.lrb.co.uk/v22/n04/thomas-jones/swete-lavender"> in the LRB
</ref>-- in 2000). But this turns out not to be the case, and not only because
of the continued presence of that indomitable spirit in the person who tweets as
@reelmolesworth. </p>
<p> The published Molesworth books brought together pieces which Willans and
Searle had published previously in a magazine called <hi rend="italic">Young
Elizabethan</hi>, an interesting title aimed at the generation not yet known as
teenagers, under the benign editorship of Kaye Webb, coincidentally Searle's
partner. But there is another and earlier Molesworth to be discovered, who
belongs to a still more distant generation. I found him the other day, while
browsing through wartime copies of the magazine <hi rend="italic">Punch </hi>
for another project. </p>
<p> Willans was a regular, if sporadic, contributor to Punch during the late
thirties and early forties. The majority of his pieces reveal the young
Molesworth in all his glory, almost fully formed as early as  1939. Some of the
characters may have different names, but much of the phrasing and all of the
attitude is already firmly in place. Here's a taster of the earliest piece I
found, dated 9 Aug 1939:</p>
<quote>
<hi rend="italic">May 6</hi>. Arrived back at school. Started to cry and went
into jim to wear it off. Ragged in jim but was stoped by Mr Trimp (headmaster)
and recived conduc mark chiz. Rember have some cigs in plabox and endevore to
remove them but Mr Gates (geog) sees me and says what have you there, nothing
sir honestly, I say you can see if you want to sir. He say I trust you
molesworth but he follow me when I go out chiz. Will have to wait. Went on
raging and mucked about and after tea went and had reeding Mr Trimp read Dr syn.
Quite a good book every body gets murded. Mr Trimp says it will be fine tomow.
<hi rend="italic">May 7</hi>. It rained. <hi rend="italic">May 27.</hi> Morning
frightful lessons. Weedy french Way Mr Trimp tells us to rember this je suis I
am a pot of jam Tu a he is a botle of fizz II est thou art an apple tart etc.:
Played cricket blowed three wide 8 no-balls. Caught Jenkins with a catch great
cheers rose. I am in fuste but have my cigs and slosh in order to get out. Hit
boundary and Mr Oates says well hit but keep a strate bat. I was l.b.w.(it shot)
and take cigs into rodendhon bushes but Mr Oates shout what are you doing in
there molesworth. Catching may bugs i reply. He belive me (sap) but not worth it
to light cigs then. Borrow Pearsons bat it has three springs and play tip and
run. I like foopbal bes.</quote>
<p>Here's another snippet, from the 27 Dec 1939 issue, giving us Molesworth's
take on the "phoney war": complete with tuough evacuees, air raid alerts, and
weedy nazis.</p>
<quote>
<hi rend="italic">Sept. 3. </hi>War declared. 3 tuoughs arrive from Bermingham
who are put in Spare room they are awful. They pute out there tongues at me so
when mum not looking i scrap them. Chiz. They overcome me but oldest blub and sa
he tell his ma. others say ya sissie then oldest hit them and all blub. Ern say
his father is a rober (swank) Arch runs about with no trousis he is not going to
be a gentlman and at cricket they all slosh and touogh each other up. <hi
rend="italic">Sept. 16.</hi> Uncle come in uniform weedy private. Now i say you
will haf to kill as many germans as the last war and as that was 5030 you will
be hard pute to it. Uncle tell how he kaptured ten germans on the Som but Ern
creep up and let off toy pistle with cap and uncle jump like anything three feet
actually. He chase Ern who hide in walnut tree but give Arch 6 Cheers Ern say
his father a murderer he murded 3 old ladies in their bath and strwth the blud
was awful. <hi rend="italic">Sept. 19. </hi>Arch has catpillar he has tamed. <hi
rend="italic">Sept. 24. </hi>Back to school weedy school. Peason and me we rage
in the jim and he say stinker (Mr. Cutler) and Sergent Buble also gone to join
up which is enough to pute the germans off. mr Trimp (headmaster) still here but
new master is awful as he deaf and face like a monky. Schwarz, german boy say
war is just british proper-gander and hitler win india paris and magninot line.
Deaf master agree with him but i do not think he hear. Fotherington-tomas has
brought back fairy cycle weedy. Mr. trimp say poland not really beaten. <hi
rend="italic">Sept. 25. </hi>7760400 secs to end of term. <hi rend="italic">Nov.
10.</hi> Air-rade warning. Masters tremble and scram, xcept deaf master who
asleep in his room. All boys very heroical and I offer cig card solder of the
british Realm to chap who hear first gun. Pearson avacutates white mice which he
sa very sussetptible to poson gas. We hear fighting planes— hurricanes—but only
deaf master snoring. At last Mr trimp comes and say all into the air-rade
shelter all to the shelter dubble. He dash in first (head­masters all the same)
and is knee deep in water cheers conduc mark laughing (manners) Very fusty in
shelter and white mice perish. We stand on benches but nazis do not come moan
groan they are weedy. <hi rend="italic">Nov. 18. </hi>Schwarz has face like a
stuffed tomato. <hi rend="italic">Nov. 20.</hi> The new bugs are like girlies
awful ticks. They hold hands with deaf master and also Mr trimp and mr Gates
(geog). they belive in faires and santa claus. They tell deaf master stories
about Snow Wite and the 7 dwarffs and he say they are delightful (sap) Deaf
master rember about deten amo moneo rego and give me twice chiz. I get new bugs
in croner and make them scrap Schwarz. He say wait till hitler gets to
London.</quote>
<p>If like me you have access to an almost complete run of Punch up to 1945, you
can find Molesworthiana at the following locations: <table>
<row>
<cell>10 Apr 1940</cell>
<cell>pp 408-9</cell>
<cell>Molesworth Detective</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>15 May 1940</cell>
<cell>pp 532-3</cell>
<cell>Molesworth and the Wicked Grandmother</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>3 July 1940</cell>
<cell>pp 10-11</cell>
<cell>Molesworth the Problem Child</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>20 Nov 1940</cell>
<cell>pp 498-9</cell>
<cell>Molesworth and the Battle of Britain (concludes "10000000 secs to Xmas and
boo to Germans")</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>5 Feb 1941</cell>
<cell>pp 144-5</cell>
<cell>Another Slice of Molesworth</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>2 Jul 1941</cell>
<cell>p 17</cell>
<cell> Molesworth Excelsior</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>6 Aug 1941</cell>
<cell>p 112</cell>
<cell>Molesworth Madcap</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>27 Aug 1941</cell>
<cell>p 188</cell>
<cell>Molesworth: Man or Beast?</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>22 Oct 1941</cell>
<cell>pp 354-5</cell>
<cell>Molesworth of Red Gulch</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>10 Dec 1941</cell>
<cell>pp 508-9</cell>
<cell>Molesworth the Fashionplate</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>24 Dec 1941</cell>
<cell>pp 564-5</cell>
<cell>Molesworth of the Remove</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>18 Mar 1942</cell>
<cell>p 219</cell>
<cell>Molesworth the Dog Fancier ("Mar. 7. Days wear on dogs bulls chickens and
land girls haf shoulders to wheel. ermintrude sa always darkest before dawn but
i am browned off i shall be in the army soon . Decide to run away to skool.
GOSH")</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>20 May 1942</cell>
<cell>pp 416-7</cell>
<cell>Molesworth and the Domestic Problem</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>29 July 1942</cell>
<cell>p 82</cell>
<cell>Molesworth's Jolliest Term</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>9 Dec 1942</cell>
<cell>pp 484-5</cell>
<cell>Molesworth or Little by Little</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>
<ref
target="http://www.penguin.co.uk/nf/Author/AuthorPage/0,,1000030746,00.html"
>According to Penguin</ref>, Willans may have also contributed Molesworth
materials to the now long-forgotten magazine <hi rend="italic">Lilliput</hi>,
but I haven't tracked any copies of that down yet. I wonder if I can persuade
someone to finance publication of the Molesworth Juvenilia? <hi rend="italic">o
go on on you mite</hi>
</p>
</div>
<div type="comments">
<head>Comments</head>
<list>
<label> Sebastian Rahtz: <date when="2010-07-26">2010-07-26</date>
</label>
<item>" I wonder if I can persuade someone to finance publication of the
Molesworth Juvenilia?" the costs are minimal. self-publish it as eBook through
Apple's iBookstore, charge £1.99, and the job is done. I can find a designer for
you.</item>
<label> Heather Cawte <date when="2010-07-27">2010-07-27</date></label>


<item>What a find! Good luck with publishing - I'd buy a copy :)))</item>
<label><ref target="http://www.lolpolz.com">Rebekka</ref>
<date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date></label>

<item>Is is out of copyright? I don't off the top of my head know the rules for
the UK, but life of the author plus x years is the general formula, so it
probably depends when he died. If not out of copyright you can't just publish
yourself as an ebook!</item>

<label> Lou <date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date>
</label>

<item>It's certainly not out of copyright, since Willans died less than 70 years
ago. Punch also may have rights in the materials, depending on the contract
Willans made with them originally. Punch was bought by the Al Fayed group a few
years ago, and they also own a small company which currently market
reproductions of the cartoons from Punch. I am starting my enquiries by
approaching the Willans estate though.</item>


<label>
<ref target="http://huskyteer.livejournal.com">Huskyteer</ref>
<date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date>
</label>

<item>I'd buy - and I'm sure if @reelmolesworth got involved we could raise the
funds in no time...</item>

<label>
<ref>Lou</ref>
<date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date>
</label>


<item>You know something about @reelmolesworth that I don't? Is secret
millionaire perhaps?</item>


<label> Bill S. Preston <date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date>
</label>

<item>Splendid stuff! I think I prefer Young Nigel as the hardened cynic of his
later years though. First the WAR then the PUKON and his TREENS is it one thing
after anuther hem hem i must sa.</item>


<label><ref target="http://pink-hebe.xanga.com">Jane</ref>
<date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date>
</label>



<item>Some of this turns up in the Punch Book of Kids.... Molesworth's Jolliest
Term is definitely in there.</item>

<label>
<ref>Lou</ref>
<date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date>
</label>



<item>Aha! that's interesting... thanks for the lead! The <hi rend="italic"
>Punch Book of Kids</hi> seems to be an anthology edited by Alan Coren in 1974.
I can see I am going to have to spend a few days in the Bod.</item>

<label> Robert Kirkpatrick <date when="2011-01-27">2011-01-27</date>
</label>

<item>Lou, Did you get any further with this? As you can see from my e-mail
address, I'm a Molesworth fan, and would love to see the Diaries
published.</item>

<label>
<ref>Lou</ref>
<date when="2011-01-28">2011-01-28</date>
</label>

<item>Well, I made some enquiries of the Willans estate (or at least the agency
which deals with them) and they didn't seem to know who had rights in the
material. I asked another literary agent of my acquaintance and she suggested I
should ask Mr Punch, but I am not too sure about who's pulling his strings (so
to speak) these days. She also suggested the society of Authors. The simplest
way forward might be just to post the material and see what happens :-) A blog
would seem the natural format... I can do that easily now I have all the text in
digital form. It would be nice to add some new illustrations and someone else
commented here that they might be interested in doing that. What do you
think?</item>





<label>
<ref target="http://www.katemanson.co.uk">Kate</ref>
<date when="2010-07-28">2010-07-28</date>
</label>


<item>Hi Lou, a chum of mine directed me to your post. I'm a Molesworthian
cartoonist who does a mean Searle parody - so if you fancy having your tome
illustrated, you can drop me an email...</item>


<label>
<ref target="http://www.lolpolz.com">Rebekka</ref>
<date when="2010-07-29">2010-07-29</date>
</label>



<item>Lou, glad to hear you're doing it properly! I'd be really happy to buy the
book if it gets published :-)</item>


<label> Robert Kirkpatrick <date when="2012-01-11">2012-01-11</date>
</label>

<item>I've just discovered that the copyright to the Molesworth Diaries rests
with Punch - who are still a going concern as a cartoon repository. I've had a
couple of e-mails to this effect. Are you still interested in publishing the
diaries? I'd be willing to help.</item>


<label><ref target="http://www.aol.com/ab4e1526797ddabf2b84b0c1c17eda74f3ab2d90"
>source</ref>
<date when="2012-06-06">2012-06-06</date>
</label>



<item>It seems to me that this website doesnt load up in a Motorola Droid. Are
other people having the exact same problem? I enjoy this site and dont want to
have to miss it when Im gone from my computer.</item>
</list>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
