<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="diaryPrint.css" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Oz notes</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
   <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
   <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
 <revisionDesc>
 <change when="2025-11-22">Converted from old web page to XML for Work</change>
 </revisionDesc>
 
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <list>
    <label><date>Monday 24 sep 2001</date></label>
    <item>Arrive Sydney a little early about 8 pm, and spot in rapid
    succession Alan M and Dave N. Mutual introductions, and we drive
    off to Sancta Sophia. Walk down to pub for a pint or so before
    collapsing.
    </item>
    <label><date>Tuesday 25</date></label>
    <item>TEI/Master Workshop: could have been worse</item>
    <label><date>Wednesay 26</date></label>
    <item>In the evening, Peter insists on taking us on ferry boat to
    ?, where we meet his mum, and proceed to a posh resto by the now
    invisibly dark seaside; a bit too pretentious for matty; he and
    i argue spiritedly about page images stoutly ignoring peter's mum
    and her aged friend, who therefore have to focus on creagh. i am
    falling asleep and want to get home to panic about my talks long
    before the taxi finally appears</item>
    <label><date>Thursday 27</date></label>
    <item><p>I give two plenaries, one at the start of the day and one
    after lunch about the BNC: both brilliant</p>
     <p>Afterwards, join D Pitti et al people for drinks in the Nags
    Head, followed by conf dinner in Indian
    resto on Glebe Pt Rd: heated argument on immigration issues with
    Ian Johnson, his charming oriental wife,  and Peter R. More
    interesting than the Burrowses anyway.</p></item>
    <label><date>Friday 28</date></label>
    <item>Last day of conf; I have to move rooms again, up to rm 215
    on top corridor. Everyone goes to dine at Toren's  house
    except me</item>
    <label><date>Saturday 29</date></label>
    <item>Wake late, shower in solitary splendour, wonder how I will
    find anyone to play with, and then Matthew and A-M turn up and we
    agree to  meet later for tourism purposes. I have time to walk down Church St
    to King St to get my haircut before meeting then again for
    expedition to the Botanic Gdns  (excellent lunch in posh resto;
    flying foxes; ) and ferry trip to
    Manly (a bit too late to do much but walk a little along the
    cliff). We drink a lot of wine in winebar on Glebe Pt Rd (Matthew
    insists on sending one bottle back) and then eat in very noisy
    thai restaurant, where the proprietor and A-M strike up
    friendship on basis of shared love for scandinavian
    furniture. Back home, I find secret instructiomns for how to get
    into my new luxury apt, and do so: goodness me, what a lot of
    space and gadgetry! </item>
    <label><date>Sunday 30</date></label>
    <item>Wake too late to find anyone much, though I just miss both
    Matty and Alan, and leave notes for both before returning to
    enjoy my splendour, shop for breakfast items, do washing
    etc. Around lunchtime, call David. Fail to connect my machine to
    the net in his office, but check email anyway. </item>

    <label><date>Monday 1st oct</date></label>
    <item>Public holiday. To Bondi Beach! To Chinatown, where we saw a
    dragon and bought opals. Was this the day we
    had delicious chinese vegeterian? </item>
    <label><date>Tuesday 2nd oct</date></label>
    <item><p>Dave rings to say he thinks the weather's too bad for an
    outing, but evidence doesnt support this, especially when he's
    finished whatever the lecture preparation panic was about. So we
    set off around midday, and drive down the Gt West Rd, to various
    scenic mountain spots: Wentworth Falls, and then Katoomba where we had
    steak and chips in beautifully preserved 20s restaurant, aptly
    named The Paragon. We do vertical
    mtn railway and swiss cable car along with many other japanese
    tourists, nice rainforest though. Back to the car just as the
    skies open and the thunder storm begins.</p>
     <p>In the evening, we drive to the Rocks, through the rain,
    interesting inner city urban renewal kind of thing, and a pub
    selling nice beer.</p></item>

    <label><date>Wednesday  3rd</date></label>
    <item><p>Got up, tidied up, reluctant to leave my palatial flat,
    but did so anyway. After 1000 re-negotiated a checkout time of 11
    with the Lancashire lass at reception, and almost made it. Walk
    across greens and the campus, dragging my stuffed suitcase to
    David's office. Kids are back, students everywhere. Had a coffee
    with David, checked my email, used the loo, left all the stuff
    with him and departed c. 1400 for Circular Harbour again</p>
     <p>Took Ferry to Manly again: this time, packed with holiday
    makers, mostly Oz or Japanese. Harbour views magnificent, sunshine
    beautiful. Arriving at Manly, walk across to the Beach proper,
    along street just like imagined English seaside town, and buy
    fish and chips to eat on the beach. Sun a bit sporadic, but enough
    of it to warrant sitting down doing nowt for half an hour or so;
    watch surfers in wet suits doing implausible things on top of
    waves, wonder whether or not to do more scenic walking, but not
    really enough time. Back on 1635 ferry, and then catch tube train
    to Newtown, wrong end of Kings road for David's flat, where he is
    packing. </p>
     <p>We get falafel sandwiches from the habibi, and wash it down
    with properly made and served delicious oolong tea, as per David's
    instructions from Meili. And then we get cab to the train for
    Melbourne.</p></item>
<label><date>Thursday 4th</date></label>
<item>Woken from fitful slumbers on lurching train by disgusting
     apology for breakfast. Never mind, we are now in Melbourne. Dave
     takes me on rapid tram-based tour for an hour or so, and we get
     some coffee, before I take next train off to Castlemaine. His
     mate that he's going to stay with has announced that Janine will
     be there too, which throws Dave somewhat. My train rattles slowly
     through the bush as I type the day's events. Jan meets me off the
     train. Meet Bernie, who's on night shift, and his bees; also 2
     dogs, 2 cats, 5 ducks, and a sheep. In the evening, attend Jan's
     rehearsal and slope off to pub across the road. </item>
<label><date>Friday 5th</date></label>
<item>Potter about in the morning. I could get to like this place:
     walk into Maldon for coffee. Home made pizza-like thing for
     lunch. Jan drives me to Melbourne again, where we eventually find
    resto. Strange dinner with their mum, (my long lost aunty Etty), Dave's asstd chums,
     Eva and Swedish husband. Jan and Dave take me back to airport in
     good time for return to business class space and time: flight is
     full, unfortunately, but I manage to sleep a bit. And so
     eventually, back to Bangkok airport where I have a trouser disaster. </item>
   </list>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>