<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/yes-it-can-be-done-ad5839dabc15-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Yes it CAN be done</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/yes-it-can-be-done-ad5839dabc15, published on Medium 2015-02-01 and translated from HTML to TEI. </p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>


<head>Yes it CAN be done</head>
<p>So there I was listening to the radio news on Saturday (17 January 2015), when they announced
that the channel tunnel had just been shut down on account of a flaming lorry (I
use the words advisedly: last time this happened, the continent was cut off for
weeks). Which was bad news for those, like me, planning to travel to Tours via a
tightish connexion in Paris the following day. I spent an indecent amount of
time investigating economically viable alternatives (bus to Heathrow, flight to
Paris, total cost one way in excess of £300, no I think not) and somewhat to my
surprise came up with the following. And here’s how it went.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*AvokzJBaplJqLFH1MvW8DQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>10:19 Bus into town</quote>
<p>It’s the one you can just see approaching over this chap’s shoulder. It’s
free. It comes every five minutes or so, though less often on Sundays. It has
wifi which occasionally works, and which on this occasion enables me to confirm
that Eurostar services are running, but with delays of “up to an hour”. A delay
of 20 minutes would be enough for me to miss my connexion at Montparnasse.</p>
<quote>10:35 Start walk across town from St Giles to the station…</quote>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*F3AGMynm6QCXI8GeS-FcKA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote><ref target="http://1">1</ref>0:47 arrive Oxford Station</quote>
<p>There is a bus reminding me that one day not so far away I will be able to
get to Marylebone via the Chiltern Line, but not today. Indeed, any thoughts of
a last</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*fmpD_xJS9SIREiti8gIiTQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>What’s wrong with this picture?</head>
</figure>
<p> minute change of plan in favour of the Eurostar route are firmly put aside
when I enter the strangely silent station building. Yes, it’s Sunday,
maintenance work is in progress, and there are no trains to London anyway. So I
settle down to wait for a train to Birmingham Airport instead.</p>
<quote>11:36 depart Oxford station</quote>
<p>(from platform 1, since it’s the only one working today)</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*YAsaOV0xe9tck4QVFGtsEg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>An encouraging poster greets me</head>
</figure>
<quote>12:40 arrive Birmingham International</quote>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*3U0nZ7TC2Gw75BdYfG0AiQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>12:45 Catch silly monorail across to the real airport</quote>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*PgO4Jn2epyQjIWnHRRgFig.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>12:55 Consider, briefly, the excessive amount of silly signage</quote>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*6E388DAfVAZLpzkavtGFTw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Pakora and lassi: excellent fastfood</head>
</figure>
<quote>13:05 : Catch a bite to eat</quote>
<p>I always arrive too early at airports. Last time I went through security at
BHI they found (but graciously permitted me to post home) an offensive opinel.
This time I forgot to extract my Samsung tablet from the backpack, and also to
put my toothpaste into a plastic bag. All of which meant that I just arrived at
the departure gate in time, somewhat breathless, as they were starting to board.
Airports, bah.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*im5HpkwKMgFpztVSvwfDrA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>All aboard, and waiting for blast off</head>
</figure>
<quote>13:42 Flight BE 3007 Non-stop Airbus A318 service to Paris is now fully
boarded and ready to depart</quote>
<p>(And despite code-sharing with AF1065, MU 8602, and indeed MK9337, the flight
was pleasingly empty) I concentrated on getting my slides ready, as per usual,
and almost failed to catch the moment when suddenly the clocks went forward an
hour, and the plane started its descent on to the solid ground of la belle
France.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*nobxECrohYBK2fPG0HoNCA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>15:57 (French time) the long process of landing begins</quote>
<p>And then of course, once they have let us out, we can start the endless
journey up and down and round about the twisty maze of corridors and zones and
terminals that is Charles de Gaulle Airport</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*n5R2aPGHUbxD_50JrBDT6A.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>16:08 Yes, it’s an airport: keep walking</quote>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*T2fYQqmlEJbk7tgWktx3BQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>16:15 Oh look it’s an escalator</quote>
<p>You are in Terminal 2 zone D, area K, and that is not where you want to be.
Keep walking.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*48cBgWvO-74ydgV4MkHiFQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>16:16 Oh how nice it’s a shuttle.</quote>
<p>Let’s see where this one takes us…</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*jZ63ZYfLX9Y0nuvqXiPYEA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>16:29 You are in Terminal 2, area B.</quote>
<p>Clever. Keep walking. The railway station is nearby, allegedly.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1_BDtSwmPnlvQpseMFRzNDtQ.jpg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>16:35 Just in time for the non-stop service to Gare du Nord!</quote>
<p>(Which is a distinct improvement on the trains that stop everywhere) Mind
you, it’s still the RER B, so it then goes on to stop everywhere subsequently.
Which is fine, since we are going to change trains at Saint Michel.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*QSgFr9grIUMKXtCnyGRciA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>17:19 Hello St Michel, ligne 4</quote>
<p>The RER is fast but subterranean and post-apocalyptic. The metro has more
charm, let’s face it, even la ligne 4 which snakes across the map like a lost
soul.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*ldFCGKVWerRKpvdxMFtoAw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>17:31 Dont forget to allow for that damnable tunnel between
Montparnasse-Bienvenue (the metro) and the Gare Montparnasse proper.</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*7VVZG8HPiW77OUeibKUPDA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<quote>17:35 Up the escalators to the real Gare de Montparnasse (1
&amp; 2)</quote>
<p>It’s still Sunday, but I have never seen this station empty. I am feeling
smug as it looks as if I am going to catch my 18:16 departure to Tours without
even breaking into a sweat.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*DtInyyJ4G1xKTCB0Rvyrew.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>And here she is. TGV 8327, all the way to Tours in first
class confort.</head>
</figure>
<quote>17:59 And so to carriage 13</quote>
<p>where I sit down and complete work on my talk for tomorrow. Well, nearly. The
gig is a re-run of one I gave a year ago, so it’s only a matter of reconciling
myself to not having improved on it much. And into Tours station we roll, on
time at 1930, giving me plenty of time to check in at my favourite Hotel, wash
my face, and get to <ref target="http://www.lachope.info/">La Chope</ref> in
time for an excellent dinner with Marie-Luce.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*P10_lk-a30n_SqezN8x2Ug.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Wild salmon and chicory. Much nicer than it looks in this
rubbish photo</head>
</figure>
<p>Conclusions? Total time door to door: 8 hours. Had I caught the Eurostar, it
would have been almost exactly the same. The cost was also much the same. All
the same, I took the Eurostar home — and even though they were still making dire
warnings about delays of up to an hour going through the tunnel (a week later!)
in the event it arrived back at St Pancras only 15 minutes late.</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
