<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/2016-in-review-dff802345b80-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>2016 in review</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/> using CETEICEAN</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/2016-in-review-dff802345b80 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2026-05-01">Reformatted for Archive</change>
<change when="2017-01-02">Originally published on Medium </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head>2016 in review</head>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*edwZC6HCsS3RmYz_eZqEkw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>This is me photographing me with my new phone in January 2016.</head>
</figure>
<p> It’s January 2 in 2017, and everyone is banging on about how 2016 was a
watershed moment in the history of everything. It was also a year which I
recorded in the form of diary entries. So, since that’s what blogs are supposed
to be for, here’s my record of what happened in 2016, starting in February since
January was mostly a washout.</p>

<div>
<head> February</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Weds 10 Feb:</hi> OXP to MYB enlivened by sheep on the line at
Haddenham, but plenty of time to get to StP for the 1230 eurostar to Paris. At
Austerlitz it is raining and we have nearly two hours to kill before the next
train to Vierzon, which is at 1652. The Jardin des Plantes being less attractive
than usual on account of the rain, we have a cup of tea in the nearest cafe.
Train is unaccountably late starting, and finally gets to Vierzon about 15 mins
late, where we meet Guy, already gesticulating with our host. And so rapidly to
the Hotel des Particuliers, two huge rooms in a palace, complete with garden and
chickens. For dinner we make a forced march back to the station and the really
rather good “Les petits plats de Celestin” (see review) .</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Thu 11 Feb:</hi> We travel by 1st class and Guy by 2nd (he
gets an entire carriage) to La Souterraine, where we pick up the bus to St Vaury
where our taxi awaits. Lilette persuades taxi driver (a native of Bussiere I
learn) to drop her in Bussiere, then drive me and Guy back to the house to
deposit bags, and back again in time for lunch at La Tilleule, which is potato
pie and chips, no really, sans blague. Back home by foot along the road, a quick
visit to the Brocante, and so on. In my post: a new SIM for my phone which Just
Works, hoorah, enabling me to request redelivery of L’s parcel, eventually.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Fri 12 Feb:</hi> Lilette’s boots are delivered. M Mauchassaut
comes to size us up for wood burning stove, and departs having left brochure and
dilemma: is it to be logs (more trouble to use, more expensive to install, but
looks much nicer) or pellets (idiot proof, easy to install, but uses electricity
as well) ? It stops raining long enough for a walk round the lake and some
desultory hacking down of old ground elder in the orchard. Apple trees need
serious pruning though. L makes delicious rabbit stew for lunch.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sat 13 Feb:</hi> TAD comes for us all at 0950. We are an hour
early for Guy’s train, so up the road to the much superior Brocante in Gueret
where G buys an ancient guide book, and we are impressed by availability of
cheap armchairs. It’s still raining, occasionally pouring, so the market is
hastily done, followed by ancient pintade disguised by sauce with chips, which
is all the so-called Grand Cafe offers for lunch, followed by a frustrating hour
or so trying to get my letsgo recharged and a phone line installed chez Orange,
which now combines the worst aspects of private and government agencies having
taken over France Telecom. We also take shelter from the rain in Monoprix, and
in the Musée d’art et archéologie de Guéret, before the TAD returns us and our
bulging caddy home again. It’s raining too hard to face the walk to La Tilleul
for the evening “St Valentin dinner” we had optimistically booked on Friday, so
we stay in instead.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 14 Feb</hi>: Less rain but very cold. Discover that my
phone as a hotspot is at least as good as the Huawei mifi letsgo gadget. Walked
round the lake. Quiet evening watching telly (Glossy French film adaptation of
“Un Secret” de Philippe Grimbert).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 15 Feb:</hi> Snowing for a change. After lunch,
experimentally switch on bread maker, which causes electric circuit breaker #12
to break. Somewhat confounded by this, as it happened just as Shaun and Lisa
turned up to attempt to solve Deirdre’s house entrance problem. About 5 pm, a
white van arrived bearing the huge box full of duvets and sheets despatched via
Parcel Monkey from Oxford last Tuesday (price £15 a snip for 20 kg). <lb/>  <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 16 Feb:</hi> L summoned the TAD and went to Gueret on her
own in the morning, while I pootled around doing TEI tickets instead of
preparing lunch. Delicious entrecote (bought at Gueret market on Sat). Lazy
afternoon. A bit of vine pruning. CME phones me back to help with internet prob
and also to offer cheaper credit card, hoorah. Watch fr comedy called “Vilaine”,
an amusingly sarcastic take on “Amelie Poudat”.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Weds 17 Feb :</hi> spurt of activity on the phone arranging
future trips. More desultory pruning. We walk into Bussiere, as weather is
lovely; crisp and sunny. Mauchaussat senior pledges his son’s attention to our
needs. Coffee at La T before we walk back feeling suitably smug. Yves and
Francine invite us over for drinkies ce soir. Made mistake of asking him about
La Creuse during the war, and was rewarded by brief lecture on the subject.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*3fyWDPljUUy3JK0VOA7tgw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Chairs huddle together in snowy back garden</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Thurs 18th fev:</hi> Up early for taxi to La Souterraine at
0915: snow has fallen. Jonathan delivers his devis before we go, total price
just under 4k as expected. Am emptying rubbish bin as alpha taxi arrives, same
taximan as when we arrived of course. Arrive at station 0935: train is only 5
mins late. Off we go: train recovers time so effectively that it arrives at Les
Aubrais 25 mins early, where it is held immobile as a punishment. We arrive,
very hungry (disgusting SNCF “bagel” notwithstanding) at Austerlitz and
foolishly buy the first sandwich we see on the corner of place de la Republique
instead of pausing for lunch. Never mind. Hotel de Paris offers us a kettle to
make tea, when requested. We are on 7th floor, accessed by means of a very small
lift. I leave L at hotel, and meet Florence in new building of Archives
Nationales; she tells me the backstory of the crowdsourcing event she’s
organising next month, and we discuss the binding schema a bit. Then back to
collect L and meet up for nice early dinner at Le comptoir Des Archives: I
recommend the coq au vin.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Fri 19th feb :</hi> manage to speak to Jonathan by phone. He
agrees that removing the old stove should be included in price, and asks for 20%
deposit. Or was it 30%? Anyway, a nice morning wandering about in le Marais.
Manage to find le marche des enfants rouges again and enjoy quick moroccan lunch
before heading back to Gare du Nord for the 1430 eurostar.</p></div>
<div>
<head> March</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">2–4 March :</hi> Quick visit to Paris to teach new improved
TEI ODD course for ENC with Emmanuel DuChateau. I stayed at the Timhotel just
round the corner, which was fine. As ever, the course was under prepared but
they seemed happy enough.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">14–17 March :</hi> Back in Paris, this time to give talk at
Archives Nationales at invitation of Florence. Can’t remember where we stayed. L
explored the area a bit, but mostly stayed in bed while I went to meetings.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">20 March :</hi> We set off for London, have nice lunch with
Elizabeth (Chutneys), and head for Stansted airport via tube and train.
Outrageous fee of 3 quid for 5 min bus ride for unwalkable journey to Premier
Inn. Good nights sleep, somewhat spoiled by text message arriving at 0600 to
tell me our flight has been cancelled.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">21 March :</hi> Groggily assess situation, and resolve to
fight on. So back to St P. where we pay enormous sums for a ride on the next
Eurostar, which is a nice new one, though full. In Paris there is time for a
large entrecote lunch before next train to La Souterraine, from which bus, and
taxi as per usual, arriving in time to admire full moon over the lake</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">23 March:</hi> TAD to Gueret, shopping for L; for me it’s the
1530 bus to Limoges, a loquacious taxi driver to Bellegard, and the 1810 flight
back to Stansted. Train, tube, bus, train, bus. Hello Oxford. Bed.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">24 March:</hi> get surprising amount done in the morning; then
off to Crem to pay respects to SPQR. In the evening back to London for a cheap
hotel overnight before my early start.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">25 March :</hi> Up at 07 on Good friday and back to St P for
0850 Eurostar crammed with small kids on holiday and harrassed parents. About 30
mins outside Paris, power fails and Eurostar grinds to a halt. Delayed for 90
mins, which means I miss onward connexion to La S. and have to spend an hour or
two lunching and pottering about Blvd St Marcel. AGAIN. Never mind, the train to
La S leaves and arrives on time, and Shaun is there to give me a ride home,
huzzah, and no more journeys for a few days.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">26 mar :</hi> Sunny walk into Bussiere Dunoise: lunch on
entrecote chez Benoit. That’s a bit better thank you.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">27–8 mar:</hi> It’s cold and windy and sunny, and occasionally
wet. Do nothing at all, unless you count fiddling with fotos, painting letter
box, desultory weeding. L not feeling well. Internet angst.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">29 mar:</hi> Phone Jonathan who says he is waiting for part,
and can start work next week. Instruct him to collect key from Shaun and where
to place poele. Mow lawns, phew. S&amp;L turn up about 18h to discuss making
potager, for which he proposes to charge me 100+ euro, and 50 for trip to
hairport.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">30 mar:</hi> L summons TAD and goes shopping, while I stay
home doing a bit more weeding, and writing my abstract for Poitiers. And not
very successfully getting lunch ready. Lovely sunny day. We even risk having
lunch in the garden. This is all going well, until I learn that tomorrows flight
is cancelled. And the trains are also cancelled tomorrow, mostly: la greve. Damn
and blast. Hastily plot alternative route: expensive taxi to La Souterraine,
last train to Paris, over night in Paris, first reasonably priced eurostar
tomorrow. And so it was.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">31 mar:</hi> After good night sleep in not too awful hotel in
the 10eme (Aulivia Opera), we find mauritian grocer in rue fbg st denis;
speedily visit cheese monger in marche st quentin, and then home in eurostar 2nd
class. Not too bad actually. I still feel cheated of my creuse time. Kev and SD
turn up to reclaim their car from our drive, full of delights of their trip to
Italy.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head> April</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">11–21 apr:</hi> Spanish hols with guy i.e. train bus tube
train plane to Madrid (OXP — STP — Warren St — TOM — SSD). And then lots of
train, <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/feveFever.html">see blog</ref>.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">24–29 apr :</hi> To Boston and Providence for TEI Council ftf
(bus to Gatwick, Norwegian air to Boston, MBTA train to Providence)</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>May</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">7 -14 May :</hi> Back in Paris again for ENC course with
Emmanuel Duchateau. Stayed at airbnb flat on rue Ordener which was quite nice,
though I did not clean it very well. Suffering from back problems slowed me down
a bit.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">15–19 May :</hi> to Caen for MRSH CS Meanwhile (I learned on
13th) Jonathan is coming to install stove on 17th. Shaun and Lisa are doing
garden in same week and Lisa will clean up before we arrive on Thurs. We
hope.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">19 May :</hi> arrive at Gare du Nord from St Lazare via RER E
a good 4 mins before Lilette arrives from Londres, even though SNCF is en greve.
Spend night at overpriced Hotel Devillas after nice Thai dinner in deserted
resto on Blvd St Marcel.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">20 May :</hi> Up very early for the 0840 train to La
Souterraine, connecting with the 1133 bus to St Vaury, where Shaun and Lisa pick
us up, drive to Coop for quick shopping, and thence home to see my new cabbage
patch in creation. Open door to find a poele installed and functional hoorah for
Mauchaussat freres, esp Jonathan who depannes us with a mass of logs about 7
pm.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">21 May :</hi> sun shines, but we still go TADding to Gueret
market to buy cabbage plants and meat. Back home to find Lisa still cleaning.
Chops and sausages for lunch. Later on Shaun drives to Gueret again to get peat
to improve soil, also garlic from coop, and a smart hoe for me to play with, as
well as a flashy power tool. Nice evening by the fire.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*dp6jxgAxE2cJLNqlD-c9wg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Lilette anticipating rain</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">22 May :</hi> Anticipated downpour delays sufficiently for me
to get all my jobs done, i.e. planting cabbages, tomatoes, cucumbers, celery,
row of left over potatoes, beans, and two kinds of chicory. Followed by mending
back door hinges (hence need for new power tool), and preceded by relighting the
stove. Large steak lunch followed by siesta ensues. We sit around in back garden
waiting for the downpour and watching the birds fly around most of the
evening.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">23 May :</hi> Johan eventually arrives to finish encarcerating
tuyau in bedroom, at which point I confess to my idiocy re outside light switch,
which he corrects. We go for nice walk round the lake at last, and lunch. Ppope
phones to confirm his imminence, and they arrive about 6 pm.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">24 May:</hi> Walk to Bussiere for lunch with Popes at Benoit’
s (bourguignonne for P and L, fish n chips for G and me): then back via scenic
route. Popes suitably impressed.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">25 May :</hi> Shopping expedition to Gueret, for hose pipes
and such. Lunch in the garden, in the sun.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">26 May</hi> (Genevieves birthday) Expedition to Anzeme, Bourg
d’Hem for lunch, also feat TEI Council, on to La Celle Dunoise for nice cup of
tea.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">27 May </hi>: (Fri) Expedition to Benevent L’abbaye for
lunch : shopping in Gueret much later than we should have, found mustard seeds
and returned exhausted.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">28 May </hi>: P&amp;I drove to Bussiere Poste to sort out his
mobile. Later, to M Bricolage to buy wheelbarrow and also briefly to Carrefour.
Hailstorm announces beginning of rainy season.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">29 May </hi>: Fete des meres; wheelbarrow is assembled and
used. Popes announce their day of departure is tues not mon. Rain continues.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">30 May </hi>: Dash to Intermarche in Dun for 20 minute shop in
the morning. Rain continues</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">31 May </hi> : Popes leave earlyish. We cope. Rain
continues.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>June</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">1 June (weds) :</hi> L TADs to Gueret while I cook souris
d’agneau for lunch. Rain continues.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">2 June (thurs) :</hi> we both TAD to Gueret. Rain
continues</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">3 june (fri) :</hi> amazingly, the rain stops. But the sun
does not come out. I plant the gooseberry bush we bought from monoprix
yesterday, attack some weeds, and generally potter, when not worrying about what
train we can catch tomorrow … cestlagreve.fr and indeed the SNCF have both
informed me that the reasonably timed 1030 train is not running tomorrow so we
will have to take the unreasonably timed 0930 one instead.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">4 june (sat) :</hi> Up VERY EARLY: clean up the house. Shaun
drives us to La S. in good time for the rescheduled 0937 train and insists on
taking only 20 euro for the ride. The route across country is twisty but speedy
and we get there by something ridiculous like 0900. Sit and wait with our
luggage. Train arrives late-ish and gets later because of power supply problems,
so we are into Austerlitz more or less the same time as planned, i.e. still
plenty of time to get across to Gare du Nord, find the Mauritian resto again
(it’s easy: top end of rue du fbg st jacques, just down from marche st quentin).
Since it’s lunch time, it’s packed with suspicious mauritians. Undeterred we sit
at the table and demand instant service which amazingly we get: a large plate of
biryani poisson. And so back to Nord, where I wave Lilette bye bye, and saunter
off to Montparnasse, to await my train to Poitiers. Which, as SNCF has already
proudly informed me, is a TGV and therefore unaffected by the strike. Poitiers
is of course almost as far away as La Souterraine, though slightly to the left,
so the journey is just as long. I join the mildly disgruntled queue of people
waiting for a taxi, but then after discussion (the taxi drivers are all
profiting from the strike by taking people on long journeys for which trains
are not currently available, allegedly) head off to the nasty civic escalators
(not working) and stairs up to the (comparatively) nicer 19th century stair case
built to link the town with the station. Puff pant. And reflect, not for the
first time, that they did a better job of building staircases for old farts in
the 19th c. And so, with the aid of Google Maps, and after a longish parcours
through downtown Poitiers, to my Hotel de l’europe, which proclaims itself as
HOTEL TRANQUILLE in huge reassuring blue letters. Which indeed it proves to be,
despite being right next to the main restaurant area and 5 minutes from the
enormous and entirely empty square in front of the Hotel de Ville. Burger and
chips for dinner, French stylee.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*JOlPtEAz9ZW-f2UdChc9WA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Interior of La Serrurie</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">5 june (sun)</hi> Poitiers. Mostly spent hacking at my talk,
alas. Found La Serrurie, the best place to have brunch in Poitiers and had it,
round about 3pm.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">6 jun (mon) :</hi> Along with nice biblissima lady I am guided
to the MSH by dragooned postgrad. Good thing as we’d never have found it
otherwise. It’s quiet, since not term time, and a typically huge campus. Settle
down to conference mode, as various talks are delivered. In the evening we are
all taken to dine at the not so marvellous maitre kanter on steak and chips.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">7 jun :</hi> give brilliant talk. We are taken to staff
canteen for posh lunch: not bad: some sort of elaborately presented game pie.
Everyone drifts away. I look at the horror which is some students dictionary
transcription.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">8 jun:</hi> leisurely breakfast and checkout of the Hotel
Europe [79.10] : a last stroll around Poitiers (Hotel Something; and of course
the cathedral, even though it is miles away down a hill). The sun shines. Panic
buy a short sleeved cotton shirt, very expensively. Coffee, then catch the bus
back to the station in time for the 1331 TER to Tours. My connecting train to
Blois (IC 14064) is cancelled because of the strike, so I have to wander about
the familiar environs of Tour station for an extra 45 minutes or so, many of
them spent drinking tea and watching the girls walk by. Blois has a nice free
navette running direct from the station up the hill into town, which I take
gratefully. Check into Hotel de Guise et de Guise, which is rather nice, creaky
floor boards, naff ancient décor, etc. [67.66 ]</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">9 jun :</hi> Do Blois, in particular its Chateau, despite the
heat of the sun which is still shining and despite the hills. A formule for
lunch at “Les 3 Clefs” but can’t remember what [24.70] Panic buy another short
sleeved shirt, this time in linen. Train 14064 is cancelled today as well, so I
am constrained to go back to St Pierre de Corps and try again, via a different
train Bordeaux-Paris. Which works. Get lost looking for Metro 6 at Montparnasse
as usual: eventually find it, despite the heat, and find way through rush hour
to Nation and the utterly charming Nouvel Hotel. Dine at Chez Prosper, ave de
Trone on fish and chips, yum. [26.80 with Chardonnay, and coco mangue
verrine]</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">10 Jun :</hi> Nice breakfast in the garden. Appreciate the
coolth and the fresh croissant and the (more or less) drinkable coffee. Shoulder
increasingly tiresome back pack and set off via RER A to Nanterre, along with
the other happy commuters at 0845. CS du Labex PASP. Sneak out about 17h45, and
struggle back to the new RER station, whence to Lyon, where I do not get lost
for once (exit 11, Maison de la RATP is the one you want if you’re planning to
struggle across the bridge to Austerlitz, which I am). Sit down in the sun and
pant for a while. Chat amiably with cigar smoking dude claiming to be the deputy
mayor of Limoges. Cut him short and search for tea before 1848 train departs
(another reschedule). It is only 30 mins late into La Souterraine, and there has
been rain hereabouts. Streets are almost entirely deserted, whether because it’s
getting on for 10 pm, or because everyone is watching les bleus thrash roumania,
who knows. Struggle up small slope into La S to find the Hotel Porte St Jean.
Which turns out to be run by an English lady. My room is large creaky, sparsely
furnished, but clean. [58.50 in advance please, plus the 15 already extracted
over the internet]</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sat 11 Jun :</hi> The serve yourself breakfast is minimalistic
and a bit sparse for 10 euros. Can’t complain as there’s no-one to complain to.
Down the hill again, now showing signs of commercial activity, and scattered
rain, absurdly early for the 0930 bus to Gueret. Do the market, within
constraints of what I can carry. Buy Lilette some chilli plants. Coffee in the
Cafe de la Poste is better than the Moderne, but nothing to grignoter. And TAD
it home, eventually, after long detour in wrong direction for another passenger.
House looks very clean, so I put on a week’s worth of washing, and consider my
options for a light supper: mushroom omelette, ancient salad, and fairly old
bread.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 12 Jun :</hi> Mow grass. Which takes most of day because I
am feeble, but looks much better when done. Indulge in orgy of internet shopping
for things to be delivered tomorrow. Dine on cod fish, carrots, and potatoe pie.
Light stove. TV still not working, so watch stored video “The Men who stare at
Goats” : quite good.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 13 Jun :</hi> And sure enough, the things are delivered,
just as I am getting up. A reasonably sized frying pan, a steamer, a top quality
blue boiler suit (l’ideal combinaison) which sadly does not fit, and an
ingenious agenouilloire for kneeling on when weeding, which does. Plant out
chilli plants, do some weeding (in the less rainy intervals). Cook frozen duck
(tough) with delicious saute potatoes. Phone Lilette to get birds eye low down
on the weekend girly caper. Light stove. TV still not working, so watch stored
video “Imaginarium of Dr Parnassus” : quite good. Ponder briefly Wim’s strange
taste in movies.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 14 Jun:</hi> A wild deer runs across the back garden as I
am peering out of the bathroom window pre-shower. That’s more like it. Walk into
Bussiere noticing the return of foxgloves to foxglove corner, some sheep, some
donkeys, and the return of some cherries on the tree at the end of rue Nichon.
La Poste does not have a printer so shamelessly exploit Benoit’s printer to
print the return label for the non-fitting overalls, which get into a box and
posted back to Mr Amazon just before noon. A hasty shop at Jean Luc’s, then
lunch at Benoit’s in solitary splendour on strange eggs in aspic, turkey leg,
chips. Corinne chats about their former pet goats while B reads the paper. And
so back home to await delivery of my shopping — mostly wine, but also bread, and
a spare bottle of gas. A spot of ironing? Why not. [60.81 Panier Sympa; 14.7
Benoit]</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Weds 15th :</hi> Finally realise why telly isn’t working. Fr
govt switched off TNT in non-HD end april. All I need is a new gizmo. Order one
from Amazon and then wonder how it can work if it’s squirrelled away behind the
telly. Banging away on Simple most of the day.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Thurs 16th :</hi> Peter, followed by Deidre arrive at an
inopportune moment, but that’s not their fault. Also, eventually, my new telly
gizmo arrives, is installed, and it works. There’s a little plugin IR sensor for
the remote to talk to, obvs. Dine at Deidre and Peter’s on rather good chicken
stew with potatoes and beans. Drink wine, chat, slope home rather late, light
stove anyway, watch stupid telly and into bed by midnight. Tomorrow must clean
up and pack.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Fri 17th:</hi> Wake late. Sunshine and showers, but not enough
of either really. Cook souris d’agneau for lunch. Tidy up, sweep floor, feel
sorry for self because have to leave. Experiment with slides in CETEI. Order
TAD. Light fire with firelighter.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sat 18 :</hi> Washup, lockup… up and ready for 1002 TAD which
perversely arrives 5 minutes late, and is a real bus driven by someone I’ve
never seen before. Weather is surprisingly nice, warm even. Bus takes scenic
route to Gueret, via Monneger, Longechaud, St Sulplice Gueretois, hoorah. Market
is busy. Briefly consider very fine leather jacket at only 570 euros, sensibly
buy nice sweets from nice middle eastern lady instead. She says she makes them
all herself and coming to sell them at the market is the only time she gets to
relax. Sit in sun outside Grand cafe and have a coffee. Wander round
backstreets, visit church for first time where someone is punishing the organ
big time, and someone else is praying. Happen upon exhibition of splendid
ancient musical instruments and buy CD. Decide maybe Gueret is not such a dump:
there are some parts that would be charming if they were a tiny bit busier and a
lot less hilly, eg the other market. Anyway, back to Place B and Le Moderne for
lunch, which is fairly unremarkable, though the ambience in the big back room is
pleasant enough and la petite serveuse est charmante. Walk very slowly indeed
down to the station. The Bar opposite which is open, but I cannot face any more
food or drink. Wait for my bus to arrive. Bus arrives only 7 minutes late and,
as expected, zooms along boring motorway to Montlucon, which has even more huge
horrible shopping centres fringing it than Gueret.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*VrFitFg8vsklAGRayoOycw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>Not the train I was expecting to catch at Montlucon</head>
</figure>
<p>At the station, a rare treat : a steam train, making the return journey to
Limoges from Montlucon as part of “le festirail de montlucon”. Lots of French
geeks, not so different from English ones, much photography. Large contingent of
ladies in traditional dress of some sort hanging out at the cafe opposite the
station.</p>
<p>And my train is already a quai! IC 3918 is going to Paris eventually, but
stops almost everywhere first, including Bourges. And it’s a proper train with
proper compartments, mostly empty, despite reservations. Sun continues. Fellow
passengers come and go. All very nice. I work a bit more on talks for
tuesday.</p>
<p>In Bourges, I see there are actually two trains due to leave for Nevers, the
first being signalled as 10 minutes late. This is the stopping train but it’s
still due into Nevers before the one that is due oin 20 minutes or so, so I get
on it. Unfortunately, it then sits at the platform unmoving for another half an
hour, by which time the direct train has arrived, so I swap to that. Which then
sits there unmoving for another hour and a half… It seems the previous train on
the line had a brakes failure and nothing is moving until that is sorted out.
Various friendly conducteurs inform me as best they can what’s going on, but a
delay of two hours is not the way one likes to end a long day, especially as
night is falling and I want my dinner. Up the hill from the station to the hotel
reserved for me by the discourgaingly named Albatross travel agency; which is of
course shut. And its starting to rain. Banging on the door effectuates an
entrance however and madame informs me where I might get something to eat round
the corner. It seems she was promised more guests from the delayed train, but
they have not materialised, presumably because they made the connecting train to
Clermont wait a bit. Eat a fairly nasty croque madame and chips, drink a glass
of drinkable red wine, and so to bed.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 19 :</hi> after very uninteresting breakfast, ten minutes
walk round Nevers confirms that it’s actually rather pretty, and worth a proper
visit some time. Back to the station, and all aboard the 0930 to Dijon. Which
rattles along at a fair speed across the rich burgundian countryside, fields
full of fat white cows, nice old churches etc. Too fast to take any photos so I
found nmyself wishing it would slow down a bit. For which thought I was suitably
chastised when the train got to ?, half an hour from Dijon, and announced that
it was going to be delayed by up to 15 mins because of signalling problems.
After ten minutes or so we set off again, at a crawling pace till we approach
Montchanin where it speeds up again, but is now 20 mins late.. will I make my
connexion in Dijon? The man assures me my correspondence is assured. As we
approach Dijon I notice that the stations whizzing by are all named after
wines : Meursault, Beaune, Nuits St George…</p>
<p>And in fact my correspondence is assured; they kept the train waiting for me
two minutes while I puffed from platform A to platform E. Which meant I didnt
get time to get a sandwich. Train proceeded to chug for an hour or so, stopping
at what I might have (with a fuller stomach) considered a delightful number of
tiny halts, before arriving in Besancon Viotte at 1327, just too late to get any
lunch. Grrr. And where is my reception committee? Grr. And it starts to rain.
Never mind, eventually (one hour later) JeanMarie and Jules turn up and collect
me for the drive out to Foyer St Anne.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">20–21 Jun:</hi> Do my bit (unchanged from a million years ago)
at MISAT, trying to explain why markup is necessary to bemused statisticians.
Eat lots of cheese under gaze of watchful nuns. Escape by TGV as soon as
possible.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">22–30 Jun:</hi> An action-packed week en Angleterre, beginning
with that Referendum and its appalling consequences. Louis got a broken arm for
his birthday. Lilette sang Bach Grand Mass in B mol in the Sheldonian which was
quite impressive. We went to Nottingham on a train for Louis’ birthday, staying
at Belinda’s house the night before and after. Then home to Victoria Rd for four
whole days, including an evening bemoaning the Referendum and Mr Corbyn chez
Bekhradnia.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>July</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">2–4 July:</hi> By train to Totnes (with a huge suitcase) for
another Winnie Wedding. We stayed in a rather posh B&amp;B called Blackster
Buckler House vel sim, formerly a large farm, run by elderly NZ couple, yis.
Drank devonian cider and eat steak for dinner in a pub. Went for healthy walks
along narrow lanes. Noted dominance of Organic Farming on (approximately) an
industrial scale. Wedding remarkable for Jonah the performing dog, vows of
considerable soppiness, and music, both dreadful (bride’s bruvver) and really
funky (the latter being provided by a band called Harare fronted by a marimba
player formerly with Bhundu Boys). Up in the morning on Sunday, and off to
London, and eventually (very hot) to Elizabeth’s new gaffe in Maryland, near
Stratford. Another version of London in London. Interesting. We dined at trendy
but inefficient resto in Forest Gate (Corner Kitchen, see reviews) and slept in
the Ibis, Stratford, which was just fine. Then train to St Pancras Intnl at
enormous expense, where we met E for a much nicer lunch at German Kitchen. And
so eventually back on Eurostar.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">4–6 Jul :</hi> Two nights in Paris, the first at the
surprisingly pleasant Tiquetonne Hotel, walkable distance to INHA where I am to
participate in a Paul Dermée meeting on the 5th. Paris is always Paris, but
never more so than round hereabout. Meeting goes reasonably well and I meet the
world’s only expert on Dermée, a Belgian called Schmets who is editing his
complete works. Collect L and off we go to Austerlitz to check into the last
hotel of the trip. Where I get my wallet stolen, sigh. Long pointless walk to
Police station Place d’Italie. Consolatory dinner of magret de canard et puree.
Start tedious process of getting cards replaced, stopped etc.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">6 July :</hi> Up very early and in time to get my carte senior
replaced at SNCF ticket office. 0840 dep from Austerlitz to La Souterraine is
packed with kids going on hols, but the weather is fine and even when the train
is delayed for some obscure reason… arrive into La S. with 40 mins delay, which
is just fine, since we have time to kill. Taxi whisks us and one other person
off to Gueret, where we have lunch in Le Bureau, which is open for a miracle.
And serves a reasonable approximation to a pub lunch. Then we take the bus into
Gueret proper, L goes to Monoprix, I sit in the sun and think how nice not to
have to do anything at all. Eventually, the 1540 TAD collects us and here we are
back home and it’s still sunny.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">7 July :</hi> attack tall weeds with strimmer; mow lawn. That
takes up most of the day. Faffing about with fallout from loss of wallet
continues. Nice lunch of rabbit stew, nice snooze in garden. France beat Germany
2:0 on telly. We can get used to this.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">8 Jul :</hi> L TADs it to Gueret and I walk into Bussiere.
Sausage lunch, nice snooze in garden from which we are woken by Shaun and Lisa.
Shaun obligingly hacks a path through the weeds at the back as a present for
Lilette. Walk round the lake clockwise.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">9 Jul :</hi> Mystery box for L is delivered by TNT before 10
am. Tie tomatoes to stakes. Trev comes to look at my garden, followed by Val,
followed by lengthy chat. Walk round the lake anticlockwise.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">10 Jul :</hi> Quiet day, mostly. Riz de Camargue for lunch,
with tasty chicken sauce. Walk with T&amp;V into Bussiere in time for dinner at
Benoit’s which is covered in bunting and excitement for this evening’s
euro-final. Meet strange Nottingham lady who has bought house by church. Drink
beers. Watch an ENTIRE FOOTBALL MATCH in which not much happens unless you count
Ronaldo blubbing. Walk back in the dark, about midnight.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">11 Jul :</hi> get up v late, huzzah. Do some more weeding.
Review task list for La Vergne. Shaun and Lisa come to discuss decorating house:
probably 2 weeks work, at 120 day. They will probly start in Aug.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">12 Jul :</hi> get up early to catch TAD, and spend an hour or
so at the Police Station making my formal complaint about being robbed, so I can
send it to bank, so I can get some of money back. A quick shop at Monoprix, and
back home for nice lunch of rice and leftovers. L not feeling well. I spend most
of afternoon trying to find out why I cant install stupid french phone app:
still none the wiser.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">13 Jul :</hi> My new gold card arrives, huzzah. Walk into
Bussiere to post letters to bank. Lunch on steak and excellent chips from
Benoit. Weather a bit chilly, so not much done in garden, apart from planting
out mint in a pot.<lb/>  <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">14–16 July :</hi> Bucolic calm rules.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 17th :</hi> Village fete! Two bands! Great excitement and
a fair amount of pink wine.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 18th:</hi> Very hot. Zampolli prize news hits TEI-L.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 19th:</hi> L took TAD to Gueret to return/change shorts;
I made her lunch of steak and chips. Finished and sent SPQR piece to B Beeton.
In the evening skyped D Birnbaum re Vilnius teaching.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Wed 20th </hi>: very hot. Shaun came and massacred orchard.
Back to working on Simple</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Thurs 21:</hi> Discovered monster nest of hornets in shed and
wondered what to do about it. After a late lunch Shaun and Lisa drove us to
Gueret; bought 250 euros worth of paint for decorating house. Paid S a
downpayment of 360 for the work he will do start of next month.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Fri 22 :</hi> Sowed some meche and some radishes and some
coriander. Weather warm but overcast. Still working on Simple. Nice fishy lunch.
Embarked on major walk over the hill to the Vedrine memorial after tea.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*VGZltEGeoG9spKoU_Fyoyg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>This memorial commemorates Jules Vedrine, famous French flying ace, who
landed his biplane here in April 1911 in order to visit his mum. Or
something.</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sat 23:</hi> L TADs. I poke more at Simple etc. Make duck for
lunch, a bit tuough. Planted flowers L bought in Gueret.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 24:</hi> Devoted to lunch with Yves and Francine, who
arrive at 13h and feast on anchovies, curried chicken, rhubarb crumble, fruit
salad, and tunisian sweets till after 16h. In the garden, in the sun.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 25:</hi> tidying up mostly, tho I did do a bit of
gardening.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 26 :</hi> Shaun comes at 0930: coffee in La souteraine’s
cafe de la gare which is open for once; train to Paris only 10 mins late; worked
on birnbaum talks; metro to Nord relatively painless; find nice Indian lunch for
5 euro/head chicken biryani and dhall and fresh chillis… Eurostar in cattle
class, but not too bad, quiet enough for me to do procmod table for simple. 205
bus arrives at bus stop same time as we do; train from MYB leaves 4 mins after
we have bought tickets for it. Home, pooped by 2030 or so.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head> August</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">27 Jul to 21 Aug </hi>: Another action packed few weeks en
Angleterre, mostly concerned with grandchildren : Louis stayed with us 20 jul to
1 aug; HARVEY GUY MARIO appeared on 6 aug, and DAPHNE MARIE JOSEPHINE somewhat
unexepectedly a week later. Brief trips to inspect both. See social media,
passim et seriatim. Hastily bought new pair of shoes in sale (45 pounds).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">21 Aug to 26 Aug :</hi> in Vilnius for El’ Manuscript,
teaching TEI with David Birnbaum, an interesting experience on several levels.
Regretted new shoes which made walking from Guest House to University a torture
till I had the sense to buy some new new shoes, with Tania’s help, from the
Vilnius market 45 euros.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">26 Aug </hi>: Say goodbye to sunny Vilnius drinking coffee
with Tania at the airport. Usual tedium of getting on and off a budget airplane
to Luton. Uneventful but exhausting journey from Luton airport to St Pancras,
tube to Baker St, foot to Americana Hotel, 78 quid for a very hot little attic
room and breakfast. But close to Marylebone where…</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">27 Aug :</hi> Meet lovely wife, freshly arrived from Oxford
Parkway at Marylebone station which is hot and crowded with happy holidaymakers.
Take a leisurely coffee before proceeding back to St Pancras by bus, buy some
lunch and some bread: reflect how nice not to be in a hurry, and so to a
deserted Eurostar lounge (it’s saturday) in good time for the 13h30 train to
Paris. Stepping off the train we are confronted by canicule: Paris temperature
has been over 30 all week. Still not in a hurry, we continue by metro to
Austerlitz, where all the trains are delayed “by meteorological conditions”. We
find a seat on a comparatively deserted platform, enjoying the occasional breeze
and wait for 90 mins or so for the 1840 departure to Limoges (should have booked
on the 1811 but I didn’t). Which is quite comfortable once the aircon starts
working, all the way to La Souterraine. Where we wait sit in the car park, and
wait some more, and more anxiously, for Shaun, who arrives just as I have given
up hope and am contemplating a call to the seedy hotel in La S. It seems he was
delayed by the fete in Bussiere-Dunoise, which has transformed itself into a
mini version of St Giles fair this weekend. And so to bed, in our very white
rooms, which smells very faintly of paint, though we’re too tired to notice.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">28 Aug :</hi> Wake late, breakfast later, it’s raining! But by
the time S&amp;L appear to take us to the Fete de Saint Symphorien it’s already
clearing up, and the sun comes out in force to welcome the dodgems and allied
delights of the fair now spread all along the village street. And especially the
carnival parade, featuring exotic dancers, and majestic floats populated by
small children distributing confetti on the assembled multitudes. The procession
is led by a large fake horse, pulled very slowly by a tractor; this is followed
by the exotic dancing troupe and their sound system; then comes a replica of the
Moulin Rouge, another of the Arc de Triomphe, and a third of the Eiffel Tower.
Not forgetting the large swan full of small girls in ballet costumes. We sit
outside La Tilleul and get through quite a lot of pink wine watching the crowds
and chatting. M. Mauchaussat snr explains to me that the Pompiers used to be
responsible for disposing of hornets nests but don’t do so anymore, though he
will ask Johan for me anyway. Further gossip ensues as the evening sets in and
we consume fish and chips with Lisa since Shaun has had a bit too much Beer
(much tutting). And then the walk home: a very nice welcome back. (but burnt up
a lot of my internet sending videos of dancers to whatsapp)</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">29 Aug:</hi> Wake late, breakfast later. It’s not raining, but
it is very overcast and stays gray most of the day. I go to take a look at
Frelonopolis which is now huge (about the size of a football) and covered in
inhabitants, one of which decides I look threatening (moi!) and goes straight
for my elbow. Ouch! These are nasty fellers and no mistake. Lilette cooks
delicious consolatory lunch of couscous and lamb tagine. We then inspect the
garden more carefully, and discover that the trees at the front are covered in
tiny little yellow plums, mirabelle plums. Just the thing for making jam, which
I spend the rest of the day doing. If the tree produces this much fruit next
year I will learn from experience and pit the fruit first. It’s tedious, but so
is trying to separate the pips out after you’ve cooked them.<lb/> Seven jars.
Good work.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">30 Aug :</hi> Wake early, breakfast late. It’s sunny! Phone
Banbury to try to get L’s op date shifted, with little success. Walk into
Bussieres to restock the store cupboard from Jean Luc’s emporium: get meat from
butcher, who is a new man, apparently taking over from Madame when she retires
in a couple of weeks. He has no front teeth, but apparently 20 years of
experience as a butcher in Croydon. Benoit’s shut so no lunch; on hearing which,
Mrs Jean Luc kindly offers us a lift back with our enormous shopping, mostly
liquids, in their nice new car. At home we see S&amp;L and a new English
acquaintaince John Farmer, a wood man. He is invited in to consider our kitchen
plank problem, and I give him a jar of jam to make sure he doesn’t forget us.
Rest of the afternoon, following enormous tortilla and pink wine, is spent
dozing or reading big fat novel (vol 2 from A Mars-Jones) in the sun. Sardines
on toast for tea. A busy day indeed.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">31 Aug:</hi> Went for blackberrying walk #1: along railway
towards Gueret, then over field to road, then down path towards Rissat and back
via campsite. Nasty moment navigating stepping stones over stream which was
still very wet and muddy, despite canicule.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head> September</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Thurs 1 :</hi> La rentrée. Up early in time to TAD to Gueret
Market, which is somewhat diminished, with a preponderance of small scale
producers/operators. Fine by me. We got cheese and plenty veg: also half a
rabbit from english couple selling free range home grown meats of various kinds.
And queued for potato pie, which was promptly eaten with sausages for lunch. A
siesta proved essential for most of the afternoon.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">2 Sept :</hi> Discovered fig tree in front garden and hacked
away competing bushes round it. Blackberrying walk #2 : thwarted by bogginess at
the start of the path up the hill opposite, but spend much time in adjacent
field anyway, nettles and brambles notwithstanding. Raked weedy undergrowth out
of concrete breakfast patio, revealing huge gaps and chasms which need sand and
cement to fill, which I claim is now all inaccessible in Frelonopolis.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">3 Sept :</hi> Walk into Bussieres to buy fruit from Jean Luc;
inspect house he is selling; retire to Benoit’s for lazy light lunch of mostly
salad and chips. See the Mauchaussat boys on their balcony and Johan promises to
come by later for de-frelonisation. Excellent. Saw a dead pinemarten on the
track home. Make two and a half jars of blackberry jelly. Johan does the
business at 6 pm sharp; Deirdre and Peter arrive for dinner at 6.30; and stay
eating meatballs and drinking wine till dusk.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">4 Sept :</hi> Did a fair bit of hedge trimming, weeding etc.
Nice pasta lunch. Weather overcast and boring. But still warm. Some email from
Guy. L worrying about her op date. Deidre gives us two horrible side tables. And
potatoes. Packing commences, also assemblage of bunk beds. This involves
unpeeling and decoding variously coloured sticky tape, and checking the bundle
of nuts and bolts for absence. Which we have. Beautiful red sunset over lake;
Peter sends me photo which I post to Instagram immediately.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">5 Sept :</hi> Packing continues, slowly. Attack the hydrangea
patch around the pear tree with a view to reducing incidence of nettles and
brambles therein. Also do some rose pruning. I really need to find out how to do
this properly. Continue bunk bed project by asking Kev for more nuts. L cooks
proper lunch of onglet, frites, green beans, washed down with a cote du rhone.
Indoors, since the sky is gray and overcast. But it lightens during my sleepy
afternoon. In the evening we dine in D&amp;P’s back garden on chicken and listen
to them bicker and reminisce and be snobbish about Val and Trev as night falls.
And so to bed.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">6 Sept :</hi> Up early for quick round up of things. Shaun and
Lisa arrive at 0930 sharp to whisk us off to La Souterraine, arriving 10 am, so
time for coffee and (had I thought of it sooner) quick walk up road to buy
viennoiseries. Train is 5 mins late, but on time by the time we get to Paris.
Which is HOT. Metro 5 to Nord, walk down road to Bombay Palace for excellent
restorative byriani, back to the lounge, wait for train, 1613 Eurostar, and so
to London by 1745 or so, also very HOT, wait for bus to MYB, train to OXP, bus
to — wait it’s going the wrong way? Apparently buses are being diverted for our
diversion. But we are too tired to care, and back home by 2015 or so, i.e. 12
hours door to door with an hour off for lunch.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Weds 7 :</hi> L goes to get her hair done in Kidderton. I meet
her at OXP for an earlyish train to MYB. And thence across London to Maryland,
shop briefly, and hello Daphne. It’s still HOT. Baby gazing ensues. In the
evening we retire to the Ibis, Stratford. Who do not supply showercaps, though
the Morrison’s round the corner does.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Thurs 8 :</hi> Up not very early for breakfast in Morrisons,
purveyors of pink showercaps. And then more Daphne gazing till it’s time to head
out to THE SHARD. Dine at umpteen thousand feet with Joel and company. At 2230
or so make our excuses and leave for Liverpool St (via Bank), then the 2325 to
Stansted, and then a taxi to the rather curious De Salis Hotel. Deer on the
road.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Fri 9 :</hi> Up earlyish for ride back to Stansted in hotel
van. The usual ghastliness. Arrive LIG at 1445, and Shaun picks up for nice
drive back to reality, i.e. dealing with les punaises. Move into smaller bedroom
to plan.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Saturday 10th:</hi> Amazon delivers my steamer very early, so
we can walk into Bussiere to buy bread and lunch at Benoits on fish and chips as
tradition decrees. The war on punaises continues.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sunday 11th :</hi> E&amp;A announce they have got tickets to
come, arriving weds! L cooks nice lunch.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 12 :</hi> Yves and Francine take us on an excursion to
Chateau de Villemonteix. 15th c tower lovingly restored by odd couple;
tapestries, sevre porcelaine, 18th c deco over 15th c murals, double-headed
piano; in the evening dined with Y&amp;F on pasta followed by sausages and green
beans in the garden.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 13 :</hi> Dashed to Dun with Yves and Francine in the
morning: visit excellent butcher, baker, and Intermarche, back in time for
lunch. Then to La Celle Dunoise with Deidre &amp;Peter for bathing purposes,
though I went for a nice walk along the creuse.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Wed 14</hi> (Alex’s birthday) : Weather broke. It poured with
rain all day, but Alex &amp; Elizabeth &amp; Daphne finally arrived around 18h.
Hoorah. We gave them steak and roasties and courgettes and drank good wine.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Thu 15 :</hi> To Dun le Palestel for lunch on couscous royale
in nice lowbrow bar, and then Intermarche again (but I went to Gamme Vert next
door instead, who sell savon d’aleppe but an insufficient choice of nuts and
bolts). E&amp;A need to eat in the evenings too, so we had pasta and ragu.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Fri 16 :</hi> Still rainy, so stayed home being baby-drunk
most of day. Hacked at ancient rose bush and overgrown clematis over hanging
back gate. Curried beef and aubergine and potato for lunch, yum. Discuss price
of wood with next door neighbour: he took delivery today of a “remorque” (i.e.
trailerload) of logs for 3–4 hundred euros (can that be right?) from Didier
Prado, of Rissat.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sat 17 :</hi> To market in Gueret with E&amp;A&amp;D, and a
quick coffee at the Moderne, while L cooked delicious roast chicken lunch. Sunny
intervals, but not enough to sit outside. Hacked at ancient rosiers some more.
Alex helped me assemble a bunkbed. Pasta again to feed the rising generation.
Phoned Lisa to see how Shaun is: not good is the answer.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 18 :</hi> Up early to discover that Jean Luc does not sell
nappies, unsurprisingly. And suddenly we are all alone in the house with the
punaises, &lt;sadFace/&gt;. After lunch of lamb stew and spinach and potato pie,
L went to St Vaury fabric fayre with Deidre and came back very happy with lots
of colourful cloth. Weather continues gray. Discuss need to buy logs urgently
with Pierre Nextdoor, who confirms that we should and proposes Didier Pradeau at
Rissat, who however does not answer his phone. Research on tinternet tracks down
an alternative, from whom I order 3 steres of finest G1 for delivery 24 oct.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 19 :</hi>Tidying house a bit. La guerre des punaises a
toujours lieu :-( Weather not so good, but a sunny interval or two. D&amp;P came
to eat dinner in the evening : stew, courgettes, got rid of horrible
bouillabaise as starter. Phone Banbury and L gets firm date for her appointment
(30/09) since she’s paying 5K. Also sorted out delivery of logs with M . Bernard
Dupont of St Silvain Montaigut, wherever that is. Phoned Shaun in the evening:
he’s not happy.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 20 :</hi> Beautiful sunny day, of course. Morning tidying
emptying fridge etc. Picked most of tomatoes; left 2 pears on the tree to ripen
hopefully. TAD arrives at 1320 and off we go to Gueret. L checks out beauty
shop; we have a pancake lunch at ? Bar. Walk gradually down to station for bus
to Limoges, a nearby city, a real city we realise, checking in to Hotel Akeda.
Pleasant afternoon stroll to medieval shopping centre. Tea and cake, and then
large dinner at Le Bouf sur Le Toit, surprisingly very very busy. We’re too
tired to really enjoy it though.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*WqRfd2rVUQtQOJ4_ffREWg.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>Limoges gare des Benedictines by night</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Wed 21 :</hi> And so back to the Gare des Benedictines for a
taxi to l’aeroport. Nice lunch (rougets and leeks) at superior upstairs restau,
recommended by helpful if reactionary taxidriver (“les artisans n’ont pas de sec
social; les jeunes ne veulent pas travailler; il y a des gens qui touchent
beacoup sans rien contribuer” etc etc). And into the belly of the Ryanair beast
once more, somewhat more relaxed than usual due to nice lunch en terrasse and a
half bottle of sancerre. And then Stansted — Liverpool St — Marylebone — OXP as
usual, though somewhat startled to find that buses from OXP home are being
rerouted. Too tired to argue. And so to bed.</p>
<p>In Oxford for 1 day, and then I zoom off to Vienna, via Paris and Zuerich,
for my last official TEI Council ftf, mm, etc. Returning via overnight train to
Koeln, then Bruxelles, and London on Oct 1st.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head> October</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">21 oct :</hi> 0850 dep from OXP is quiet, as I am sleepy. 1130
from St P likewise. Lunch on curry and rice at the Bombay. Uneventful journey to
La S during which I write lots of odd tuto. Train brakes sharply and I close lid
in panic thus losing much of it. Oh well. Sleepy on Bus to Gueret. Long walk
from Gueret station, and Gueret even on a Fri night seems DEAD. Hotel auclair
OK, nasty burger dinner. Good night sleep.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sat 22 :</hi> Market next morning delightfully sunny. Autumnal
produce -citrouille, potiron, cepes, woolly shirts. TAD driven by nice young
woman escaped from the school run, despite no licence for sat working.,
apparently TAD is financed by all gueret businesses employing &gt; 10 persons.
On arrival I found dining rm shutters open; bathroom heater still on; water
heater plugged in (but not, I discovered next day, working). Otherwise all
normal. Grass needs cutting already. Tomatoes still going, cabbages a bit
miserable. Spot enormous hornet nest in huge wild walnut tree next door and
point it out to interested neighbours.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 23 :</hi> Invited to lunch with Yves and Francine which
was nice.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 24 :</hi> Waited in vain for log delivery. It was raining,
is his excuse. Fair enough. Arrange with Yves that he will pay the man when he
arrives, check that the logs are covered etc.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 25 :</hi> TAD to Gueret, in time to catch train to
Limoges, in time to catch 1210 departure for Tours via Angouleme, and St Pierre
des Corps. Somewhere en route Yves tells me he’s had to pass responsibility for
my logs on to Georgette, sigh. No matter, As ever, enjoy three days of luxury in
the Grand Hotel of Tours, with accompanying three days of teaching and
gastronomy. Back to Oxford on the 28th.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head> November</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">31 Oct to 20 Nov </hi>: in Mauritius</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">23 Nov :</hi> to Paris, stay at Hotel Roussillon near Place
d’italie, modest, reasonably comfy, cheap.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">24 Nov :</hi> meet with Helene and Sophie and co at Paris 3;
then take 1858 to La Souterraine, staying at the Hotel Porte St Jean.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Fri 25 Nov :</hi> La Souterraine is quite pleasant and
picturesque (if hilly) if you’re not in a hurry. Lisa comes to pick me up from
station at 11 am. News of Shaun’s eye which is at last apparently starting to
get better, despite rubbish efforts of Gueret hospital. Pause in Dun for some
shopping. And here’s my house just as untidy as I left it, but with a heap of
logs covered in assorted bits of plastic sheet in the front garden hoorah. Start
stacking them after lunch.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sat 26 :</hi> Lovely sunny walk into Bussiere for fresh
provisions (a steak, jarets de veau, some rabbit, some sausages from new
butcher). Am chatting with Jean Luc when excited lady comes in to spread gossip
about Benoit and Corinne, both in hospital. So just as well I bought my steak as
no lunch is forthcoming at the Tilleule. Sit on sunny bench outside church and
am hailed by Yves Mauchassaut who bends my ear a bit about Shaun and his
intransigeance. Walk back by scenic route and see lake draining in action. Cook
jarets with flageolots, tasty. Stack logs. Do TEI stuff.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Sun 27:</hi> Still a lovely walk into Bussiere again, this
time to get some pain levain ordered from JL. Still no lunch at Benoits, so back
home to cook onglet and chips. Continue stacking logs. Sweep up a bit. Too tired
to set out for concert in the evening: busy with TEI tickets.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Mon 28 :</hi> Get up late. Finish logs. Hoe garden, and cover
with plastic. Make mash to accompany reheated jarets de veau. Much nicer.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Tues 29 :</hi> Walk into Bussiere, in time for lunch and there
is some hoorah. Paupiettes de veau. Wish B&amp;C happy xmas, and walk back. Am
sitting toasting self by stove when Shaun and Lisa suddenly appear and invite me
to come out for beers instead of buying them lunch tomorrow. Well, why not. Back
to Benoit’s for 3 beers with S &amp; L and Y. Meet some rather strange english
people e.g. Noj and crazy Frank. Back home, drunk. Cook soss chips and eggs, and
collapse.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Weds 30 :</hi> Wake up feeling woozy. Dizziness on getting out
of bed again ( 2nd time I notice) : is this a blood pressure thing? Or a
diabetes thing? Or just flu? Clean house anyway, and then make myself get out
into sunshine and go for walk along ex-railway to Monneger and back along road.
Would have been better in more sensible shoes and not feeling so feeble, but
still very nice. S&amp;L turn up promptly at 1330, S helps turn off water, and
close down house. L drives us all to La S, and the slow journey home
commences.</p>
<p>1518 dep La Souterraine for Chateauroux (pleasantly slow train). Find bakers
and eat. Depart for Paris 1715, arriving Austerlitz at 1907. Proceed slowly to
Gare du Nord, pausing for a light and unmemorable supper en route. Eurostar
departs 2115, arrives London 2245, which is a bit tight for the 2310 last
departure from Marylebone. But fortune favours the foolhardy, at least on this
occasion: I have the sense to walk down to the front end of the train before it
actually arrives into St P., am lucky with the tube to Baker St, and have just
enough energy to propel myself from there to Marylebone in under 10 minutes.
Arrive at OXP exhausted and just after midnight, so the bus driver insists I pay
him. Ah well. And that’s it for France in 2016.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head> December</head>
<p><hi rend="italic">1–6 :</hi> Back in Oxford, a bit of hypochondria, and a bit
of cleaning up in preparation for visitors.</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">6 Dec:</hi> L returns from Mauritius; E&amp;A&amp;D come to
stay while A works at being a snowflake and D at being supercute. Lots of baby
gazing ensues.</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">10 Dec :</hi> Family party at Wolfson to celebrate my 70th,
stage managed by Pam. <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">15–16th :</hi> to Nottingham to help L babysit Louis while B performs</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">17th :</hi> A posh wedding in Wadham and at MoMa</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">27th:</hi> Collect Lila on behalf of SD who is flying back
from NY today.</p><p>
<hi rend="italic">28th:</hi> to Thamesmead West, somehow, for a Mauritian dinner
with old school chums of L’s. And thence to Stratford to see Daphne again briefly. </p><p>
<hi rend="italic">31st:</hi> See in New Year in congenial company with dinner at
Deidre and Peter’s South Oxford residence, staying at the Travelodge to avoid
taxi woes.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
