<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/at-the-end-of-my-sixth-decade-having-some-credit-at-my-bank-and-no-particular-calls-on-my-time-i-f5707a1d9ed0-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>FEVE-fever : a collaborative account</title>
<author>Guy Aston</author> 
<author>Lou Burnard</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/> using CETEICEAN</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Originally posted as a series of posts on Medium.com, this text has been translated from HTML to TEI, and combined to form a single document.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="20260501">Converted, combined, added header</change></revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>


<!--</header>-->
<p>At the end of my sixth decade, having some credit at my bank, and no
particular calls on my time, I resolved to spend a week or two travelling by
slow train from left to right along the shores of the Bay of Biscay, in the
company of my oldest surviving friend Dr G.A.</p>
<p>We began the journey proper in Santiago de Compostela and finished it in
Hendaye, so this may be thought of as a kind of reverse or widdershins
pilgrimage. To get to Santiago, we took a high speed train from Madrid; and from
Hendaye we took a high speed train to Paris. But in between we were on FEVE
trains, which is a very different kind of experience. (See  <ref
target="http://www.wikiwand.com/en/Renfe_Feve"
>http://www.wikiwand.com/en/Renfe_Feve</ref> for background on FEVE)</p>
<p>We took it in turns to write a daily log, which was first published on Medium, and is now for the first time collected as a single document.  <!--you can now read as
follows:--></p>
<list>
<item><ref target="https://medium.com/p/51571d2c981b"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
1</hi>
<hi rend="italic">In which we find the Holy Grail</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/2e3ff932e24c"><hi rend="bold">FEVE Fever :
2</hi>
<hi rend="italic">In which we pass by the end of the world</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/ffec804721ba"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
3</hi>
<hi rend="italic">The vendetta of the invincible Armada</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/ca7172868535"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
4</hi>
<hi rend="italic">In which we return to the big(gish) City</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/71b21a2e3c2a"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
5</hi>
<hi rend="italic">In my beginning is my end</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/b9a6134e17b"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
6</hi>
<hi rend="italic">In which we are translated from Asturian to
Castilian</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/b781b04e0f07"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
7</hi>
<hi rend="italic">A million Mexicans can’t be wrong: the Transcantabrian
Adventure</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/4f15cc8d4a95"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
8</hi>
<hi rend="italic">In which we reach the (other) end of the line</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/ea40bf9df5bd"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
9</hi>
<hi rend="italic">Goodbye Feve; Hail and Farewell Euskotren.</hi></ref>
</item><item>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/ca967dfec834"><hi rend="bold">FEVE fever :
10</hi>
<hi rend="italic">In which we glide back into the 21st century</hi></ref>
<ref target="https://medium.com/p/ca967dfec834"/></item></list>


<div xml:id="feveFever1" resp="CGA" n="20160413_163514">


<head><hi rend="italic">In which we find the Holy Grail</hi></head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Guy sez:</hi> What can one say about the 9.15 8-coach ALVIA
Talgo from platform 21 of Madrid Chamartin for Ferrol, calling at Zamora,
Ourense, Santiago de Compostella, A Coruna, and Betanzos?</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*cg0uLFecVP7k7RjqNFqf-w.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>The rain in Spain falls mainly on the train</head>
</figure>
<p> Very little really, and I doubt much more tomorrow when we pick it up again
from Santiago to Ferrol. Miles of empty countryside which give way to
single-track snow-lined passes and peaks after the ritual of gauge change. A
friendly guard who shows us where we are on the map. An anxious glance at the
speedometer as we come to the curve leading into Santiago where a train derailed
last year. Virtually no other traffic.</p>
<p>Lou was offered an Eeyorish dinner at Pepe’s on arrival last night, branded
(in the English menu) as beans and thistles. But with no sign of the thistles in
practice. I finished my nice acorn-fed ham boccadillo in my stuffy little room.
We depart from Chamartin not too much the worse for wear with Burnard family
blessings.</p>
<p>Lunch in the first restaurant we encounter coming out of the station at
Santiago. Galician soup proves a splendid invention. And then we set about
hunting for the Holy Grail, located after some brief confusion under a dusky
portico. A charming elderly establishment, with old wooden floors, much wooden
pannelling, low ceilings, and walls too thin to keep out the rhythm section
rehearsing next door.</p>
<p> Destination the cathedral. We come to a hat shop. Lou needs a new
beret — cheaper here than in France, it seems. Both emerge wearing berets.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*RDnhGh44nML_bXf6JB1sqw.jpg"
 mimeType="image/jpg"/>

<head>Guy is fitted for his beret (slightly smaller than mine hem hem)</head>
</figure>
<p>We proceed to purchase obligatory tourist tat, e.g. postcards, snow globes,
etc. etc. Electric candles in front of St James’ relics on behalf of Sandra and
Adolfo. But I draw the line at joining the queue to embrace the saint’s statue
from the rear, so can tell you nothing today about his bottom. His main claim to
fame (apart from apostolic status and biblical references) appears to have been
helping Alfonso the nth to defeat the Moors in 700 and something. Will try and
find out more about this guest appearance in history. Certainly convenient that
his martyred remains had been imported from the Middle East for the occasion.
Expecting to find floods of pilgrims, but there seem relatively few tourists
around, and between showers we wander round bookshops (- Do you have a book
called Transcantabrica. I don’t know the author or publisher. — No.: this
allusion reserved exclusively for the surviving Pixies among our readers.)</p>
<p>Dinner is in what we gather is <ref target="http://cafecasino.es/el-casino/"
>a former gentlemen’s club</ref> across the road, with large armchairs and
carved wood panelling mainly but not exclusively depicting naked ladies (the
panelling that is). If my guts would only behave I might appreciate it more. As
it is, I give up on my second Galician soup of the day and on Lou’s surfeit of
small green peppers, and retire for an early night: Lou shortly knocks clutching
consolatory bottles of water and clementines. More tomorrow, hopefully not of
the same, from Lou.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever2" resp="LB" n="20160414_1846">

<head>In which we pass by the end of the world</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Lou says:</hi> One (or two) good night’s sleep later, we
return to the Cafe Casino, partly to see whether it is just as extraordinary by
daylight, but mostly to enjoy its excellent coffee and selections of <hi
rend="italic">desayunos</hi> (No 2 for G, No 3 for L). These comprise crunchy
grainy toast smeared with salsa and (in the case of No 3) large quantities of
ham. And did I mention the excellent restorative coffee? A flock of tourists
comes in out of the rain, and is sent packing by the waiter, hoorah.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*q5DWJGzPevVO4x2eKljQ-w.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Death and the Maiden at the Cafe Casino</head>
</figure>
<p>We have time to purchase more <hi rend="italic">schmuck</hi> and effectuate a
further modicum of tourism, so we take in the Cathedral museum, which turns out
to be largely an advertisement for — or testimony to — the heroic efforts of the
restoration workers, but it does feature some impressive pieces of devotional
kitsch, such as you might expect to have accumulated after a few centuries</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*dPt0avyusMWUbn9jjGTmuw.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>Hi Mary! Who’s your friend?</head>
</figure>
<p> And so back the Hotel of the Holy Graal to finish packing and watch the
world go by for a few moments from my window, before paying up and moving on. I
would be happy to return here, for one. It’s noon and far too early to expect
anyone to serve lunch, but we do eventually persuade the <hi rend="italic"
>cerviceria</hi> opposite the Galician parliament to oblige. The dish of the day
is <hi rend="italic">bacalao</hi>, which seems too good to resist. Guy’s innards
are still feeling tender, but he is persuaded by the solicitous barman to order
only half a steak. And so back to the station in good time for the 1417 train to
Ferrol, the same one as we got off of yesterday, or not, depending on your views
about the nature of identity.</p>
<p>The train chunters through the glooming (is that a word?) to A Coruna while I
wrestle with the problem of reorganizing the photos I have taken on the trip so
far, and do not therefore notice that the train has had to reverse direction to
back out of A Coruna, before continuing to chunter more slowly into the rather
grim estuary of Betanzos-Infesta, and then back out again in the opposite
direction. The rain continues to fall as it skirts the edge of the estuary until
it finds a bridge to cross over and descend on the charming city of Ferrol, our
destination <hi rend="italic">du jour</hi>. From which, Guy informs me, the
Spanish armada sailed some time ago.</p>
<p>Ferrol station is where our real FEVE adventure is due to begin tomorrow,
since this is the westernmost terminus of the narrow-gauge lines we are taking
along the coast towards Bilbao. A helpful lady at the station explains to us the
rules and regulations for buying FEVE tickets (only on the day of departure,
please, and only for one section at a time), and also reveals the cost benefits
of buying a Golden Card, the Spanish equivalent of the Senior Railcard or Carte
Senior. 6 euros for a year’s half price travel is an irresistible bargain in any
language.</p>
<p>And the sun comes out! Our hotel today is a charming edifice dating from 1906
on one of the three pedestrianized shopping streets that constitute much of the
centre of Ferrol, originally laid out on a grid pattern (Guy tells me) during
the Enlightenment to house shipyard workers. We inspect the naval base, or more
exactly the wall around it and the fish market (closed), and also some tumbling
down houses on the cobbled precipitous streets of the Old Town before resting in
a park full of peacocks and seagulls. The evocative cries of the seagulls are
interspersed with the low comedy of the peacocks. And thence for a light supper
(mmm sardines, and patatas bravas) in a typical Galician meson.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*vDxdbBuM2FRY44UffdK32A.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>For low comedy, it is hard to better the peacock’s arse</head>
</figure>
</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever3" resp="CGA" n="20160415_2031">

<head>The vendetta of the invincible Armada</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">An historical note by Guy. </hi></p>
<p>El Ferrol, where I was
awakened at dawn this morning by the wheeling of gulls outside my French window
(following three prior awakenings by other calls of nature), was razed virtually
to the ground by fire in 1568. Nonetheless some accounts claim that, as the home
of the Spanish Arsenal, it was still a point of departure for the invincible
fleet in 1588.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*LxVIvXpH7egGOeYG8qbnyg.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Invincible Armada approaching the Isle of White (from our own reporter)
via Wikimedia</head>
</figure>
<p> Drake’s observations have gone down in history as relating to a game of
bowls, but Elizabethan spelling was clearly flexible, certainly on Plymouth Hoe,
so it is quite likely that the official record missed the vowel e. Some of the
Spanish ships will have visited Mexico earlier in the century, and have
encountered and duly imported to the Arsenal significant samples of Montezuma’s
revenge. Vengeance proved total last night in the (quite nice) Galician bar
where Lou succeeded, but I totally failed to hold down (or up) my dinner,
something I do not intend to try to — again until I have departed this place. As
I now write the following evening, when we have finally left Galicia and entered
Asturias, perhaps limited risks may be taken. It will be seen.</p>
<p>After this brief historical-autobiographical preface, we turn to the details
of walking to the railway station(s) in Ferrol, via two bookshops neither of
which has a book called <hi rend="italic">Transcantabrica</hi> (even though we
now know the author and publisher). Half the station being RENFE, half being
FEVE (<hi rend="italic">Ferrocarriles Españoles de Vía Estrecha = Spanish narrow
gauge railways</hi>), which is now also owned by RENFE (This means that the
national Spanish rail operator somehow manages to run trains on three different
gauges, specifically the 1668-mm “Iberian gauge”, the 1435-mm “European gauge”
and the 1000-mm “Metre Gauge” networks). Access to the two sets of platforms is
strictly segregated: to get to a FEVE platform you must have a FEVE ticket. This
also provides access to the FEVE half of the station bar, occupied by a number
of railwaymen, where we order European toasted sandwiches to accompany the
inevitable freshly squeezed orange juice and coffee, and then watch the 1030
departure move out from platform 7 prior to embarking on our 1045 from platform
5.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*x9aD4NXqt01Se_6HOJt5TQ.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>1045 Ferrol-Ribadeo preparing to leave</head>
</figure>
<p> There is an intensive service on this route for the first few miles, which
progressively thins out to become a mere two trains a day beyond Ribadeo, our
current destination which we reach some three hours later. All the trains are
two-coach articulated diesel multiple units with driver and guard which stop
upon request: so we speed happily through the first station from Ferrol before
braking dramatically and reversing into the station to pick up a previously
unnoticed would-be passenger.</p>
<p>The route is decidedly scenic, with lots of little farms, and many wooded
hills covered in eucalyptus (on which more anon). There are also lots of
crossing points with station masters/mistresses in smart hats (they aren’t the
only ones: see <ref target="http://bit.ly/feveFever1">first instalment</ref>).
The train averages 4–5 passengers until we get to the last stretch along the
coast to Ribadeo, where we are joined by a vociferous group who seem the
worse/better for drink. At Ribadeo everyone gets out, including the train crew
who are taken away in a car, presumably to lunch.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*BS0rAn2us6EiM1lcgf8MWg.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Buenos dias Ribadeo. Bring us lunch.</head>
</figure>
<p>We share this objective, and a five-minute walk takes us to <hi rend="italic"
>O Piano</hi>, and another Galician soup of a fishy nature, though I can’t
handle the boiled beef which follows it on the <hi rend="italic">Menu del
Dia</hi>.</p>
<p> Somewhat restored, we set out for the town centre, where we find: a post
office without anywhere to post things; another Casino in need of repair, the
glimmering red and silver tiles of Ribadeo’s triumph of Art Nouveau.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*T2D9rvOqrpL62mlHXsko7g.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Casino in urgent need of restoration, Ribadeo</head>
</figure>
<p>I have completely run out of energy at this point, but Lou manages to get me
back to the railway station and purchase tickets for Navia, via a supermarket
and a supply of bananas and fruit juice. Ribadeo is the last place in Galicia,
and perhaps of associated maledictions. Into the train, seated opposite a fluffy
Spanish lady whom the guard assumes is English, and here we all are in Navia
(accent on first syllable), walking down the hill to our (fairly) luxurious
hotel wherein I have the dingy desk with hi-tech bathroom facilities, and Lou
has the luxurious suite complete with view over the estuary and tailors
dummy.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*rLCcQt8AN6juV_wJYAqf-w.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> Dinner, for which the hotel cannot be held responsible, is a total disaster.
I am a wreck after struggling through the streets of Ribadeo with zero energy.
For Lou it is far too late for eating. We end up stuck between two screens
displaying the evening’s football game at full volume in an unpleasant and
largely deserted bar. My two glasses of wine do however remain <hi rend="italic"
>in situ</hi>, and we stagger back to the hotel and fall over. If only they
would invest in something over a five-watt light bulb. Good nite.</p>

</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever4" resp="LB" n="20160416_1840">


<head>In which we return to the big(gish) City</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Lou says:</hi> I am woken by the sound of rain falling on the
slate roof of my penthouse suite at the Casona Naviega, and also by occasional
swooshes of motor transport along the road outside. How nice to be staying in
bed this morning. Yes, the sky is very grey, with no evident signs of
improvement, though the view across the estuary is still quite pleasant.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*EeyNI0MyD2W6qdrMHlj2eg.jpeg"
 mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>View from the Casona Naviega, top floor</head>
</figure>
<p> Excellent breakfast awaits downstairs, so I heave myself out by 10 or so,
and graze appreciatively for a while before prodding G into making an
appearance. The hotelier converses in broken English, first with another guest,
and then with us, at some length. He knows Oxford colleges well, but from the
perspective of the migrant Spanish waiter. We leave him hastily to catch our
1225 train, which is in the event 10 minutes late arriving.</p>
<p>It is a shame about the endless rain, since the scenery we are pottering
through is very scenic. We are travelling parallel to the coast line, and
therefore of necessity having to cope with numerous inlets, estuaries, and heaps
of rock in inconvenient places. Which means that there are lots of deep
cuttings, dizzy embankments, and wiggly tunnels for the train to navigate. Every
now and then we also see snake-like motorways swooping across gorges we are
compelled to chug gingerly around or under, lifted up high on enormous concrete
pillars.</p>
<p>In between, we occasionally catch a brief perspective down a valley to a
stormy beach, but mostly masses of gumtrees. My researches indicate that the
eucalyptus is now the preferred crop in these parts, which means much <ref
target="https://www.ence.es/pdf/Eucalyptus.pdf">debate about its ecological
impact</ref>, need for careful management to avoid fires, and general political
hoo hah. It’s a profitable crop that doesn’t require industrial scale farming,
is my understanding. To celebrate which, here is <ref
target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z0SGwF7jv_s">some lumberjack porn</ref>
showing exactly how to turn a giant eucalyptus into a massive beam.</p>
<p>The train, by the way, is another two-car diesel unit, but a bit more modern
and comfortable, so that everyone on board soon dozes off.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*WFydr6Euqc3lNh5XrIVjgw.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>1330 arrival at Pravia</head>
</figure>
<p>We arrive at Pravia (not to be confused with Navia) without incident, and
detrain in search of lunch. The station master assuring us that this is only
available in town, we leave the station via a lift, and five minutes later are
walking up Pravia’s main street which does indeed boast several eating
establishments as well as some colourful architecture. Lunch is fish soup for
Guy, and salad followed by yet more ham and potatoes. But the waiter is friendly
and the ambiance agreeable. Small town vibes suit us old timers well.</p>
<p>And then back down the hill we go to pick up our onward train to Gijon. This
is an electrified item, since we are now in the metropolitan area of Gijon, and
the view from the window is remarkably different. Around the port of Aviles and
beyond we pass through an industrial wasteland, featuring huge gas and coke
processors, some of them rusting and defunct, others just rusting. There is a
brief interlude of green dotted with what appear to be small seaside villas, but
then the industrial zone reasserts itself, as for example the Zone of
Distribution, where lorries and containers are massed for despatch throughout
Europe, some of them wrapped up in plastic like the luggage of nervous air
travellers. As we trundle into Gijon there is mile upon mile of the sort of
featureless industrial estates you might see at the periphery of almost any
large European or American city. For Gijon, as we realise when we arrive, is
actually a city, with long <hi rend="italic">calles</hi> full of shops, some of
them pedestrianized, there are plazas beneath which there are car parks, so as
to permit the pedestrianization, and there’s a pleasing jumble of ancient and
modern architecture. It’s a long schlep into town and to our hotel, but
instructive.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*quAIZ6u3KRwJFoMsL1Pejw.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Backstreet Downtown Gijon</head>
</figure>
<p> After a brief nap, we take a pleasant walk along the promenade before follow
the advice of the hotel map in selecting from the dozens of <hi rend="italic"
>cidrerias</hi> along the streets around the harbour. This one aereates the
cider not by means of theatrical gestures but by means of an ingenious kind of
stopper to the bottle. The waiter also persuades us to try some freshly grilled
fish with it, which turns out to be a very good idea. And so, dear reader, to
bed.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*iT-cHn5DBKvigYTS-4zEGA.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever5" resp="CGA" n="20160417_2022">

<head>In my beginning is my end</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Guy sez:</hi> Yes, today is the only day to finish where it
starts. It thus involves a return journey. After finding breakfast near the bus
station, we proceed beneath the rain to various chemists lacking appropriate
syringes and, eventually, the Railway Museum in Gijon, which now occupies the
original railway station building . The latter celebrates, inter alia, the birth
of the Gijon-Langreo railway in 1852.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*ZZ8yEnRRGNtqgXwY23zKTg.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Opening of the Gijon-Langreo Railway, courtesy An Unknown Artist and
Wikimedia</head>
</figure>
<p> Unlike any other railway in Spain for the next century, this was built to
standard gauge (1.438m), before being forcibly converted to 1m gauge in the
1960s to become part of FEVE — a little before the Spanish AVE project was
formulated to introduce standard gauge as the high speed norm.</p>
<p>The museum hosts many fine relics of narrow gauge splendour including a
yellow FEVE travelling post office, various tank engines and 4-wheel coaches,
which we gaze at in the rain for a while. It also has a splendid and extensive
model railway of 00 gauge staffed by middle-aged spaniards happily whiling away
their Saturday morning.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*MM7N-fRb4avpVhlkQcTzjw.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>If the train risks running into the building, just move the
building…</head>
</figure>
<p> Aside from the proper gauge for railways, the main existential problem
around these parts appears to be how to pour cider. This has to be aerated prior
to consumption. The traditional means is by pouring into a glass held in one
hand by the knee from a bottle held in the other hand as far above the head as
possible. The possibilities of inaccuracy are considerable, hence best done
either outside or over a large bucket. Only a small amount has to be poured at a
time — certainly not more than 100ml — so that it does not fall flat before
consumption. At dinner yesterday we were introduced to the first technological
solution, namely a bottle top which magically mixes air with the cider as it is
poured. Today, we encountered the electronic version, where at the end of each
table is positioned a device in which you place your glass at an angle of 30
degrees in a holder, brandish your swipe card, and wait for replenishment, as an
illuminated display informs you how much you have consumed (or not) from the
hidden supply pipe.</p>
<p>This is in Oviedo, which we have reached on an express FEVE 2-coach electric
multiple unit from Gijon, taking a mere 30 minutes through a lengthy
double-track tunnel (previously home to an inclined plane operating on the
principle that the trains of coal descending were heavier than those of empties
ascending), and whose city centre is full of cranes and closed roads before we
finally reach our reference point, namely a statue of Woody Allen, who must have
a weakness for cider.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*fWjCOFlFMzANohYSpgBerQ.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Watch out Woodie, she’s checking up on you with Google</head>
</figure>
<p> Lunch takes place on Cider Boulevard in Oviedo, and consists of <hi
rend="italic">fabada</hi> (large white beans stewed with bits of sausage) as
well as our half-dozen cider top/bottom-ups. The cathedral is shut. We wander
round the closed market and sit in the park as it starts raining again. No, more
serious matters still await, in the shape of Lou’s trews. These had been looming
from various shop windows in Gijon, and after a restorative cuppa, here we are
at a mere few yards from El Corte Ingles (Oviedo branch), where a
girth-attentive lady on the second floor resolves the problem by trial and error
for a mere thirty euros, thereby enabling us to subsequently rush through the
rain and catch the 4.40 back to Gijon.</p>
<p>Here Lou will subsequently seek out and test the laundry facilities (another
advantage of remaining in the same place for two nights in a row), and I will
fall asleep for three hours feeling knackered after discovering that the hotel
laundry service hasn’t. Note: this last part of the journey also involved our
first Spanish taxi, hardly a matter of note. But there we were, and it was
pissing it down as it had been all day.</p>
<p>And the evening and that evening’s cider, which we watched being poured by a
charming lady while we drank wine, were the fifth day.</p>

</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever6" n="20160418_2034" resp="LB">

<head>In which we are translated from Asturian to Castilian</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Lou says:</hi> A pleasant breakfast in the Hernan Cortes hotel
before we shoulder our bags and decamp for Gijon’s nasty new station once more.
At least it’s not actually raining, though it soon will be. Today we are going
to leave the Asturias definitively and head deep inland to Leon in search of the
legendary once-a-day Leon-Bilbao FEVE line. We have tickets on the RENFE service
to Alacant, on which one carriage is considered to be a “regionale” (i.e. cheap)
service for poor folks like us, but only on Sundays. Which it is, plus we have
our Golden Cards as aforesaid, so we get to ride at the front of the train for
very cheap, hoorah. We head for approximately the same valley as we did on
yesterday’s trip to Oviedo, but along entirely different tracks, thus affording
a view of the opposite side of the gas-coke-processing complex outside Oviedo.
Our train continues beyond there towards the coal mining town of La Robla, which
involves going over some serious mountain ranges and (today at least) into the
clouds. For yes, it is now raining again and visibility is pretty much the same
whether we are inside or outside the numerous twisty little tunnels the train
clatters through as it goes up the valley out of Asturias and then down on the
other side into Castille y Leon. Guy remains convinced that we will at some
point enter a new more direct tunnel, scheduled to replace the numerous twisty
little tunnels, but it is clearly still scheduled for manana. Before starting
the descent and just above the cloudline the scenery mutates into jagged rock
formations, with snow lying on the ground, and very little by way of vegetation
or villages. But soon, round about Gordo country, we are speeding through a
valley that looks (by contrast) more like a lush flood plain with big meadows
full of contented cows once more. And the sun is coming out again!</p>
<p>Leon RENFE station turns out to be another nasty new one, about fifty metres
away from the perfectly good but now defunct old one. I have been here before
(last summer with Lilette and a huge suitcase) so I know the way into town,
though not much more since all we did on that occasion was have lunch. We cross
the river and walk about 15 minutes into the old town, where we are greeted by a
large roman pillar topped by a stork’s nest complete with storks.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20160417_121657.jpg"  width="600px"/>
</figure>
<p> There are (according to Guy’s Guidebook) three essential architectural
treasures in this city: the Cathedral, the College of St Isidore, and St Mark’s
church, representing the Gothic, the Classical, and the Renaissance periods
respectively. Our hotel is conveniently located in the Roman part i.e. inside
the former monastery attached to the Church of <ref
target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isidore_of_Seville">St Isidore, patron
saint of the Internet</ref> as any fule kno. It boasts the usual sort of stone
corridors and cloisters, monastic cells complete with crosses on the wall,
numerous art works, nice comfy chairs at regular intervals, and really bad wifi.
But our cells look reasonably comfortable and there is real linen on the
beds.</p>
<p> However, we urgently need lunch and sally forth in search of same. It is
Sunday and the town is full of similarly motivated families on their way back
from mass, so it takes a while to find somewhere with space to accomodate us.
The beef goulasch and potatoes were definitely worth the wait though.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*1L-6R4XWpzBzIu9jo_snMw.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>A decent meal at last</head>
</figure>
<p> Replete, we take a brief digestive stroll in order to locate the FEVE
station (thank you Google maps) which is shut, and the market, ditto, before
retiring to our cells for a well earned siesta.</p>
<p>When I wake, I spend an hour or so getting annoyed by the inadequacies of the
hotel wifi (which dear reader is why yesterday’s blog appeared 24 hours late)
and we then set off on a quixotic search for something really light for supper.
And a drink, There is no problem finding drink: the bars are all doing very
nicely thank you, and the clientele is agreeably mixed in age, but the one we
settle on offers as free munchies only crisps, olives, or something called
garlic soup. So we order raciones again (Guy has a plate of cheesy fried
croquettes, and I have a mass of fried sweetbreads) which is more than we can
eat, even with the accompaniment of a rather nice fresh white wine. But on the
way back to the cloister, we find a tiny bar which proffers grilled mushrooms to
accompany the glass of brandy I had proposed as night cap. And we begin to feel
that maybe we can cope with spanish life after all. And so to bed.</p>


</div>

<div xml:id="feveFever7" n="20160420_1935" resp="CGA">



<head>A million Mexicans can’t be wrong: the Transcantabrian Adventure</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Guy says :</hi> We inspected the FEVE station in Leon (closed
on Sundays) last night, where a substitute bus driver assured us it would be
open on Monday. As indeed it was when we went down after breakfast, but no
trains apparent. Substitute buses as far as the university, apparently, on
account of the <hi rend="italic">Obras.</hi> And thereafter, finally, there
would be trains. The ticket office lady gives us tickets and timetables for the
one train each day covering the Leon-Bilbao route, scheduled to take a mere
eight hours for the 250 miles. We aim to get off after a mere seven hours at
Balmaseda, where the Bilbao suburban service terminates. Our morning plans for
Leon therefore include substantial shopping with a visit to the market to
procure adequate supplies for the journey.</p>
<p>But first, a tour of the church of St Isidore, with its beguiling 12th
century frescoes of the months and miscellaneous saints, and many tombs of the
kings and queens of Leon. This leads us back to our <hi rend="italic"
>collegio</hi> (also dedicated to St Isidore), where a number of fellow guests
are awaiting the promised free conducted tour. However, having been talked at in
Castilian for a few minutes and inspected the Roman walls, where the mystery of
Leon’s ubiquitous cockerel is explained, we defect: we still have the cathedral
to see. So we finish packing and deposit our belongings, at a point to prove key
to a miraculous discovery some two hours later.</p>
<p>Off to the cathedral, which boasts much stained glass, some of it medieval,
in Gothic windows. Free audio guides educate us as to the spiritual significance
and purity of Gothic Architecture.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20160418_095613.jpg"  width="700px"/>
<head>Err, Mary, you seem to have a bun in the oven</head>
</figure>
<p> And then it’s time for coffee and the market, where the one open stall
convinces Lou of its wildly expensive ham and cheese while I go to the bread
shop and also pick up olives, water, and wine for which the lady lends a
corkscrew. St Isidore has become, Lou assures me, the patron saint of the
internet. Could this be the reason why, when we collect our bags from the
Collegio before retracing our tracks to the FEVE station, we find a serrated
knife miraculously hidden behind Lou’s bag, ideal for cutting bread, cheese, and
fruit on lengthy train journeys when devising bloggery? Finally, a digression
upon the nests of storks, of which one reposes outside St Isidore’s. During the
day we find these may be comfortably situated on top of a) pillars; b) derelict
industrial chimneys; c) telegraph poles, as well as trees of course. To be
defended against other marauding storks by rapid beak-clicking, not unlike the
pecking of woodpeckers.</p>
<p>After an extensive bus tour of the university, we board the train for Bilbao.
Half an hour later, we reach the junction for La Robla (where the coal came
from), and the line turns to the east, skirting the Asturian/Cantabrian peaks on
the south side. This means that while generally heading east, it turns north up
any river valley encountered, which it then descends slowly to the first
appropriate crossing place (generally coinciding with a village) before
returning south along the other side of the valley until it has reacquired
sufficient height to cross the next ridge; and then repeat the entire operation
for the next valley. This means, roughly speaking, ten kilometres of labour for
every two moved eastwards. There are no tunnels, no fancy viaducts, in fact
nothing but long curving lines of ballast, most of it with 50km/h speed limits,
presumably placed there when the line was reopened with European funding some 20
years ago.</p>
<p>We say hello to numerous cows, and few signs of human habitation. We spot
more storks (or are they cranes), we startle wild deer, and more implausibly
cattles, horses, and donkeys. The stations are nearly all request stops; the
crossing points have red-hatted station mistresses/masters; we occasionally
cross a descending train for Leon starting from Guardo, a mere 3 hours up the
line and where everything (except our train) terminates. As well as the three
staff in the driving cab, and the third different guard/ticket collector since
we started, there are three other passengers as we gradually move closer to the
bare snow-capped peaks, and up above the tree line. Until finally, after four
hours, we find ourselves running alongside the broad gauge Burgos-Santander line
into Mataporquera</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Yku643hxqJACEHWmIgpTrA.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Mataporquera. Note the cement factory.</head>
</figure>
<p> Mataporquera is the nearest thing to an event on the journey. First, it is
the only point where you could in fact change and get onto another railway line.
Second, it is the crossing point with the train in the other direction, for
which we have to wait a few minutes. This gives us time to stretch our legs and
examine the group of oldies hanging around the platform, and follow their
indications to the waiting room cum railway museum, which primarily documents
the lives of the train crews in the days of steam and their cooking skills.
Mataporquera boasts a large cement works, and numerous wagons (of both gauges),
but nothing resembling an active goods train. We agree it would not have been a
thrilling place to spend the night, even if it does apparently boast two
hotels.</p>
<p>We move on. Snow-capped peaks give way to long cliff-topped mountains and
cows to sheep as we wander around a long reservoir and then drop down to
Balmaseda.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*xVqQTsMPbfHSHtEeZtchcA.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Cliff topped mountains</head>
</figure>
<p> Balmaseda is home to the FEVE railway works, and the apparently luxurious La
Robla tourist train, and is also where we are staying tonight in a former
nunnery. Which, when we find it, is apparently closed for the night. The museum
next door provides advice, leading us to the back door of the hotel (also
closed) and then phoning them. Wait five minutes and someone will come. A
somewhat harassed-looking young lady eventually turns up, checks us in, and
departs. The rooms are reasonably comfortable, for a nunnery.</p>
<p>We wander back through the town to the main square exchanging childhood
railway memories and looking for somewhere to eat, but nine o’clock is clearly
too late for anything other than a glass of Rioja and a sandwich. It’s been a
long day, and this is the Basque country.</p>
<p>PS We never found that Transcantabrica book, either.</p>

</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever8" n="20160420_2044" resp="LB">


<head>In which we reach the (other) end of the line</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Lou says:</hi> I apologise to the noble Basques, but their
language defeats me totally. It seems to be mostly composed of the names of
minor characters in bad science fiction novels, e.g. “Norabide Guztiak”. Still,
the sun is shining and we are getting by reasonably well with pidgin spanish and
much hand waving. Nothing however had quite prepared me for the assault on the
senses this morning when I poked my head out of my cell in search of breakfast.
There is a VERY LOUD tape of VERY BAD torch singing in International Amurrican
booming out incongruously across the decorative courtyard of the Convento San
Roque. I escape from it into the bar, where I consume some coffee (reasonable),
some orange juice (fake), a croissant (fresh, but sugary), and a piece of
freshly made tortilla (quite nice).</p>
<p>Guy appears and we take a pleasant walk in the Spring Sunshine, first over a
rather scenic medieval bridge and up the road to inspect the nearest railway
station (La Calzada, terminus of the Bilbao metro) and then back along the river
to inspect the main square of <ref
target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balmaseda">Balmaseda</ref>. Apparently,
this town was big in the 12 century when the populace hit on the cunning wheeze
of charging itinerant merchants for the privilege of crossing the river by means
of their rather scenic medieval bridge, but subsequently declined when a new
road was constructed between Biscay and Navarre in the 16th century. It
recovered slightly at the end of the 19th century when the La Robla railway
arrived and is now poised for, well, whatever comes along really. Speaking for
myself, I recommend the baker in the main square, whose chocolate and buns are
both excellent. There is also a gothic church if you like that sort of
thing.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20160419_083046.jpg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>Balmaseda’s renowned medieval bridge</head>
</figure>
<p> Our train journey today is essentially a continuation of the epic trip we
did yesterday, although it is on a train which considers itself to be part of
the Greater Bilbao metropolitan area. It’s just like any other commuter train,
except that for most of the way we are descending a wooded river valley, with
occasional pasturage and villages. As we descend, industrial sites and housing
developments become more frequent, though still interspersed with spots of more
bucolic charm, until finally as we arrive at the fringes of Bilbao proper they
become entirely dominant.</p>
<p>The FEVE stations also become correspondingly grander as we approach,
boasting such luxuries as multiple platforms, escalators and so forth. And
within 40 minutes here we are back in the modern(ish) world at Bilbao’s <ref
target="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estaci%C3%B3n_de_Bilbao-Concordia"
>beautiful Concordia station</ref> (“eclecticism, 1902”), where the lines
symbolically terminate under the watchful eye of portuguese venture capitalist
<ref target="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/V%C3%ADctor_Ch%C3%A1varri">Victor de
Chavarri</ref> to whom is attributed the immortal phrase “<hi rend="italic">El
ferrocarril ademas in historia: tambien es arte</hi>” in a plaque commemorating
the terminus’s 90th birthday in 1992.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Y5re5ZBc3MBKDZ5q_9-k1g.jpeg"  mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>O mama, can this really be the end?</head>
</figure>
<p> And so we reach the end of the FEVE. Or is it? Because here in the Basque
country, there is another narrow gauge network called the “Euskotren” which
formed part of the FEVE network up till the 1980s, when the Spanish government
handed it over to the provincial government in a fit of devolution. And tomorrow
we will continue our journey on that line from its <ref
target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bilbao-Atxuri_Station">Atxuri
terminus,</ref> on the other side of the old town.</p>
<p>For now, however, it’s time to find our cheap hotel (booked by Guy at the
last minute last night, but none the worse for that), and then (a recurrent
theme I know) some lunch. Both are adjacent in Maria Somebody street, in the
heart of the pedestrianised old town. The former glories in a curvaceous wooden
staircase, and the latter (recommended by the former) is in a typical back room
<hi rend="italic">comedor</hi>, featuring nice artichokes, thin slices of
grilled meats, a scattering of chips, and a bottle of rather good wine which we
cannot quite finish, before retiring to see Esther, bless her.</p>
<p>Around 5 pm, as per usual, we re-arise and explore further. Our plan is to
stroll along the river bank to the Guggenheim museum though (I am informed) this
is more impressive on the outside than the inside. The outside certainly is
grandiose in an entirely post-modernistic way; see just about any architectural
journal. Our energies are not equal however to the task of exploring its
expensive insides, and since it is starting to rain again we take a tram back
into town instead. And then we went out and ate rice, in the form of vegetable
paella, and consumed a refreshing bottle of young red wine. And it was good. No,
really, really good. Notwithstanding our neighbours slowly and noisily scoffing
a large piece of grilled cow in the background.</p>


</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever9" n="20160421_1203" resp="CGA">
<head>Goodbye Feve; Hail and Farewell Euskotren.</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Guy says:</hi> Our efficiency when we have a train to catch is
astounding, in this case the 11 am from Bilbao Atxari to Donostia. For which, we
discovered yesterday, senior railcards give no reduction whatever. A 9am gesture
at breakfast in the hotel, who present us each with a neatly wrapped green bag
emblazoned with their name as a souvenir and an apology for the noise caused by
ongoing renovations; then off to inspect the RENFE broad gauge station, with its
magnificent stained class tribute to Basque society (miners, fishermen,
winnowers, pelote players etc), and then back across the bridge admiring the
single-track Bilbotram (this place appears to have been colonised by Tolkien
maniacs) to the Cafe Bilbao under the arches of the big square, which offers a
truly worthwhile breakfast with good tortilla.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/20160420_080852.jpg" width="600px"
 mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Um, one of them, one of them, and a <hi rend="italic">cafe con
leche </hi>please</head>
</figure>
<p> Back to the hotel for a 1030 departure, pick up bags, wave goodbye, avoid
falling down the staircase yet again, and it’s off to Atxari in the rain
(again). What else can one say? Not much really. Two tickets to Donostia and
it’s another 150 minutes stop-everywhere 4-coach Euskotren electric multiple
unit, which people get on and off at frequent intervals as we wind up and down
valleys, along and not along the coast, turning from double to single track, and
heading for what my Italian guidebook claims — under the heading of San
Sebastian — is a ridiculously overpriced resort for nouveaux riches.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*skSoBMr1nsNYQZOt5tIGdg.jpeg" 
mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Yes, that is Don Quixote and Sancho Panza trying to upstage us in this
carefully organised photo on the front in San Sebastian</head>
</figure>
<p>We do however find some two-o-clock lunch for only twice the average cost so
far, and then wander along to the seafront where Lou is able to practice his
French on a gentleman whom he convinces to take our photo in front of the local
statue of Don Quixote and Sancho Panza. And we find a bun for tea before
boarding the 1545 for Hendaye and saying farewell to Spanish (if not Basque)
soil.</p>
<p>We are booked into different Hendaye hotels under the same management, with
shared pricing and breakfasting arrangements. Visit to the station to renew my
French Carte Senior+, then a stroll along the old port, commanding magnificent
views of Spain, plus several antique cannons to fire at it. Back into town
through the seaside villas in search of a place for dinner. Three storeys of
wooden gallery in the church from which the faithful are just emerging (Lou
witnessed the transubstantiation, i.e. saw the priest quaffing the wine; Guy was
too scared to watch). Back in the square an establishment with the unpromising
name of Pizzeria 64 has a Gault&amp;Millau review in its window, and comes up
with a bottle of Basque cider (aired using the plastic top method), as well as
an entirely acceptable <hi rend="italic">gigot d’agneau</hi> and <hi
rend="italic">poulet basquaise</hi>, though we’re not sure about the guffawing
landlord. And so back to the Hotel de la Gare, where the Basque digestif could
better have been an omitted experience. And we fix breakfast for 8 in order to
further demonstrate our astounding efficiency, even where no narrow gauge is any
longer involved.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="feveFever10" n="20160421_1203" resp="LB">

<head>In which we glide back into the 21st century</head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Lou says:</hi> An early start in Hendaye, where since it is
Thursday the artisanal boulangerie is shut. But breakfast in the cafe de la gare
is <hi rend="italic">sympathique</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">petit
déjeuner</hi> is <hi rend="italic">offert</hi> (Madame said pityingly when we
arrived, “<hi rend="italic">parce que vous êtes tous seuls, les deux</hi>”) so
not to be spurned. We bid farewell to the Basque country, which is just waking
up, and board the 0910 idTGV to Paris. Our carriage is at the very very end of
the platform, in an almost deserted <hi rend="italic">espace idZen</hi> (i.e.
quiet zone), so we choose the comfiest best placed seats available and take in
the view all the way to Bordeaux (stopping at St Jean de Luz, Bayonne, and Dax)
at which point the train fills up and we have to return to our allocated seats,
curses curses. The view is however fairly unspectacular: the route takes us
briefly along the coast through some bosky bays, but then turns inland and
proceeds in an absolutely straight line across what I surmise was once a flood
plain to Bordeaux. Guy (who has bought a map) observes that the straight line
deviates whenever necessary in order to cross a river at exactly 90 degrees.</p>
<p>After Bordeaux, one of my fellow passengers complains that I am typing too
loudly, but another graciously restores to me the passport I had accidentally
dropped when changing my seat. So honour is satisfied. I contemplate the green
fields, modest woods, villages, and occasional chateaux of Aquitaine
disappearing rapidly from view outside the window, and ponder the wonders of
modern science which enable me to do so at the same time as engaging in badinage
with my daughters via Whatsapp. Well, perhaps “ponder” is too strong a word. And
in a final feat of tail-consuming bravado, I try to complete my final blog entry
for this trip, without hitting the keys too hard or too fast. Speeding across
France by TGV is becoming so routine I am not sure what to write about it: it’s
faster and mostly more comfortable than the FEVE, obviously, but you miss the
sense of proximity to the landscape that slower speed and frequent wiggling
confer. So I scarcely notice when our train finally gets to the high speed line
north of Bordeaux and hits its top speed of around 300 km/hr. At 15h33 precisely
we are at Paris Montparnasse (at the very front of the train now, which is an
unexpected bonus), and being swallowed up by the general rush to the metro: line
6 for Guy, who is going to rest for the night before proceeding back to Italy;
line 4 for me, as I am going on to Paris Nord, for the Eurostar to London. So
farewells are said, and we disappear into the crowd.</p>
<p>Fortunately there are (a few) bits of FEVE left which neither Guy nor I has
yet explored; plus a few places that seemed worth a second visit (Ferrol and
Leon, notably) so we’ll just have to come back some time.</p>
</div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
