<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" n="2009-09-marseilles">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Transports en commun</title>
<author>louburnard</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Self-published (WordPress)</publisher>
<idno type="URL">https://louburnard.wordpress.com/2009/09/09/transports-en-commun/</idno>
<date when="2009-09-09">2009-09-09</date>
<availability>
<p>Originally published on WordPress.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from WordPress WXR export.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="category">
<term>Biographical</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="post">
<head>Transports en commun</head>
<head>How to get from Belfast to Marseilles</head>
<list><item>
0915 Hand in keys and summon a taxi</item><item>
0935 Taxi (£5) arrives EuropaCentre Bus Station, having negotiated Belfast morning traffic</item><item>
0945 Double decker Ulsterbus no 33 sets off for airport through Belfast morning traffic</item><item>
1020 Join shortish check in queue for flight EI58</item><item> 1030 proceed through the usual formalities in search of coffee</item><item>
1040 enjoy coffee and work on talk a bit</item><item>
1115 proceed to gate and find a plug so as to continue working.</item><item>
1135 all boarded and off we go. Continue to work as much as inflight regulations permit</item><item>
1415 (French time) land at CDG</item><item>
1430 air bridge finally produced, and we disembark and join queue to show passports</item><item>
1440 join small mob of fractious infants waiting for bags to be delivered</item><item>
1505 pick up bag, rush to bus stop and get on Roissybus to Opera in (false) belief it would leave before the Airfrance bus to GdL</item><item>
1532 Roissybus negotiates Paris late afternoon traffic, changes driver</item><item>
1600 Roissybus arrives Opera; dash to Auber RER D </item><item>
1602 RER train leaves for GdL</item><item>
1610 RER Train arrives Gare du Lyon. Hot, and hotfoot upstairs, arriving at Platform A with precisely 2 minutes to spare before</item><item>
1616 TGV 6119 takes off. Phew.</item><item>
1930 arrive Marseille, after a relaxing time working on my talk... wander hopefully out of Gare St Charles into adjacent University campus, where there is a large crowd of people enjoying une piquenique alfresco. Goodness me, c'est un universite d'ete! and a nice cheese sandwich too.
</item></list>       </div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
