<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More hopeful travelling</title>
            <author/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2024-03-18T13:14:04.802061716</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <name/>
               <date>2024-03-26T23:51:46.997651847</date>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
   
            <head>An expedition across the hexagon</head>
            <p>Our first visit to France this year started on the ill-omened 13 March, just before the Ides of March, the latter being quite coincidentally the day on which I had been invited to make <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-03-15_caen.html">the first ever presentation of my Digital Lacy project</ref>, live at the Université de Caen Normandie. Yes, in French.</p>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Weds 13 March</head>
                  <p>According to a map and indeed to common sense, the most direct way of getting from Bristol to Caen is not via London and Eurostar but via  Portsmouth and ferry.  It also takes less time if trains are timely and costs considerably less money. So that is what we did. We got up infeasibly early, ordered an Uber, and arrived at Bristol TM a good half hour before the train to Portsmouth was due to appear. Which it then did not: indeed for one heart-stopping moment it advertised itself as having been cancelled, before reinstating itself as merely 15 minutes late. It then went into that strange limbo which  very much delayed trains sometimes do: we knew it was there (because we were on  it); we know it was in progress (because it was moving on) but no online timetable system would admit to its existence. GWR staff explained that this was because of something called a set swap, necessitated by the train arriving late into TM from Cardiff, further delayed by the fact that only the driver of the delayed Cardiff train could prosecute the journey. Or something. Anyway, it left and stubbornly remained 15 minutes late all the way to Portsmouth.</p>
                  <p>Where, I regret to say, there are two stations, one very much nearer to the Continental ferry port than the other. No prizes for guessing at which one we chose to detrain and were misdirected to the Isle of Wight ferry, before rushing  back in search of a friendly taxi to the right ferry port. As we approached the taxi, a Brittany Ferries functionary phoned solicitous for our welfare, since we were by  now decidedly late for checkin. Onward! We bundled out of the taxi 10 minutes later and into the ferry port, where assorted functionaries processed passports and boarding cards in record time, since everyone else was by now waiting for us on a little bus. Not sure  I like being that annoying person who makes every one wait, but at least you don’t have to wait yourself. And so into the bowels  of the utterly wonderful good ship Mont St Michel,  which has had a  substantial and vaguely Titanic-inspired make-over and  now looks much cleaner than I remember it from the last time -- many years ago. We have booked a posh above decks cabin, so we can enjoy the view in comfort while decompressing  after the journey. </p>
                <figure><graphic url="20240313_145406.jpg"/><head>Posh above decks cabin and view</head></figure>
                  <p>Promptly at 3 pm, the ferry starts to move imperceptibly out of the harbour, past the Isle of Wight, and assorted bits of mysterious military  and naval hardware, and into the Channel. We lunch with the lorry drivers (not as good as I remember), and take tea. I probably looked briefly at my slides again.  The sea was wondrous calm, and our progress stately and unhurried. Six hours later, we  were allowed to stagger across the gang plank, down the walkway, and out onto dry land, at a place called Ouistreham. Just opposite the ferry port, as predicted, is the Ibis Styles hotel, where my booking has apparently been cancelled by mistake, but no matter, they still have room for us to collapse in. Which we do.  It’s an Ibis,<hi rend="italic">comme les autres</hi>, more or less and we have had  a long day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Thurs 14 March</head>
                  <p>Next morning, we rejoice in the traditional Ibis french breakfast, and then go in search of a bus.  The best efforts of Google Maps take us to a bus stop, where two other elderly persons are waiting, usually a good sign but on this occasion it  seems we have all missed one  bus, and the next one isn’t due for another  45 minutes.  So despite the baggage we walk into the centre of the charming seaside  village of Ouistreham, admiring its seaside architecture and its tidy gardens. Also it’s not raining.  When the bus suddenly appears, I am still grappling with the  problem of working out how to pay for  tickets, which has to be done online, involving more registering and password typing than I am prepared to envisage this early in the day. But the fat bus driver gives a pleasantly gallic shrug and indicates we can get on anyway.</p>
                  <p>And so to the familiar centre of Caen, where I have not been for five years or so,  but which looks much the same. We catch the tram to the University and lug the luggage  up to the <hi rend="italic">Maison de Recherche en Sciences Humaines</hi>, or as I like to think of it “Mrs H”.</p>
                  <p>We are staying in the visitors flats attached to the Maison, another new experience for me. The “studio” in question proves to be reasonably comfortable if spartan, although getting into it involves  a scary spiral staircase. We dump the bags, and go in search of refreshment in the Cafeteria (<hi rend="italic">plat de jour</hi>  for me; <hi rend="italic">salade de jour</hi>  for L; she wins) Three people I recognise recognise me back, which is nice. PY is of course <hi rend="italic">débordé</hi>, but promises a time to meet, which gives us enough time in between to walk into town and get some provisions. Though walking into town proves to be not as I had expected, since access to the Chateau is currently blocked by renovations against the proper summer tourist trade. Back in PY’s office at the appointed hour, we go through my slides, with PY pointing out missing accents and other infelicities, while enthusing generally about the pedagogy, and me trying to keep up  making corrections.  I also  say hello to the équipe and get a recommendation  for dinner – the nearest place being <hi rend="italic">L’assiette de beurre</hi>, since the <hi rend="italic">Ptit Gibus</hi> is  closed. </p>
                  <p>End of Friday, so all the students are departing for the weekend familiale. We potter down to L’assiette and get there in good time – indeed they have only just opened.  Our first decent meal in several  days: L had the tongue, and I followed the <hi rend="italic">suggestion du jour</hi>, which was bits of duck. Worth the money, just about. And so to bed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Fri 15 March</head>
                  <p>Nobody appeared muttering “Beware the Ides of March” so I kept to the plan. No, of course the display system didn’t quite work the first time round, nor indeed the second. But a superior person arrived to fix that (the trick is seemingly to tell the browser to display 90% of the screen, not all of it) and I duly I chuntered on about Lacy’s Acting Edition for 90 minutes, falling over not too many gaps in vocab and  firing off mistaken gender assignations like a pro (so Lilette, sitting at the back, said). The questions were interesting and did not dry up completely. You can see the slides here <ptr target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2024-03-15_caen.html"/> and I am told there will also be a video some day soon.  <hi rend="italic">Et in Arcadia ego</hi>  – we then adjourned for  lunch to <hi rend="italic">L’Acadiane</hi>  a very correct resto perched on the edge of the campus and catering almost exclusively for the university staff (the students go to the pizza joint next door, apparently owned by the same enterprise),  I had quite a lot of wine, and a savoury galette with <hi rend="italic">magret de canard</hi>. Six or so of PY’s team, were also invited to lunch which was all very jolly, and there was much discussion.,</p>
                  <p>After a lengthy post prandial nap, we set out for a walk into town, down the hill, through the abandoned and increasingly decrepit protestant cemetery where I once again  failed to locate the tomb of Beau Brummel though Wikipedia assures me it is there somewhere. And then of course it started to rain. Not just your usual Norman mist, but a  proper downpour, forcing us to take shelter in a cafe and drink tea for half an hour or so. I rediscovered the route through the little 1970s shopping precinct near the former Hotel Quatrans, where are still to be found Normandy’s only (sfaik) réunionnais  resto , a gaming mecca called “Le temple du geek”, a nice bookshop called “Le coin du Polar” etc. And then some silly shopping for belts and jewellers. And so to an early dinner with PY at the <hi rend="italic">Bouchon du Vaugueux</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Entrée: paté  de lapin; plat: poulet a la crème; dessert: café  gourmand</hi>) <figure><graphic url="20240315_200015.jpg"/><head>poulet a la creme, restaurant stylee</head></figure>. Burp. Stagger back up  the hill engaging PY in smalltalk  Good night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Sat 16 March</head>
                  <p>Holiday starts  officially today. Down the hill, clompety clomp, trundle trundle, no 2 tram to the station, looking for a train to Valognes. Which is 10 mins late, having had to come all the  way from Paris, poor thing. We have first  class comfort at the very end of the train so we really don’t  care. Negotiate a plausible arrival  time with AirBNB host lady, once we have established that the address we want is in fact 15 rue de Barneville, as indicated on Google, and not  15 route de Barneville, as she initially insists, even though that is  5 miles away in the countryside. And when we get to Valognes here are Jef and Nicole ready to chauffeur us thither. A small smartly converted barn with a toilet inexplicably located  on the ground floor and a bathroom and bedroom at the top of a winding staircase. Also lots of electric radiators which I have no idea how to make them work.  Oh and the wifi is not where they say it is either. Well, we’re not staying here for long.</p>
                  <p>In Normandy, rain comes unpredictably in little bits and pieces interspersed with misleading bits of sunshine. Also in Normandy, or at least this bit of it,  the  roads are very straight but switchback like. Jef drives in a sober and restrained manner, fortunately. He did a lot of driving, with L and L chattering away in the back seat like two school girls. We visited the Chateau Gratot, a rather interesting ruin with a very long history and many ducks; we also visited the former home of Jacques Prevert which has a much shorter one. We saw Surville, where what is allegedly  the tiniest harbour in France has been constructed.  We eat very well, once at the Auberge de Pecheurs in Port Bail sur mer (actual fresh fish and chips), and several times in Nicole and Jef’s gaff. On Sunday, Nicole brought out her <hi rend="italic">raclette</hi>  kit,  and we were suitably impressed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Mon 18 March</head>
                  <p>One weekend <hi rend="italic">en famille</hi>  later we are driven to Coutances, a largish town, with a vast gothic cathedral on top of a hill. The station is at the bottom of the hill so we parked there, and walked up the hill in search of coffee and croissants befor starting our journey  to La Rochelle, via Nantes and Rennes. Or in fact, via Granville, the terminus where the first little TER we took sat down, changed driver, and generally gave signs of being out of breath, before changing direction out of the station, and proceeding 10 minutes late for Rennes, where we changed onto another little TER, en route for  Nantes. A much grander station, with escalators  and enough  time (40 mins)  to grab a sandwich for lunch from the Relay before we piled onto  a slightly grander Intercité train courtesy of Breton Railways, all the way down the coast to La Rochelle,arriving at 1939.</p>
                  <p>At La Rochelle, we had a short walk out of the station and up Charles de Gaulle avenue to the old port, and the dead posh Ibis Hotel I had sensibly booked already. Too tired for dinner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Tues 19 March</head>
                  <p>Another Ibis quality breakfast, and a general sense of holiday time. We had an hour or so to wander  around the main monuments of La Rochelle’s old port, basking in the unexpected spring sunshine before finding our way back to the station and over the new Josephine Baker bridge to the even newer bus station where the 1240  bus to the Ile de Re awaits. It takes 45 minutes to get through La Rochelle’s unlovely conurbation  and out to the Belvedere overlooking the bridge to the island. And even longer to trundle through many villages before reaching the very last on the island, as far from the mainland as you can get, the evocatively named “Ars en Ré” . It has a lot of small white houses arranged along narrow streets and a scattering of elderly buildings, many  of them now subsumed into the posh hotel where we are staying. Outside the village there is agriculture (some vines, some potatoes, and – on the salt marshy bits – oysters and sheep)  and there are camp sites. To the North, the island is sheltered by lots of salt marsh, where they grow the oysters and (I believe) samphire, and harvest the salt. To the South there are woods and dunes and eventually, a sandy beach and the waves of the Atlantic. Quebec is over that way, I believe.</p>
                  <p>3.30 is not a good time to be looking for lunch anywhere in France, but especially not here, since apparently Tuesday  is early closing day.  The only place which would deign to serve us was the Café de Commerce; this  overlooks Ars’s recently constructed tiny harbour and has a curious but not unpleasant interior décor of vaguely American inspiration (the barman is trained to show you where there is a bullet hole in one of the mirrors behind the bar). There is nothing unsugary available for lunch except for a variety of galettes  so I have the biggest one on offer, and Lilette has a smaller one. Then back to our boutique hotel for a brief snooze. </p>
               </div>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Wed 20 March</head>
                  <p>Woken today by much banging and muttering from two workmen outside our window on the amusingly-named rue  Tourettes. They are (I discover eventually) trying to make safer the weather-worn 17th century stone tower I can see from my bed, which is currently falling down. By lunch time they have successfully inserted a steel girder to hold it up and wrapped the whole site up in wooden packaging.  Today we explored the Ile de Ré to the North, Mr Google guiding us along cycle paths and farm tracks. We discovered the only supermarket in the area, and bought nibbles and for me espadrilles so I could discard my clumpy boots at last. After lunch I sat in the sunny terrace and tapped on my laptop in a desultory sort of way. Dinner at the Hotel Clocher across the square was a little disappointing : I had canard with rice, L had something called risotto swimming in a  creamy sauce and resembling rice pudding more than anything else. </p></div>
                  <div type="div4">
                     <head>Thur 21 March</head>
                     <p>Morning breakfast on the terrace, enlivened by lengthy  diatribe from local help, former engineer, detailing the pernicious effect of AirBnb, deploring the pace of modern life, the impossibility of maintaining peasant ways etc etc. We agreed with him, and went to the beach. Mr G let me down by claiming that a road existed where none was to  be found, so we spent more time walking along the sand than intended. But how wonderful to be walking along an entirely deserted stretch of sand, with occasional bits of driftwood to sit on, no sound but the crashing of waves and the chanting of birds, and the sun shining brightly. We then had a late lunch at the next door posh resto which was very pleasant .</p>
                  </div>
               <div type="div3">
                  <head>Fri 22 March</head>
                  <p>Time to go home. We had a leisurely breakfast, checked out, and walked down to the bus stop, half an hour earlier than needful. It was HOT. I phoned the TAD and arranged for a transport tomorrow. The bus to La R. appeared and got us to the station in plenty of time. And then fate intervened as it sometimes, thankfully not often, does. The train we were aiming for, and on top of which a teetering pile of consequent arrangements depended, was announced with first 60 minutes, than 2 hours of delay.</p>
                  <p>La Rochelle station  was littered with the debris, including a large troupe of small children en colonie de vacances, being first shouted out and then cajoled into group play. It seems there has been a major accident this morning somewhere on the TGV Atlantique line, which has brought all trains into and out of Paris Montparnasse to a halt. After some lengthy weighing up of alternatives,  and despairing of ever finding a quiet spot to sit in the shade, we decide to give up on trains for today, and try again tomorrow. This meant (a) queuing up for 20  minutes in the ticket office to change tickets for free (b) staying an extra night at the Ibis vieux port. Which seemed less stressful than trying to find somewhere quiet and cool to wait at La Rochelle station. And so dear reader we did. </p></div><div type="div3">
                  <head>Sat 23 March</head>
                  <p>Another nice Ibis breakfast. Another stroll down to La Rochelle gare, which is much less busy  this morning.  Our train leaves on time, but makes up for that eccentricity quite soon: five minutes late at Niort, ten minutes late at the next station. But  we have comfortable first class seats and the nice ticket man says our  correspondence at Poitiers is assured, so we might as well enjoy the ride. Which is scenic and varied. At Poitiers, we hump our luggage down to platform 41 (a bay) without time to buy a sandwich, and board the slow train to Limoges, a TER which stops everywhere. The countryside changes as we leave the Central Region and enter the Haute Vienne. And look, at last, here is Limoges station, and they have opened the new buffet bar just in time for us to buy a sandwich.  30 minutes Intercité ride  to La Souterraine. Here is Lucy, here is Lidl, here is La Vergne: we're home again. And about time too.</p>
               </div>
  
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
