<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../diaryPrint.css" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>2024: nothing new</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-09-17">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <!-- <head>2024: still nothing new</head>
 -->
   <!--<figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/2023-timeline.png"
     width="450px" height="500px"/>
    <head>European end of my time line</head>
   </figure>-->
   <p>What's left to say about the year 2024? Almost, but not quite, everything this year seems to
    have been a replay of something that happened last year, with some minor variation in the
    detail... but, no, there were two distinct novelties. We enjoyed some excellent theatre -- <ref
    target="https://southwarkplayhouse.co.uk/productions/cable-street">the new musical Cable
    Street</ref> (twice), <ref
    target="https://www.theatreroyal.org.uk/events/sweeney-todd-a-victorian-melodrama/">a splendid
    melodrama</ref> , and <ref
    target="https://www.theatreroyal.org.uk/events/snow-white-the-seven-dwarfs/">a fine panto</ref>
    -- and I gave two presentations about<ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy"> my friend Mr
    Lacy</ref> disguised as a real academic. </p>

   <p> <label>January</label> On the 19th, P&amp;P took us out for lunch to one of the pubs in
    Oldbury on Severn (was it the Ship or the Anchor?), after which we inspected the charming Church
    of Saint Arilda, commanding splendid views of the Severn Bridge. <figure>
    <graphic url="../media/20240119_000000.jpg"/>
    <head>Sundown at St Arilda's</head>
    </figure></p>
   <p> <label>February</label> On the 17th we were in Maryland for Elizabeth's birthday, notable
    this year for balloons and a gold bangle from the Dragon Workshop. <figure>
    <graphic url="../media/20240217_183208.jpg"/>
    <head>Birthday Balloons</head>
    </figure></p>
   <p>This was followed by a trip to exotic Southwark to see <ref
    target="https://southwarkplayhouse.co.uk/productions/cable-street-1/">Cable Street the Musical
    (Mk1)</ref>. We stayed in a Travelodge over the road and ate at a rather disappointing street
    food market. Back in the West Country, on the 24th, P&amp;P took us to the Clevedon Gardeners
    Club show, where we ate too much cake and were impressed by vegetables. </p>
   <p> <label>March</label> At the start of the month, we went to Nottingham to enjoy Belinda's new
    klezmer band in action, which was a musical treat. And then, hoorah for <ref
    target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/2024-03-13.html">An expedition across the Hexagon</ref>
    during which we went on a mostly Norman holiday, taking in my first ever talk all about Lacy's
    Acting Edition (in French), a visit to Jef and Nicole, some tourism on the Ile De Re, and
    getting stuck in La Rochelle, before proceeding to La Vergne for a couple of weeks. Follow the
    link for more details and lovely photos. </p>
   <p> <label>April</label> Leaving La Vergne on the 15th, we experimented with the
    La-Souterraine-Limoges-Poitiers-Tours-Caen route back to the ferry. It took a while, but the
    trains all connected. In Caen, Mrs H's <hi>Comité Scientifique</hi> was its usual sybaritic
    self, of course. On the evening of the 18th, we took the overnight ferry back to Portsmouth,
    this time paying fopr a belowdecks cabin, which was a rather unpleasant box. Back in Portsmouth
    Harbour and Southsea station we had a long wait for the first train to Bristol, on a very chilly
    morning. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="../media/20240419_070138.jpg"/>
    <head>It's seven a.m. and this is a war memorial</head>
   </figure>

   <p> <label>May</label> This month I headed back to La Vergne on my own, via Caen, Tours, and
    Vierzon: see further <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/2024-05-20.html">Another Tours de
    force</ref> </p>
   <p> <label>June</label> We are visited in Bristol by (most of) the Kayes, which provides the
    occasion for a rare (almost complete) family photo: <figure>
    <graphic url="../media/20240615_170538.jpg"/>
    <head>Fromage de famille</head>
    </figure> Also this month, I had another summer school teaching gig so proceeded back to France
    on my own. The journey to Lyon, via London and Paris, with major train delays at every step, is
    painstakingly documented in <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/2024-06-17.html">Best Laid
    Plans</ref>, as is the continuation from Lyon to Gueret during which I learned (from experience)
    the French for bus replacement service. For the last week of the month, Lilette came out to join
    me contemplating the grass growing at La Vergne, and we then we flew back together from Limoges
    to Bristol without incident. </p>
   <p> <label>July</label> Birthday lunches for Lilette at Sonny Stores on the 10th and for Coco at
    The Stratford Bamboo Mat on the 13th. Unbirthday lunch at Nando's Park Street for the mysterious
    Mr and Mrs Robert Price. Birthday dinner chez Bekhradnia for Bahram on the 24th. And, as
    aforesaid, to Bath on the 23rd for <ref
    target="https://www.theatreroyal.org.uk/events/sweeney-todd-a-victorian-melodrama/">a splendid
    melodrama</ref>, though not one included in Lacy's Acting Edition.</p>
   <p> <label>August</label> This month we made a quick round of visits before evaporating to France
    for what was left of the summer. This turned out to need complex planning to cope with
    unexpected Mauritian arrivals. On the 4th we went to Nottingham, staying at an AirBnb on Loscoe
    Rd, to celebrate Harvey's birthday; we also visited Wollaton Hall and saw huge trees, tiny
    artworks, and lots of deer. On the 9th we went Maryland, staying at the Ibis Stratford, to
    celebrate Daphne's birthday on the 9th. On the 11th we were back in Bristol welcoming Roger and
    Olive. And on the 15th we took the ferry from Portsmouth back to Caen, and thence to La Vergne,
    via Paris and La Souterraine, which is (a bit) speedier though more expensive. The journey
    passed this time without incident. The news of Michael Sperberg McQueen's unexpected decease hit
    Facebook and therefore also La Vergne a few days later, and I spent some time pondering the best
    sort of response, <ref target="https://balisage.net/RememberingMSM.html"> as did many other
    people</ref>. In Bussière, we did more or less nothing much except for the occasional excursion;
    the fete de St Syphorien at the end of the month passed as it always does with a splendid
    procession of tractor-hauled floral floats, excellent music, and dancing girls. </p>
   <p> <label>September</label> We returned to Caen for a different Comite Scientifique meeting,
    which was interesting, and thence via Paris and London back home to Bristol on the 6th, since
    Mrs H was paying. We had a few days to sort things out for a visit from Mr and Mrs Feigenbaum on
    which we took them to the same pub in OldBury on Severn (but was it the Anchor or the Ship?),
    despite car problems ; on the 13th we went to London again, partly for Al's birthday, but mostly
    for Cable Street (Mk 2) which was much better than Mk 1, whatever <ref
    target="https://www.musicalsmagazine.com/features/article/cable-street-review">this
    reviewer</ref> says; we stayed at Z Hotel Shoreditch in an overpriced un-windowed cellar; on the
    18th cheerful plumbers came and restored hot water apparently without needing to send in a
    little bill. </p>
   <p> <label>October and November</label> The first fortnight of October I seem to have been
    walking up to the Clifton Observatory rather frequently, with no other motivation than a need
    for exercise and a desire for this -dare I say - iconic view <figure>
    <graphic url="../media/20241004_122800.jpg"/>
    <head>As seen on tv</head>
    </figure> </p>
   <p> On the 15th, however I set off from Clifton Down for France again, solus. I have to teach
    "TEI niveau 2" in Tours, but there's a week before and after it during which, despite the wintry
    weather, I will hide away in La Vergne, before proceeding (yes, again) to Caen to give a real
    academic conference paper in English at a real academic conference. Read all about it at <ref
    target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/2024-11-09.html">Once more with feeling</ref>!</p>

   <p> <label>December</label> On the 6th, I went to Oxford for a brief lunchtime reunion of ex-OUCS
    employees, those who are not yet dead. A curious experience, which I may write about elsewhere
    some time. I proceeded from there to London for another Stratford weekend with the Kayes before
    returning to Bristol on the 8th for the traditional, not to say inevitable, end of year
    amusements and over-eating-occasions, namely viz, my birthday dinner at Pam's; a wedding
    anniversary lunch at the Ivy; and a vast Xmas lunch at Sarah's with everyone except Elizabeth
    and company. 
    <figure><graphic url="../media/20241209_184513.jpg"/><head>Pam's cat watching us lunch </head></figure>
    <figure><graphic url="../media/20241223_185348.jpg"/><head>Congratulatory cake from the Ivy </head></figure>
    
    But the high spot of the season was undoubtedly (as it should be) going to see the
    panto at Bath, with Elizabeth, Daphne, Coco, and Leon.</p>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
