<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Once more, with feeling</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <editionStmt>
    <edition>
     <date>2024-12-24</date>
    </edition>
   </editionStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <listChange>
    <change>
     <name/>
     <date>2024-12-24</date>
    </change>
   </listChange>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
  
         <p>My final trip to France this year was another solo expedition, and  much the same as before. I took an evening Eurostar on Oct 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, arriving in time for dinner, stayed overnight at an over priced hotel within walking distance of the Gare D’Austerlitz (Hotel Formio) and got up early enough to catch the 0930 train to La Souterraine  where, eventually, Lucy came to pick me up. The sun shone and the journey was entirely uneventful. A quick rush round Lidl and so to La Vergne, where the water is still on, and the weeds are not yet reduced to wintery proportions, The plan is to spend a week here before proceeding to Tours for the celebrated Formation TEI-XML Niveau 1; then come back for a further week finalising my presentation for the Punch Pocket Books conference and then travel via Vierzon to Caen in order to deliver same, before proceeding to Nottingham for Belinda’ s birthday. Spoiler alert: it all went according to plan.</p>
         <p>I made a half hearted attempt attempt to trim the garden, but rain stopped play fairly rapidly. I inspected the newly installed (by Patrice)  bed in the annexe and it seemed fine, and the plumbing problem seems to have been resolved. I scouted around for remnants of firewood and found a little, though  not enough for the long haul.  Srill smarting from the pain of realising I was being conned by the fake internet wood sellers back in September, I splash out on some  amazon-hosted purveyors of outrageously over priced fire wood  for the rest of the week. I eat. I order the TAD to take me to Gueret market on Saturday, and so it does. The place Bonnyaud is being reconfigured, yet again, to allow for more parking places, and the market is consequently all over the place. The headline story  in <title>La Montagne</title> is all about the American take over of the suppliers of dolipran, which is (I learn) France’s preferred pain killer. The cafe de la poste is full of old farts drinking coffee: I join them thankfully before the TAD reappears and drives me back home. Next day, being Sunday, the sun comes out and I walk into Bussiere for a change, to see that yes,  O’Tilleul really is shut for good. I go and sit on a bench round the corner in the place de Tilleuls to enjoy the sunshine, and pass the time ordering train tickets for my next few journeys, before returning to La Petite Surface  to take coffee chez Oceane. All very quiet: and I take the  scenic route  home over the hills, pausing to contemplate the partially drained Etang de la Vergne as dusk approaches.  Very relaxing, up till the moment later that evening when I realised I have somehow contrived to lose my wallet, and  panic sets in. Various phone calls ensue. Maybe I left it at Oceans – but she can’t check till Tuesday. Maybe I dropped it on my walk,though  this seems unlikely. Maybe someone will have found it and handed it in at the Mairie, which seems even more unlikely. In any case, nothing is to be done till Monday, when everything is shut. So I pass a miserable night feeling very stupid, having temporarily frozen the French bank card on which everything (more or less) depends. And on Monday, I deliberately retrace my steps, even though  the scenic route is not just less scenic but also much steeper uphill in reverse. Before checking at the Mairie, I walk back to the bench in the place des Tilleuls and…  my heart leaps, somewhat shamefully, but definitely it leaps. For here is my wallet,  sitting patiently on the bench where I parked it yesterday, ignored by everyone and everything except a somewhat startled beetle who must have taken refuge inside it last night.  You see, as I told you, everything on this trip went to plan, sort of. </p>
   <figure><graphic url="../media/20241021_110246.jpg" width="80%"/><head>Blink and you'll miss it</head></figure>
         <p>Later on, I realised that the train ticket bookings I had made (which were the proximate cause of all this kerfuffle) had not benefited from the reduction in price due to holders of a valid Carte Senior, due to said carte being itself in need of renewal. So I renewed it, cancelled all the bookings, and rebooked everything, thus resulting in an overall saving of ooh maybe 9 euros, certainly more than 5. And of course a pleasant sensation of having finally set the world to rights again.  </p>
         <p>On Wednesday afternoon, Lucy reappeared and drove me back to La Souterraine in good time for the 1530 departure for Vierzon, with onward connexion to Tours. Since it’s Wednesday afternoon and I am in first class, the trains are both quiet and the journey unremarkable. The CESR has booked me into what turns out to be a rather pleasant little hotel in a quiet back street, five minutes walk from the main drag, and the CESR, and everywhere else really. According to long established tradition, the <foreign>formateurs</foreign> (Alexei, Mathieu and I) are taken out for dinner each of the three evenings by a different person: first up is Chiara who awaits us at the Bistrot des Halles this Wednesday. As ever my enjoyment of the dinner is tempered by worrying about the need to  get up early the following morning to greet this year’s punters at 0900.  And as ever,the next day I worry that this is all going a bit too slickly and easily and shouldn’t some of these slides be updated or even retired ? But the punters seem to be lapping it up, still. In the evening, we are to dine at a place called “Ceci’bon” where the apostrophe is presumably to indicate that the first word is not pronounced as you might expect. This is an odd little establishment in a very old cellar which I stumbled upon by chance last time I was in Tours (in May), and which Elena has independently decided to invite us to. Day 2 of the course unrolls as usual,  following which Marie-Luce invites us to dine at the justly famed Bistrot des belles caves.And so to Saturday morning and  the last stretch of the course, which (again) goes better than I thought it should. If I were in charge,  it would  worry me that this course is taught entirely by contractual staff not associated  with the Universite de Tours, all of them male. But tradition is tradition, and this one presumably contributes something to the CESR’s finances so there is little motivation to rethink it after gosh is that the time already 12 years ... At the end of the day, I meet up with Alexei and his train driver friend for a drink and a chat,  followed by a nice light dinner at Le plazza. I don’t think I’ve ever had a conversation with a train driver before, certainly not in French. </p>
         <p>Next morning I have a lazy breakfast, and there is time to visit the market before catching my train at midday. Tours market is, as ever, full of so many good things to eat it’s impossible to make a rational decision which ones to buy. I think I settled on a large sausage though.  And just as I am starting to wander back down to the station, I run into an extraordinary long procession of aged people  wearing ancient costume, clearly in honour of something or other. I  takes me a while and some internet searching to determine that these are members of something called the <title>Confrérie des Talmeliers du Bon Pain de Saint-Martin de Touraine à Tours</title>, and if I had not had to rush off to catch a train I should have stuck with them for the chance of getting some specially blessed bread after the ceremony they were heading to.  <ref target="../media/20241027_101429.mp4">This video</ref> shows some of the participants on their approach to the market: they don’t look very happy yet, but there’s a lot more processing to come before they get to the splendid free lunch described here: <ref target="https://www.facebook.com/domainedelahuberdiere/posts/33ème-chapitre-de-la-confrérie-des-talmeliers-du-bon-pain-de-st-martin-de-tourai/1063054265830246/">https://www.facebook.com/domainedelahuberdiere/posts/33%C3%A8me-chapitre-de-la-confr%C3%A9rie-des-talmeliers-du-bon-pain-de-st-martin-de-tourai/1063054265830246/</ref>from which  I am happy to quote this peroration :  <hi rend="italic">Longue vie à cette manifestation pour valoriser et mettre à l’honneur les métiers de la boulangerie-pâtisserie et la gastronomie française, pilier des valeurs à la française.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>And so by yet another uneventful punctual train ride via Vierzon, to La Souterraine, and the ever reliable Lucy-lift back to La Vergne. I am  planning to stay here in monkish seclusion for at least a week working on a presentable version of my first ever real live non-computer-related conference paper. Which I mostly do, though there are a few distractions, mostly related to the problem of keeping warm and well fed, since winter is definitely setting in. Fortunately my neighbour Patrice is now back, and willing to help with the logistics of getting a load of logs, though it takes a while. On Wednesday, eventually, he attaches Sebastian’s trailer to his massive motor and off we go to M. Antoine Tison’s farm on the outskirts of Saint Vaury. Here, after some more prevarication, a bright yellow tractor driven by a picturesque rural person disgorges several mouthfuls of logs into the trailer. I hand over my 80 euros, and off we go, pausing for lunch at L’etape creusois.And back home Patrice energetically unloads  the trailer into successive wheelbarrow loads that I then  stack up in the sheltered space appointed. They’re not the best logs I’ve ever burned, but they fill the gap.  </p>
         <p>My monastic week went reasonably well.  I made a warm spot in the dining room to work during the day, and lit the log burner around tea time so that I could continue to work of an evening.  I went out for the occasional walk round the lake, now much reduced for the annual fish-purge. 
          </p><figure><graphic url="../media/20241031_163055.jpg" width="90%"/><head>View across the shrinking plan d'eau</head></figure><p>
          I took the TAD into Gueret to consult with an expert on my tv reception problems and also to buy some smart new shoes. On  a couple of occasions I was invited to drink rum with Patrice.  On the one hand, this means I have to listen patiently to his proto-fascistic ranting without losing my temper; on the other, he renders  me numerous services, like the afore mentioned log trundling, junk disposal, and indeed the use of a printer when my own died the death.  I needed the printer because by  the 1st  November, I had a draft of my conference paper ready and needed to test the reading of it. Various earlier drafts had hared off over various topics some way removed from the abstract I sent back in the summer; I spent the next few days  sweating the resulting verbiage down to a precisely-focussed 3000  words (as recommended by Philip). By Monday 4th, I had something to read and a set of slides to go with it, which I duly celebrated with home made chips and roast duck. </p>
         <p>On the 6th  Lucy drove me back to La Souterraine,  whence I took the train all the way to Austerlitz again, but this time I crossed the bridge over the Seine to the gare de Lyon metro, to catch the ligne 13 to Gare St Lazare. A much travelled and heavily signposted route, since the Olympics at any rate. And at St Lazare I had time to  buy fancy chocolates for Belinda, to complement the possibly horrible gluten-free ones I’d bought already in Tours, before taking my comfy seat on board the 1558 Nomad departure to Caen, arriving on time at  1653. As a self-funded private researcher I have to do everything for myself from now on, including  finding my hotel (Hotel Francois d’O, very convenient for the Quatrans tram stop), finding my own dinner,  and locating the conference itself the following morning (not so difficult – it is hosted by my old friend Mrs H.) .  </p>
         <p>And so to the conference in question: the Punch Pocket Book Project’s inaugural event on  “Victorian humour and the digital”. I wrote a short blog entry about this immediately after the event (<ptr target="https://foxglove.hypotheses.org/949"/>) ,  which was also picked up by the conference’s own blogger (see <ptr target="https://ppbka.hypotheses.org/696"/> ) under the heading  <title> We Were, in Fact, Amused</title>. As indeed we were, both by the mixture of topics addressed and the manner of addressing them. It’s been many years since I participated as a nervous speaker at an academic conference,  and moreover without an aura of technological flim flam. It seemed to go down reasonably well, as did the post conference drink social event, after which a small subset of those depicted in the photo joined me for a very nice dinner at the Saveurs de la Reunion restaurant, still in business.</p>
         <p>Next morning, I stay luxuriously in bed till past 10 a.m. and then put on my (new) travelling shoes. Back to the station, back to Paris, back to London, and then (just for a change) a train to Nottingham. St Pancras station is largely spectacle now: there is no customer service, no first class lounge, and the bar bears only notional resemblance to what a station bar should look like. And the beer is outrageously priced. Never mind. I filled up on free tea and biscuits on board my train when I finally was allowed on it. And so to Belinda's in good time to celebrate her birthday!</p>
   <figure><graphic url="../media/20241110_125901.jpg"/><head>Belinda Birthday Lunch, Sherwood</head></figure>   </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
