<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>More hopeful travelling (contd)</title>
            <author/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2024-05-21T18:24:32.679439424</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <name/>
               <date>2024-05-26T16:57:04.761991101</date>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body><head>Another Tours de force</head><p>My second trip to France this year was a solo one, revisiting Caen only incidentally, since it was financed by the Université of Tours...</p><div>
          <head>Monday 20 May</head>
         <p>Why does the Great Western Railway persist in torturing me with its so-called service from Bristol via Westbury to Southampton and, eventually, Portsmouth? Last time I used it, the train was seriously delayed and I almost missed the ferry (see <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/2024-03-13.html">details of that  adventure </ref>); this time, I meticulously built some spare minutes into my proposed timetable (a 0926 from Clifton Down, to ensure I caught the 1020 from Temple Meads) , only to have my morning slumbers perturbed by news that there wouldn’t be any 1020 to catch, it having been cancelled “due to a problem with a preceding train” whatever that means. So I rescheduled  hastily since I was awake anyway, and Ubered myself and my bag to Temple Meads in good time to catch the 0920 instead. The sun shone, my fellow passengers seemed cheerful, the train pootled along through the idyllic countryside and I  wished I’d picked up some breakfast goodies at TM before joining it.</p>
         <p>Portsmouth and Southsea station, when I finally get there is just as I remember – a Victorian lady mistreated and shamed by the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>  century. Tutting briefly I head into the unlovely shopping precinct which now lies on the other side of the even less lovely streams of traffic encircling her and search for breakfast. The shopping centre offers a choice of Greggs, Macdonalds,  and (strangely) Korean noodle joints, so I start the day with some udon soup. Persistence eventually uncovers the existence or maybe survival would be a better word, of “Jenny’s Cafe” a proper greasy spoon, tucked away down a side street behind building works, where I get something like coffee and some rather nice greasy mushrooms on toast. And by now, it’s clear that I am going to persist in the folly of walking to the Ferry Port, even though this means walking along the A10, competing for breathing space with dozens of lorries. But the sun is still shining and it’s only 10, maybe 15 minutes. </p>
         <p>At 2.15 pm promptly the process of boarding the ferry to Ouistreham begins, and not a moment too soon since the terminal building is now awash with newly arrived French school kids travelling in the opposite direction. This time I have booked a reclining chair in what turns out to be a rather pleasant quiet lounge at the back end of the ship, along with the other geriatric passengers. Encumbered with only one bag, I am free to experiment with several other locations on the ship during the six hour crossing, including sitting outside on deck (very nice till the wind got up), inside in a bar (also quite nice until the entertainment lady kicked off), and even the highly expensive and pretentious restaurant (more my kind of thing, let’s face it). And so, eventually, once the cleaning staff have boarded,  to disembarkation time, ashort stroll through the Ouistreham dusk to the Hotel Phare and a much needed bed. </p>
        </div><div> <head>Tues 21 May</head>
         <p>I get out of bed reluctantly at about 9 and make a dramatic entrance into the breakfast room by falling down a step I hadn’t noticed, resulting in a little broken crockery, but no other damage. The sky is still grey, but I have time to explore Ouistrehan, so set off on a brisk walk to the beach, which is not as close as it looks on the map. But worth the walk, if only for the sudden appearance of a street full of cosy little seaside shops such as us retired folks enjoy the world over. This particular beach was of course one of The Normandy Beaches of 1944 fame, and so there are pictures of brave service personnel hanging from every lamp-post as  well as many flags fluttering in the grayness. Lots of traditional Normandy souvenirs as well of course. The beach has a large and rather out of place London-Eye-style wheel, and  is also covered in small sheds, which I think must once  have been used as bathing machines. If I had more time I would explore it more thoroughly, but since I have to be back before 11 to vacate my hotel room, I rewind  my brisk walk, reclaim my bag, and proceed to wait for the 1122 express bus into Caen. Which duly arrives, and deposits me at the Gare where I continue to wait, this time for the 1250 train to Tours. A lot of waiting about on this trip, clearly.</p>
         <p>The journey is for the most part sunny, and the train is not busy, so I do some pottering about on my laptop as we leave Normandy and enter the Central Region, pausing at numerous stations to check if anyone wants to get on or off.  It’s a three hour journey, and it’s raining in Tours when we get there. My shoes get so wet that I impetuously purchase a new pair from the first shoe shop I meet on the walk to the hotel.  Which was not a good idea, as things turned out. Also not so good was the fact that the room allocated to me at the Hotel Mondial (which does not have a lift) turned out to be on the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>  floor, requiring me to proceed up 8 flights of stairs, a total of 85 steps (I counted). But it was comfortable enough, reasonably sized, and conveniently located (apart from its height above sea level).  In the evening I renewed my acquaintance with the tangled mass of nice old buildings almost entirely now appropriated by touristic restaurants which they call “Le vieux Tours”, and dined in splendid isolation in a cellar somewhere or other. </p>
        </div><div> <head>Weds 22 May</head>
         <p>My first engagement of the day is lunch with Toshi and Marie Luce and the rest of the gang, ahead of a special 2 pm meeting Sandrine has arranged for the benefit of a new BVH project rejoicing in the acronym “POMONE” (<hi>Poésie Manuscrite Oubliée Nouvellement Exposée</hi>), and nothing to do with fruit, so far as I can tell.  I am here, as are Alexei and Mathieu and  virtual versions of other illuminati such as Pierre Yves  via zoom, to listen politely to presentations of the project and its needs, given by PIs Claire Sicard  and Pascal Joubaud,  before suggesting some TEI-compatible approaches and software, which we duly do. Research students watch us in a goldfish like manner. Ah well: everyone seems happy anyway. And so to dinner again, huzzah, though I cannot remember where.</p>
        </div><div> <head>Thurs 23 May</head>
         <p>It’s day one of the famous TEI Niveau 2 “Advanced TEI” course today. This consists of my trying to cram <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Talks/2024-05-tours/index.html">a full day’s worth</ref> of ODD explanation and practical into a half pint pot, twice, with Elena’s and Mathieu’s  choice of other topics as light relief.  I say nothing of the surprisingly good buffet lunch, laid on in the CESR, over which we did a lot of workshop style mingling, as one does. The day was appropriately rounded out by another fine dinner, this time in the Bistrot des Belles Caves (five stars), where they don’t let you choose the wine, and a good thing too, since they have a proper sommelier to do it for you.</p>
        </div><div> <head>Fri 24 May</head>
         <p>Before anyone can say “is that all there is to it?” it’s time for Day 2 of the famous TEI Niveau 2 “Advanced TEI” course, featuring all the other bits we failed to fit into day one and a little audience participation, which went reasonably well. And everyone goes away happy, including me, heading for an earlier train  than anticipated. No-one checks my ticket, although the train is quite busy, mostly with students going home for the weekend. The route follows the valley of the Cher, which means there are quaint old houses built into aged cliffs to be seen en route. As we approach Vierzon, after a long journey of alternating rain and sunshine, suddenly  a huge and satisfyingly complete rainbow appears in the sky. I am staying in the appropriately named Hotel Arche (which does have a lift), and my room overlooks the bridge over the Canal de Berry, today framed by said rainbow. </p>
          <figure> <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/20240524_191802.jpg"/></figure><p> I will say nothing of my depressing experience in one of Vierzon’s  posher  restaurants: it was late, I was tired, the cook was incapable of dealing with a rush of (four) clients, the sommelier was more interested in preaching the virtues of his organic wines than actually getting any food delivered; the prices were absurd. So let us pass over all of that in silence, and consider instead the splendid cinematic décor of the Arche Hotel:  every available piece of wall in which is covered with last-century American film posters, covers of cinephile magazines etc.</p>
      </div><div>   <head>Sat 25 May</head>
         <p>It’s very misty when I wake up, but by the time I’ve had my undistinguished breakfast, the sun is making an effort to cheer up the market square, where I would love to fill my bags with tasty goodies and fresh veg, but alas my bag is already full of old washing. Particularly tempting are new season asparagus and strawberries: maybe later. At one end of the walk back to the station there is a little garden containing a heroic though idealized presentation of the noble Peasant; at the other, there is a slightly larger one dominated by an over-sized portrait bust of some fat capitalist/pioneering agriculturalist  called Célestin Gérard ; make of that what you will. I am taking the 1150 train to La Souterraine, where, yes I expect to be collected by Lucy, for a quick and sunny ride  back to my garden in La Vergne, where the grass is as high as an elephant’s eye, not to mention the nettles. No matter, it’s still  good to be home.</p>
  </div>    </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
