<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/a-week-of-wetness-in-la-vergne-a412b6564d8b-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A week of wetness in La Vergne</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from  https://medium.com/@louBurnard/a-week-of-wetness-in-la-vergne-a412b6564d8b and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head><hi rend="bold">A week of wetness in La Vergne</hi></head>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">SUNDAY April 1</hi></p>
<p>Sun shines! We stay in bed to make sure it’s not an april fool, then get up
as usual. I try on my blue boiler suit, bought last year at a jumble sale, but
it fits. Spend rest of day pottering around garden, mostly. Plant out herbs
bought yesterday in pots; destroy some snowdrops to make space for raspberry
bush ditto, in front. Formulate cunning plan to repurpose old meat cupboard in
the shed as safe house for lettuces, and proceed to implement same. This
involves some minor d.i.y. but is satisfyingly done by lunch time. Which is
roast lamb because that’s what Lilette took out of the freezer yesterday
thinking it was chicken, but none the worse for that. She has also made bread
pudding. After lunch, paint the Lettuce House, chat to neighbours who are busy
erecting a new terrasse, plant out some onions. Reflect over cup of tea that
this is more than enough for one day, so maybe I should start diarizing (which I
am).</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">SATURDAY march 31</hi></p>
<p>Up earlyish for TAD which is driven by strange old man who seems uncertain of
route, and asks me to navigate to his first pick up point, at Le Monteil which I
duly do with the aid of M Google, but alas Mme Chloe doesn’t show up, so we set
off to Gueret, and the market, which is still much the same, tho wet. Veg,
bread, cheese, plants for the garden, anything else? Ah yes, milk. Coffee in :e
Moderne to shelter from the rain, and then back we go, in time for lunch of
choucroute and potatos dauphinoises from the traiteurs. Light stove. Fall
asleep. Outside it continues to rain, but waits to hail till L insists on going
out for a walk. That’ll teach her.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">FRIDAY march 30</hi></p>
<p>Did lots more work on ELTeC tutorial prep. L made pasta for lunch. We
snoozed. We ordered a brand new turkish style tapis. Watched rather good Chabrol
film <hi rend="italic">La femme infidele</hi> on telly.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">THURS march 29</hi></p>
<p>L went by TAD alone to Gueret; I walked to Jean-Luc’s to get gas, wine, and
water, thus making myself late for lunch prep. I prepared potato pie, which
always takes longer to heat up than you think, and sausages, which always take
less. Worked on ELTEC tutorial.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">WED march 28</hi></p>
<p>A day of washing machine business. In the morning cheerful young man arrives
to take away old machine and install new one. Much clucking and tutting to see
that I am disposing of a genuine Miele museum piece like what they don’t make
them any more. New machine is finally wheeled into place and appears to work. In
the afternoon M Leffort came and took away the dryer for examination. He also
managed to impress on me what a shame it was I had bought a Hotpoint washing
machine. Dammit all, at least it works.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">TUE march 27</hi></p>
<p>By TAD to Gueret Gare. The idea was to take the E bus to E Leclerc, but when
it came it looked like an F bus so we missed it. So we walked, which really
wasn’t far, expecially if you stop for coffee on the way to avoid getting
entirely soaked. At Mr Leclerc’s emporium we purchased a top loading Hotpoint
washing machine on special offer (199 euro) which the man agreed to deliver it
for free, the next day, by the Lord. Eleclerc is a cavern of consumerist joys,
though virtually nobody is actually working or shopping. We checked out the
bookshop until it was time for lunch, which meant finding our way out of there
and down the hill to the Campanile restaurant, attaced to the motel by the
motorway. This bit of Gueret is not intended for pedestrians. I had the 3 course
buffet, L had the two course; both of us got stuffed, and then staggered back up
the hill, L to go grocery shopping., and I to go shoe shopping. Neither totally
successful nor entirely unsuccessful in either case. M Leffort phones and we
make a date for tomorrow, so he can give his view on the defunct dryer. The Tad
arrives eventually and takes us home for a well deserved snooze.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">MON march 26</hi></p>
<p>Walk squelchily into Bussiere, for lunch at Benoit’s. Fish and chips for me,
daube flamande for L, which turns out to be rather nice, and consoling on a wet
day. Johan appears just as we are setting off for the walk back, and gives us a
ride home. He then explains that they don’t do electro menager, and I need to
talk to Alain Leffort in St Vaury about my dead washing machine, which I duly
do. He doesn’t answer of course, because it’s Monday. No matter. We have a plan
to go to Gueret and buy a new one. Continue to roast selves in front of
fire.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">SUN march 25</hi></p>
<p> Beautiful spring sunshine to console us for the dampness within doors. I lug
the sodden carpet into the garden and light the stove again. Richard turns up,
inspects the damage, explains the error of my ways to me, fixes up a temporary
solution so that we can turn the water on again, disappears to get a spare part
from some other job while we have lunch. Later on we realise that the washing
machine is also kaput : makes sad clunking noises when it should be spinning.
And won’t open. Phone Johan again to ask for help.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">SAT march 24</hi></p>
<p>Up early to get the 0845 to get the 1130 eurostar … plenty of time to cross
Paris and pick up a few groceries at Monop before catching the 1640 train to La
Souterraine. Which is on time, and crowded only at our end, as I discover when
going in search of the buffet ambulant. And when we arrive, here is Lisa come to
drive us home in time. The familiar pattern all going well, till we actually
arrive, and I open the front door to hear the sound of running water. A pipe in
the bathroom has burst, and we have a small flood to contend with. Turning off
the mains down the hole is evidently still necessary: Lisa helps me do it, waits
patiently while we contend with the forces of dark panic, leave a message for
Jonathan (he’s away this weekend), she will contact Richard to see if he can
help, then drives us to Benoit’s to get some supper and consolation. And so to
the Tilleule, where we are in time for consolatory dinner (burgers and beer) and
Corinne kindly gives us a lift home. Into our chilly bed, thinking of adventures
ahead.</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
