<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/mugshots-c4808fd5e442-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Mugshots</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/mugshots-c4808fd5e442 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head>Mugshots</head>
<p> Yesterday I rushed off to London having paid an outrageous fee in order to
get myself a new proper European maroon passport in a hurry before the old one
expired. Having done so, I fell into a reverie concerning the mugshots that have
accompanied me through the decades. The images they provide, while standing up
to the scrutiny of suspicious US (inter alia) immigration officers and — more
recently — unreliable automated systems, seem far removed from my sense of self,
so inevitably I will blog about them.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*0eQ74NWZLH4ZBUyG3_cGpg.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Passport valid from 1965–1975</head>
</figure>
<p> This photo was taken outside Sea Mills Library in Bristol, which was my
first place of work, by my friend Chris’s dad, and shows my first beard, not to
mention a Beatle haircut. The passport must have been obtained for trips to
France. In those days the Exchange Control Act (1957) apparently required your
bank to record foreign currency transactions in your passport and so this one
shows that I took out £35 of foreign currency at the end of July 1965, £20 in
June 1968, £15 in 1971, and an astonishing £250 in 1973. The pound survived. The
passport also has many exotic stamps in it recording my Temporary Employment
Permit for Malawi, Transit Visas for Kenya and Mozambique and, on 24 Dec 1973,
the addition of a child called Belinda Daphne. We had to extract the British
High Commissioner from a good game of golf to get that one, and he was Not
Amused.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*z4QEaZv9penf79fKjoM50g.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Passport valid 1977–1978</head>
</figure>
<p> Back in the day you could get a so-called British Visitor’s Passport, which
was only valid for a year but was a lot cheaper than the real deal. And you
could also get a shared passport which included your partner and children. And
they seem to have been a lot less fussy about what was an acceptable mugshot in
those happy times too. (I liked the photo of Lilette so much, I reused it on my
next proper passport). We must have used this passport for family expeditions to
Italy and France, though there are no stamps in it to prove the point.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*NeyvDRgPB2f9JAL_fljhog.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Passport valid 1979 — 1989</head>
</figure>
<p> This passport shows my profession as “computer programmer” and Lilette’s as
“housewife”. It also has a stamp confirming that “The holder is a British
citizen under the provisions of the British Nationality Act 1981”. Which was
just as well since I started to do a lot of globe trotting with this passport:
there are traces of visits to the US, Canada, Japan, Zimbabwe and Denmark. Plus
a US Visa valid for “indefinitely” many return visits in 1979, at least until it
was revoked (“cancelled without prejudice”) some time later. And of course, the
addition of Elizabeth in 1986.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*BwQOsA8YUs8Z2mV3oMy_8w.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Passport valid 1989–1999</head>
</figure>
<p> During the tenure of this passport, my brow is clearly getting more
Shakespearian by the moment, and the globe trotting is also approaching
theatrical proportions. There are stamps from Israel, Canada, Norway, Japan,
Korea, Poland, and (many times over) the US. In those days, US Immigration would
staple a little card into your passport on arrival, and rip it out again on
departure, usually leaving the staple behind and tearing the page in the
process. Fortunately this was before the days of hyper-sensitive metal detectors
at airports. At the end of 1998 this one was cancelled anyway in favour of a
new-fangled burgundy-hued biometric passport.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*zy3qjMjrMerSU0rf5TtPvQ.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Passport valid 1998–2008</head>
</figure>
<p>My first proper European passport, which says “European Union” on its first
page in 11 languages. The biometric overlay has played havoc with the visibility
of the photo to the human eye, but that increasingly matters less than its
recognizability by other devices. A fine crop of foreign stamps in this
passport: apparently, with this face I managed to get into (and out of) Canada,
India, Bulgaria, Mauritius, the US, Japan, Korea, Serbia, Korea, Slovenia,
Australia, Taiwan, and the Czech Republic.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*ynZSrQtf7IuCvpD34cEbwQ.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Passport valid 2008–2018</head>
</figure>
<p>And this is the mugshot from my second European passport, which I replaced
yesterday. Again, my ageing features are somewhat obscured by digital
biometrical magic, though this was getting increasingly unreliable as far as the
machines controlling the gates at St Pancras were concerned. This passport
features some rather tasteful pictures of birds and a few immigration stamps
(US, Mauritius, Taiwan, Croatia and Russia), to say nothing of a proper Russian
visa, which I had to queue up in the rain outside the embassy to get. But it was
mostly used to take advantage of the wonderful freedom of movement within the
European Union, while it lasts. How many times has it been scowled out by a man
in a box labelled “Non-Schengen area” before waving me graciously through? How
many times has it been scanned and my details recorded in some scary database? I
have no idea: and what a good thing that is. I just know I shall miss it when I
can’t join the queue with the nice blue flag and all those stars.</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
