<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/in-which-we-go-to-the-seaside-or-what-i-did-in-my-holidays-cf530bc0605a-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>In which we go to the seaside. Or, What I Did In My Holidays</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/in-which-we-go-to-the-seaside-or-what-i-did-in-my-holidays-cf530bc0605a and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head>In which we go to the seaside. Or, What I Did In My Holidays</head>
<p>In August, all right-minded French citizens head for the coast, usually all
at the same time. We decided this year to award ourselves a small holiday and do
likewise.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*P88sqsCad7pMEtP-e0rPRQ.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>
</figure>
<p> Now, if you look at this map you can see that the easiest way to get from
Gueret (our nearest railway station) to the sea would be to go to Limoges and
then proceed in a straightish line due west, via Angouleme, to Royan, the
renowned Atlantic bathing place which the RAF flattened in 1945 (allegedly it
was all a terrible mistake), but which has since been reconstructed as a
splendid holiday resort, and is warmly recommended by our local grocer Jean-Luc.
However, as is well known, the SNCF have a distinct aversion for doing anything
as simple as going from right to left (or indeed left to right), so this trip
was not as straightforward as it should have been: in particular (despite the
existence of the line shown above) there is no train from Limoges to Angouleme
which does not grind to a premature halt at a station in the middle of nowhere
called Saillat-Chassenon: I hypothesize that this is because said halt is the
last one in the Haute Vienne, so presumably if the train were to continue it
would need to be co-financed by the neighbouring department of Poitou-Charentes.
There does appear to be an intermittent bus service onwards to Angouleme, but I
couldn’t find anyone willing to sell me a through ticket using it.</p>
<p> Consequently, we had to make a detour of many kilometres via Poitiers. Never
mind: to travel hopefully etc. etc. Out itinerary was as follows:</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Ia4bNHNRxRYDzz6fwLk54w.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>
</figure>
<p> All the trains were on time and mostly uncrowded and the sun shone
encouragingly all day long. I got a bit discombobulated by misunderstanding
instructions at Poitiers as to where we should board the TGV as it flashed by,
but otherwise a journey entirely without incident. The last stretch of the
journey, from Saintes to Royan, was notable for the fact that all the <hi
rend="italic">bien pensant</hi> and serious minded holiday makers got off the
train at Saintes to head for its wooded coves and beaches and special campsites,
leaving only day trippers, the poor, and incorrigibly vulgar tourists like
ourselves to trundle on to the seaside splendours of Royan.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*IWZos73t1MUGPy6mQqVu_g.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>I had booked us into a fancy hotel at a location very convenient for the
ferry (see later) but not at all for the train station; consequently we had to
walk a while, along the obligatory grand boulevard connecting the station to the
town centre, across the park, a quick view of the sea, and this magnificent
violin. Also, in the excitement of leaving home, L had forgotten to change out
of her golden slippers, and was thus ill equipped for sensible walking, a
problem to be resolved tomorrow when the shops are open. And so to the Hotel
Beau Rivage, where we have what is described as a <hi rend="italic">chambre
fantastique</hi> i.e. a corner room on the first floor, with a balcony around
two sides of it, looking out over the beach, and (less charmingly) the road.
There is an electric fan, which is good, though getting it to work is not the
work of an instant. By now, it’s also peak dining time in Royan, so we work our
way along the sea front from one over-crowded restaurant serving marine produce
to another, until finally finding a table for two <hi rend="italic">sans
reservation</hi> inside the misleadingly named “L’instant” where we eat
undistinguished chips, accompanied (in my case) by an undistinguished steak, and
(in L’s) by a plate of <hi rend="italic">moules gratinées,</hi> i.e. accompanied
by a green garlicky sauce called <hi rend="italic">beurre d’escargot</hi>,
though it was mercifully snail-free. It’s been a long day.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*D9Fi6YKuFAaZtJZCkgt0Cg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> Next day is bright and sunny and we are up in time to inspect all the shoe
shops on Royan’s main drag, of which there are not a few. By 11 am, L has found
a really rather snazzy pair of snakeskin shoes, so that walking is no longer a
torment.</p>
<p>Much heartened we head for the market, which is everything a French
provincial market should be: full of fresh fruit, fresh veg, umpteen cheeses,
and a gazillion kinds of fish.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*m_Eu_lqc_qWfRj1xAH2MQw.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*RO8WrgKWJxM_73FRbwLKBQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>oh look, she sells sea shells and  piments à volonté</head>
</figure>
<p> There’s a chilli-vendor, a seller of antique macaroons, disreputable looking
hippies selling organic produce, two bars, and … what is this? an interesting
looking little restaurant with an acceptable menu. Hoorah! Replete by two pm, we
waddle back to the hotel for a small siesta, as it is much too hot to consider
anything doing anything else.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*4uUOJMDfKpbfSyPiwDzzuw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*TqO7rJmqzYi0s6XqREMvcw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*x5y0I9ieBV4LimRk60ttjA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>antique fishing equipment; well stocked beach; splendid
seaside villa</head>
</figure>
<p> For our afternoon constitutional we head out along the cliff top walk which
winds around the coast west from Royan, taking in splendid sea views and equally
splendid seaside villas to view them from. We admire antique fishing equipment,
and enjoy pleasant coastal breezes. There is some shade, and not much traffic.
We survey from on high a total of three beaches, each of them now covered with
people (this is peak bathing time) before finally deciding it’s time for a cool
beer in the next village along what I now learn is officially known as the <hi
rend="italic">Cote de Beauté</hi>, which village rejoices not only in the name
of Saint Palais sur Mer, but also in a bus stop. And in the evening we spend a
lot of energy trying to find a restaurant which will serve rice (frites, pizza,
pasta, and even paella of a sort are all on offer, but no rice), until
eventually we stumble upon Royan’s only Indian restaurant and gorge ourselves on
rice and curry. And so to bed.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*cLUMkVyTG2971YErhkpppQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Well-manicured beach. Ferry already arriving.</head>
</figure>
<p> Next morning, outside our window a row of cones has materialised and a
tailback of traffic is crawling along towards the ferry embarkation point we
will be taking tomorrow. It’s Saturday and just everyone wants to get out of
town, apparently. We walk along the sea front, past the recently manicured
beach, to check out the ferry, and then proceed round yet another seafront
shopping area, this one overlooking an actual harbour with cute yachts in it,
before finally arriving at the business end of the celebrated and justly named
Grande Conche, which is an immense and well maintained expanse of sand
stretching for some 3 km south. It’s also (we realise after a while) devoid of
cliffs, and largely devoid of shade, which makes the walk less and less pleasant
as the sun rises in the sky. We stagger into the first watering hole we can for
a drink, and then take the bus back into town, which is largely deserted. After
last night’s rice fest, we’re not very hungry, but I can just about manage a <hi
rend="italic">salade composée</hi> sitting on the terrace of <hi rend="italic"
>Le forum</hi> before staggering back to the hotel for a very necessary
siesta.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*exXjjikmP16HrCL8tjpAtQ.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>At bathing time we finally manage to do the right thing. This means paying
for a nice umbrella and two loungers on the gradually filling-up beach across
the road. L has a specially bought swimming costume and proceeds to try it out,
even the water looks a little murky. The ferry boat trundles majestically to and
fro in the background and I am content to toast myself in the sun for the rest
of the day. Ater which, since it’s our last evening in Royan, we proceed to
Nona’s restaurant for genuine sicilian pizze, which turn out to be really rather
pleasant.</p>
<p>In the morning we pay up for the hotel, and move on out. The cones are gone,
but there’s still a queue of vehicles and bikes for the ferry. As pedestrians we
get to wait for the ferry in a nice shady spot under some trees, and also to
climb onto it first. Hoorah! And off it sails: the crossing takes about 20
minutes, as advertised, and is entirely uneventful : no pirates, no whales, no
dolphins. Lots of happy families and flocks of cyclists heading for a day’s
excursion around the sand dunes of Le Verdon or maybe they’re aiming for the
nudist beach. My goal is of course the little known railway station of Pointe de
Garde, which Google and the SNCF both assure me exists even though it’s not
entirely clear where, possibly because trains run there only every other hour
and for two months of the year. It takes all of ten minutes to locate it,
conveniently round the corner from a couple of restaurants, one of which will
deign to serve us coffee. Which is good, as we have an hour to kill till the
next train. We can sit in the shade, and watch the queue of traffic now fitfully
moving onto the ferry we have just disembarked from.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*VaZ8qq1WSZRJs15tenEOIA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Ui9YMnOxsjeoDGxufngFgQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head> End of the line at Pointe de Garde</head>
</figure>
<p> And by jingo here is our train! The 1148 departure for Bordeaux arrives
promptly at around 1130, disgorges its one or two passengers and sits panting
for a while before setting off again, this time with us on and a couple more
punters on board. This tranquillity does not last, however: the train starts
filling up at Le Verdon, and even more so at Soullac sur mer, where an entire
<hi rend="italic">colonie de vacance</hi> or similar piles in, to be joined by
another massive influx of young persons at Lesparre. They don’t seem to mind
having to lie on the floor, and no-one cares to check their tickets, which is
probably just as well. The scenery changes gradually from pine forest to
vineyard country, for this is the Medoc, and soon all you can see from the
windows is fields and fields of vines. After a while I see that that the
stations we pass through are named for celebrated wines (Margaux, Pauillac…) and
yes, just over there that is your actual Chateau Lafite Rothschild… and so
eventually into Bordeaux, where we are planning to return to civilisation.</p>
<p>I have booked us into a hotel within spitting distance of the Gare St Jean,
though I am not sure why since it is not the most salubrious of districts and we
have plenty of time between trains (we’re booked on the TGV to Paris tomorrow
afternoon, since our home-bound Eurostar was booked on the assumption we’d be
starting from La Souterraine, long before the planning of this little escapade).
Never mind, it’s too hot to consider anywhere more than five minutes walk away
for lunch. Fortunately this is not hard to find: and the <hi rend="italic">plat
de jour</hi> at Le Terminus is a very acceptable <hi rend="italic">joue de porc
confite</hi>. Do we do anything except eat on holiday? Well, maybe a bit.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*vnUWw2SLNabRsfWe-zeWqQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Mint tea. It’s well peng on a hot day.</head>
</figure>
<p> For example, I went for an explore up the hill away from the station after
lunch, first to the cathedral, and then to the basilique saint michel. I vaguely
recall the nice narrow streets around the former from my last visit here: at the
moment everything is shut of course, but the streets are still pleasant: I
really must come here more often and get to know this city properly. And by the
time I get to the basilica, place Meynard is humming with people sitting around
drinking delicious iced mint tea.</p>
<p>I entice L out for a short stroll in the evening, by when the bars and shops
in the narrow streets around the cathedral are starting to open up: we decide to
patronize a tiny Brazilian bar for tasty tapas and caiporinhas. City life, eh
what.</p>
<p>Next morning, it’s back to place Meynard, where a morning market is in full
swing. I complain that, like me, all my shirts are now tired and sweaty but
no-one seems to be selling nice cool shirts for men, walk round a corner and
discover hundreds of them: I buy one and shut up. A very pleasant morning. Back
down the hill to the station where we have to collect our bags, and lunch for
the last time, this time at Le Potager, whose menu made no impression on me at
all. We are on time for the TGV to Paris, which is 40 minutes late on arrival,
but since our Eurostar is 30 minutes late leaving, we have a net profit
time-wise, which we spend glugging cocktails in the eurostar lounge. The
holidays are over, and this seems like an entirely correct parting gesture.</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
