<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/remembering-guy-8243a7872690-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Remembering Guy</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/remembering-guy-8243a7872690 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head>Remembering Guy</head>

<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*422-mmdEAt4GQiZ9oGdW0Q.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Federico sent me this photo of Guy. I don’t know where or when exactly it
was taken, but it’s nice to think that it captures an essential part of his
life, waiting for lunch in the restaurant car of a central European train
somewhere, perhaps en route to see some more Brueghels</head>
</figure>

<p>My friend Guy Aston died on 31 October this year in hospital in Modena, after
a year or more of obstinately refusing to give in to cancer and other ills. He
was cared for in his last days by a small network of close long-term friends,
who also organized a special memorial event for him on Dec 8th in Vergato, which
I attended along with maybe sixty other people. There were photos of Guy’s life
and speeches, and (for me) the unexpected pleasure of meeting again some people
I had not seen for many years and also meeting some that I had never met before;
but who all had in common their love for Guy. There were former students and
colleagues from Forli and Modena, whose careers he had helped advance; there
were neighbours and friends from Vergato with whom he shared his long life in
Italy. It was a surprisingly joyful occasion and blessed by wintry sunshine.</p>
<p>There were three pre-prepared speeches, which you can read in English or
Italian by clicking the links below :</p>
<list type="unordered">

<item>
<ref target="http://lb42.github.io/guyMemorial/Talks/michelaNerio.pdf">Michela
and Nerio</ref>, Guy’s neighbours in Liserna, set the scene</item>

<item>I spoke <ref
target="https://lb42.github.io/guyMemorial/Talks/louBurnard.pdf">about our long
friendship</ref></item>

<item>
<ref target="https://lb42.github.io/guyMemorial/Talks/pierPaola.pdf">Pier Paola
Calori</ref> spoke about his life in Liserna</item>
</list>
<p>At the invitation of the organisers, many other people also spoke, in
particular fellow researchers and teachers, providing anecdotes and
reminiscences about his influence on them, and his character. These remarks were
not recorded, but I am of course happy to add other people’s memories to this
site as they become available.</p>
<p>I have made and annotated <ref
target="https://photos.app.goo.gl/Q8GZWgboFRDZb6oFA">a small sample of the many
photos I have of Guy</ref>; a representative sample of moments where our lives
intersected. Please click the link above to see them!</p>
<p> Finally, it is good to record that on December 23, 2018, Guy’s ashes were
scattered (as he had requested) on the hillside in Liserna which had been his
true home for so long.</p>
<p>Lou Burnard</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
