<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/from-one-garden-to-the-other-in-24-hours-f908b2cf5d0-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>From one garden to the other (in 24 hours)</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<head>From one garden to the other (in 24 hours)</head>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*C6wbVhtEq4Z_C2npeLh6yA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>An Oxford back garden</head>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">10 May</hi> and it’s time to leave 111 Victoria Road for my
other garden, not tended since March, and therefore in dire need of attention.
So I lock up the house carefully and set off on the dot of 1430. I have my
minimalist backpack, packed with all that is needful in the way of tickets and
passport and such like; I am wearing a nice khaki jacket which has languished
too long in the cupboard and some new brown shoes from Gueret, in which I am
less confident, but they deserve a chance… The sun shines benevolently on
Victoria Road as I saunter to the bus stop, and within five minutes up rolls
that comparative rarity, a 700 bus.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*ZQy6nTkwjW1Oqn_Ts6c4iA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>They only run every hour</head>
</figure>
<p>I don’t appreciate the journey as I am busy trying to book a bus for the
final stage of this journey and the <hi rend="italic">Service Mobilité du Grand
Guere</hi>t (aka le TAD) for some reason is not answering its phone. And goes on
not answering when I get to Oxford Parkway 10 minutes later, when I board the
1502 departure to Oxford, and indeed at each subsequent stop for the rest of the
day, as I keep hopefully trying at every opportunity.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*GW3IIyehctpQlNgIX-BfiQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Today I am getting on where I usually get off</head>
</figure>
<p> Mysterious, and not a little frustrating, since my planned itinerary has me
arriving at Gueret station at 1735 tomorrow, which is just right for the last
TAD of the day, but completely useless in every other respect. Have I got the
wrong phone number? Are they on strike? This is the sort of thing that spoils an
otherwise perfect journey, sidling around North Oxford by train for a change
instead of lurching down the Banbury Road by bus. And here is my 1530 cross
country train to Southampton Airport Parkway, on time and not too crowded, and I
sit on it for an hour getting more and more annoyed by the absence of response
from Gueret, instead of enjoying the cross country experience.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*5lJoQoQRh-XHbM9CEJ_iqA.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Count ‘em</head>
</figure>
<p>At the airport, which is only 99 steps from the train station as a notice
helpfully reminds me, I saunter through security, with plenty of time to go and
get a coffee upstairs, before buying a vegan sandwich and a bilious green drink
to eat on the plane. The man in the shop points out that I could get this “meal
deal” for 2 pounds less if I add a packet of crisps, so I ask him to get me a
packet of crisps, and then give it to him since I hate crisps. I ponder this
retail marketing madness and then Go To My Gate (i.e. cross the floor to a
different chair). There are only a dozen or so people waiting for this flight,
but we still have to be processed through the door onto a bus. Which cannot move
until all the people walking in front of it from some other flight have safely
crossed. And so into the little sardine tin in the sky, with all the other
sardines. Half the seats on the plane are empty, so I move to one of the more
remote ones as soon as the door is shut and do some not too stressful markup of
a Swiss French 19th century novel to pass the time. Bonjour Limoges Bellegard!
All is much as it was the last time I saw it but this time I am going to explore
its hinterland. For Mr Google assures me that across the car park, there is a
bijou hotel, the Citotel Alizes, a one storey building of modest dimensions,
where one can get a bed for the night though not much else.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*Bi4Nd7EFiDiZkYS4R9_vbQ.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Citotel Alizes in the cold hard light of morning</head>
</figure>
<p>I think it is owned by the same company as the airport’s posh restaurant. No
matter: the nice lady at reception provides me with all I require for the
moment, namely viz a bottle of beer, and the loan of a phone charger (what? Did
I really leave my phone charger behind in Oxford? Yes, dear reader, I did.
Fortunately my destination is replete with such things). Having given up on the
TAD for tomorrow, plan B is to hunt down an outrageously expensive taxi, rather
than exploit Lisa’s motor, since she isn’t available anyway. And so to bed.</p>
<p>Next morning, the TAD answers its phone and gives me the simple and obvious
explanation for yesterday’s debacle: it was a <hi rend="italic">jour férié</hi>,
a public holiday, as any (French) fool would know, so naturally there was no one
there. And no, out of the question of course to arrange a tad for today today;
it has to be for tomorrow. So I arrange one for tomorrow, thinking at least I
will get some tomato plants in Gueret market. And checking today’s trains, I
discover that the one I was planning to take in order to connect with the TAD
has been cancelled anyway. A reason to be cheerful, and even more so to accept
Lisa’s kind offer of a lift with some unknown friend of hers, assuming I can get
to Gueret a bit earlier. Which I certainly can, for I have a cunning plan. All
this before a rather dull French breakfast, after which I pay the bill, and set
off for the first part of the cunning plan. Mr Google says it can be done, and
the Limoge bus company agrees. There is a bus stop just outside the hotel, but
buses stop there only 3 times a day, all inconvenient. Much more interestingly,
there is another bus stop down the road some 800 metres away, where buses also
stop 4 or 5 times a day, but at more useful times.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*fVScH6sk5dsVhQsNxQB5VA.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Here’s where Ave de l’Aeroport gets sneaky</head>
</figure>
<p>So off I plod, down Avenue de l’Aeroport, which is surprised to see a
pedestrian but makes room for me all the same, even providing a helpful crossing
point when the road hits one of the many roundabouts which France decrees must
accompany every major intersection. This all goes remarkably smoothly: also it’s
still a lovely sunny day, which is good, as I arrive at the bus stop in question
a good 20 minutes too early. And lo, exactly on time at 1046, the promised EX1
bus hoves into view and picks me up.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*ZqvQ5GLg8-ZQmaBekYhZww.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Patience is rewarded</head>
</figure>
<p>It is a luxurious coach with one other passenger on it, and it whisks me away
to the centre of Limoges for a mere 1 euro 50 (i.e. approx 24 euros less than a
taxi). I stroll through Limoges feeling very smug, and with time in hand to do
my chores. These include buying some toothpaste, getting in food for the next
few days, but firstly sorting out my Carte Senior at the magnificent Gare de
Limoges Benedictines.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*2gWnreCDcu8OOazPeswe1w.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>What is it about this photo which got so many likes on Instagram?</head>
</figure>
<p> Inside, I have to queue up for what feels like forever, but is only about 10
minutes before I can get someone to help resolve the “<hi rend="italic"
>coquille</hi>” somewhere in my <hi rend="italic">dossier</hi> on the SNCF
computer. The unflappable cheminot regulates the affair <hi rend="italic">sans
problème</hi> and sells me a ticket to Gueret as well. And then I walk round the
corner to the Grand Frais supermarket to buy some provisions: sadly they have
run out of milk, and don’t sell bread at all, which I should have remembered.
But they do sell nice fresh vegetables. And so back to the architectural joys of
Limoges station in good time for my train, and thinking about lunch. But what
fresh torture is this?</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*Db0eu8zKgJ0SyrROFtORiQ.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>The post modern station buffet is no more</head>
</figure>
<p> Alas, the station buffet has closed down seemingly forever; somewhat
chastened I have no choice but to buy a horrible industrial sandwich from the
station mewsagent and eat it sitting outside in the sunshine. The 1311 TER to
Gueret is at the platform already, and ready to trundle along via Bonnat, Saint
Sulpice Le Laurier (where it changes direction), Vielleville, Montaigut etc as
usual, though this time with a minor excitement en route. They are renewing the
<hi rend="italic">caténaire</hi>, I learned from the guard, and people were
still on the line, so we had to stop. Being at the front I witnessed the driver
descending from the train to shout at a trackside phone, then returning to get
an instruction manual or page of secret codes from his bag in the cab, then
going back to shout at it some more before proceeding gingerly through a red
light.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*O5KJ4YZ50_ZKetGNALtBzw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> Anyway, we arrived in Gueret on time, and here is Lisa and her new friend
Debbie, and Debbie’s rather splendid red Rover to greet me and drive me home in
style, in return for a cup of tea and some petrol money. Debbie comes from the
West Country, as is evident in her speech, and has just bought a house down the
road in Monneger, where she spent the winter. I also learn that she is or was a
professional musician, (double bass, but none of that jazz nonsense; we are
talking proper orchestra here) and find myself feeling unusually well disposed
to her amiable doggy.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*w4T3UZ7wgNgMyLbInEw-Jw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Plenty of work to do in this garden</head>
</figure>
<p> And after they leave I determine that there is a clear need for urgent
attention to the jungle that the garden has become, but put it off till
tomorrow. It’s been a long journey : 24 hours exactly, bearing in mind <hi
rend="italic">le décalage horaire</hi>.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">Itinerary</hi></p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*YwemZ50QjtyoUSaA56d5TA.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Costs in time</head>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*yoOjTNbMboWyOKK5uQeQvA.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>

<head>Costs in money</head>
</figure>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
