<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/in-which-we-go-to-the-opera-83ca7ca013f7-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>In which we go to the Opera</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/in-which-we-go-to-the-opera-83ca7ca013f7 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>
<head>In which we go to the Opera</head>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*1vi6NzfYpsWAoUAu1MZXVg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> This picture summarizes more or less where we’d got to by the end of July,
after a month or so of La Vergne summer, replete with village festivities,
ranging from the Claude Francois look-alike concert, to the Potato Festival and
Village Hoe-down. The nice pink flowers were a birthday present from Deidre to
Lilette; I planted them out in a pot in which lettuces had failed to grow, and
they flourished much better, probably because they got watered more frequently.
The village cat is also flourishing if hot, as she is rumoured to be about to
give birth. We are not staying for that though: it is the last Monday in July,
and Shawn is coming in his smart new car to drive us to the airport. A first for
all of us, since we are going to try a new route back to Blighty: Ryanair to
Bristol. Getting from Bristol to Oxford looks a lot easier and quicker than from
either Gatwick or (god save the mark) Stansted, and the flight is much cheaper
too, even when you factor in an extra 7 euros for “Priority Boarding”, a
misnomer if ever there was one, since over half the passengers have opted for
it, so that they can block up the aisles with their massive suitcases as usual.
But no Ryanair carping on this occasion, beastly though the experience is: not
only did the flight leave on time, but it also arrived nearly half an hour
early. Outside the airport, it is sunny, and here is a bus which will take us to
Temple Meads station for a mere 7 quid each. I don’t recognise this bit of
Bristol: in all my years of living there I never ventured south of the harbour
into the wildness of Bedminster and the jungle beyond. But here we are at
Bristol TM, slightly frazzled by the ease of it all, and looking for a train.
Definitely easier than expected, we collapse into a comfy seat and watch the
stations on the Great Western tick by in an orderly fashion, ten to 15 minutes
apart: Bath, Chippenham, Swindon, and Didcot, where we have to wait for a train
to Oxford. I have fallen into a time warp, and am replaying my student
travelling days. As if to stress the point, some of our fellow passengers are
youthful, extravagantly clothed, and burdened with camping equipment (though
nothing like as many as we encounter a couple of days later, when we next board
a GWR train, this time bound for Moreton in Marsh); and so, finally, back to
Victoria Road. Total journey time door to door 8 hours, total cost (per person)
£87 made up as follows: Taxi (Shawn) : €50 ; Flights : €74.36 ; Bristol Bus:
£14; BRI-OXF train: £26 , ; Taxi (Oxf) : £10.</p>
<p>Back in Oxford we spent a couple of days doing necessary business like
defrosting and restocking the fridge, prodding the estate agent who has still
failed to sell our house, saying hello to the neighbours, etc. But mostly I
focussed on organizing our expedition into the Northern Cotswolds to visit the
Longborough Opera: which implied assorted phone calls concerning accomodation
and other arrangements made back in April when we had hoped to be visiting <hi
rend="italic">à quatre</hi>. I also took delivery of a rather flaky but
apparently functional SPY CAMERA and tested same, as far as possible without
actually visiting the opera house. And made a large salade nicoise and an
impromptu picnic hamper. And so, in an advanced state of preparation, through
the sunshine by bus to Oxford station again in good time for the 1523 Great
Western Trains Service to Moreton in Marsh. Which is sorely delayed, as is every
other train heading north from Oxford this afternoon, by signalling failures,
trespassers on the line, break downs, wrong kind of sun, who knows. There are
two trains on platform three, neither of them moving anywhere, and the one we
want has just left Reading. Ah well, this is England. In France there wouldn’t
be any trains anywhere until the wee hours of tomorrow morning anyway, so we are
resigned. After half an hour or so, one of the trains heads off mysteriously in
the wrong direction, but the other one isn’t budging. And then we are invited to
trot over to the opposite platform to join ours, which has just arrived, hoorah,
along with several hundred tent-carrying, backpack-sporting, very clean young
persons presumably en route to some kind of tribal gathering. Which when the
train arrives, somehow manage to squeeze into it, as do we. At least it is air
conditioned, even if we have to stand all the way to Charlbury, where the young
persons and their baggage decant themselves en masse, though rather slowly,
proceeding I assume on foot to their gathering, which we learn from a patient
commuter is an annual event: the Wilderness festival. I am too preoccupied with
trying to contact my taxi lady to rail over much against the follies of youth or
the speciousness of a wilderness festival for weekend drop outs, which is
probably just as well. For here we are at Moreton in Marsh, 30 minutes late i.e.
with 20 minutes to go before curtain up, where one taxi driver (having
ascertained that I am indeed “Louis from France”) assures me that mine will be
along shortly. As indeed she is, bless her. And so through the scenic Northern
Cotswold lanes at top speed to the bosky retreat within which lurks the
Longborough Festival Opera. Spy camera switched on, we duck around the side of
the building to find the Blue Door and our seats in the pit. Hoorah!</p>
<p>The opera house (I later learn) is actually a converted barn. Inside,
however, it looks just like a medium sized opera house should, with comfy
chairs, a balcony, and an orchestra pit currently full of theorbos and similar.
There are surtitles displayed on a TV monitor, and there is a slightly too tall
person sitting directly in front of me, or to be more exact directly in front of
my spy camera, as I later discover. No matter, the performance begins with a
disputation between Fate and Virtue, settled once for all by Love, not to
mention a writhing mass of humanity in a heap on the floor. Yes, this is
Monteverdi’s celebrated <hi rend="italic">L’incoronazione di Poppea</hi>. Fate
Virtue, and Love are young persons with rather smaller backpacks than those on
the train, and are also equipped with little spotlights. Occasionally they write
a graffito on the back wall., and dance around making chorus-style commentary on
the action. But mostly they sing, with impressive verve, conviction, and
technical mastery. As indeed does everyone. Poppea, a majestic and rather sultry
beauty, writhes convincingly on the floor for a bit; Nerone turns out to be a
female contralto, which gives some of the duets an added <hi rend="italic"
>frisson</hi>. The much put-upon Ottone is a counter tenor and rather large,
especially by comparison with his equally put-upon girlfriend Drusilla, which
provokes the only laugh of the whole performance (when he offers to disguise
himself in her clothes). But this show is not being played for laughs: it’s an
opera already headquartered in Bizarroville, Planet Weird, so all the players
are focussed entirely on their vocal skills and larger than life
characterisation, without worrying too much about plausibility or morality.
Which is just as well, since this story is neither moral nor plausible: except
perhaps that the bad guys come out on top. The nearest thing to a good guy is
Seneca, a solemn bass who is ordered to kill himself, with much ensuing hilarity
when he does; Nerone’s matronly and abused wife suffers a fate worse than death
(banishment) as a penalty for objecting to her husband’s canoodling with Poppea;
her incompetent instrument Ottone is threatened with the same fate but then
magnanimously forgiven as a reward for not letting his girlfriend carry the can…
But the singing, once you have adjusted your ear to the Monteverdian sound
world, is entrancing, and we are duly entranced.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*NlsvadaY6ZZC69y9oMUWww.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>The Opera House itself, Mozart, Wagner, and Verdi presiding.</head>
</figure>
<p> Opera is of course something only those of a certain age and class have much
time for these days, whatever they tell you. And the audience, which we inspect
during the ninety minute interval, is just what you might have expected: aged
couples, looking remarkably like us, though the men usually in better maintained
suits, and only a small sprinkling of young persons (the others are all gone to
the Wilderness, I surmise). During the interval, the audience spreads itself out
between four large tents, corresponding with the main divisions of English
society: one for the merely unspeakably rich, who have paid to be served with a
posh dinner; and a choice of three marquees for the rest: at the top the
“Benefactors” (minimum annual contribution £3000); next the “Patrons” (ditto,
£600); and then the “General” (10 quid a head).</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*4fjFbYuZtVwnXr2Y_WMzlg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> Thanks to Guy’s foresight, we have a place in the last of these, a small
table, with a minimalist flower on it, where we can sit down and eat our own
picnic.It’s right over there, on the other side of the car park, commanding
magnificent views over the Cotswolds, though not as magnificent as those to be
had from the other marquees, as we ascertain after disposing of the salad
nicoise and guacamole. But an atmosphere of general well heeled bonhomie
prevails as the dusk comes in and we find our way back to our seats for the
second half. And so, in due course, back to the station for an entirely
uneventful journey back to Summertown and what passes for reality
thereabouts.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*H-NI9fH5ROa9nZ_dCrpggQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>The view from the rich folks tent</head>
</figure>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
