<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>On the intelligent handling of free text retrieval</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard <lb/>Oxford University Computing Service </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>XML version for my archive</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from an email with header <code>From: VAX::LOU "Lou Burnard" 20-APR-1989
                  18:50:27.79 To: CBS%RL.MAIL::UICVM::U35395 </code></p>
            <p>Text published in <bibl><title>Informatics 10 : prospects for intelligent retrieval :
                     proceedings of a conference jointly sponsored by Aslib, the Aslib Informatics
                     Group and the Information Retrieval Specialist Group of the British Computer
                     Society, University of York, 21-23 March 1989 / edited by Kevin P.
                     Jones.</title>
                  <note>(title page says King's College Cambridge).</note><publisher>London :
                     Aslib, 1990</publisher>
                  <biblScope>viii, 351 p. : ill. ; 30 cm. </biblScope>
                  <idno type="isbn">0851422527 (pbk) </idno>
               </bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2014-10-06">Remembered to add revisionDesc</change>
         <change when="2014-08-06">Converted via word and oxyGen from old email</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1. The textual trinity</head>
            <p>Electronic texts challenge all three of the software paradigms that have evolved in
               response to the ways we usually process non-electronic texts. The human eye and brain
               switch unconsciously between seeing a text as a visual image, decoding it as a
               linguistic construct, and extrapolating a meaning structure with some relationship to
               (non-linguistic/extra- textual) events in the "real" world. Software is less flexible
               and tends, when processing an electronic text, to limit its operations to only one of
               these three levels.</p>
            <p> Word processing software concerns itself only with marks on an medium, ink on paper,
               dots on a screen: textual character sets, appearance and layout are consequently most
               often expressed in functional terms (use this type face, in that point size, indent
               so many mm here...). Even in the trend to descriptive markup the focus has so far
               been to tag features already marked in non-electronic texts: the purpose of the
               software being to produce more, and more visually pleasing, paper texts. </p>
            <p> A second software paradigm sees texts as composed of primarily linguistic
               constructs. Most present-day indexing and retrieval systems are even-handedly
               uninterested both in presentational variation and in the meaning structure which a
               text exists to convey. Texts are processed solely in terms of the lexical items they
               contain, their relationship to each other, and to other texts containing the same
               items. The identification and categorisation of lexical items in a text is a major
               concern of such systems, and by no means a trivial one; it also has some theoretical
               justification. To grossly simplify one influential school of linguistic theory: as
               there is no way of expressing meaning without recourse to words, so meaning itself is
               probably an emergent property of the way words are used, rather than an independent
               conceptual structure. Parsers have been built that recognise syntax on purely
               probabilistic principles, divorced from 'deep structure', or which employ a
               'systemic' grammar, derived solely from what is legal in the lexicon. The success of
               automatic document classification systems is further good empirical evidence for this
               hypothesis. </p>
            <p> By contrast, in the third software paradigm, texts are primarily vehicles for
               conveying a meaning, which can also be expressed in terms of higher order
               abstractions - a conceptual model. This model can then be represented by a database
               management system, of some kind. Software of this kind naturally ignores both
               presentational and linguistic features: equally naturally it is best suited to texts
               which assert fairly simple propositions like "The Endeavour arrived at London from
               Hamburg in 1558 with a cargo of train oil worth £12 for Otto Spinks". By creating a
               formal model of the real world (in which ships leave ports, carrying cargo belonging
               to people, all cargoes having names and values which are themselves categorised or
               analysable in some way), the database designer effectively defines a universe of
               discourse, in which a very large, but well defined, set of questions and answers can
               exist. He or she is, in a sense, an ideal reader of the text. </p>
            <p> This distinction (between the 2nd and 3rd paradigms) has an analogue also in the way
               we partition research and expertise: considering why `data processing' and `natural
               language processing' are regarded as distinct fields sheds much light on both as well
               as on philosophical attitudes to the function of meaning. One obvious consequence of
               the separation is that results from one field are rarely applied in the other, to
               their mutual detriment. The tools developed by computer science to represent and
               analyse complex data objects and processes are rarely applied to the equally complex
               analysis of sentence structure or argument in real discourse. The insights offered by
               natural language processing into the way human reasoning is performed and human
               concepts are organised are often ignored in constructing such tools. Even within
               computer science, a purely adventitious distinction between free-text indexing
               systems and other sorts of data processing systems has resulted in the creation of
               `information retrieval' as an academic sub- discipline in its own right. </p>
            <p> A similar divide, between `linguistics' and `literary studies', has had equally
               unfortunate results: practitioners of literary studies have had to re-invent a theory
               of how texts are processed by readers and writers independently of linguists who have
               been busily engaged in inventing such theories independently of any awareness of
               their application in the real world of textual communication. The linguistic model
               thus created is inevitably incomplete and reductionist, while the literary one is
               inconsistent and computationally naive. </p>
            <p> However there are hopeful signs of change in the way that disciplines, tools and
               techniques are increasingly converging: there is a creative flow of energy advancing
               on some of the hoarier problems of processing electronic text, the more creative
               because it comes from several directions, synergistically. Mediating the gap between
               word processing and database management systems a new understanding of the importance
               of descriptive mark up is emerging; while the theme of this conference straddles the
               gap between database and document retrieval system, between conceptual and linguistic
               models of what text is. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head> 2. Structuring a text</head>
            <p>Text is most unlike other data in the complexity of its structure: the phrase
               "unstructured text" is as close to an oxymoron as could be wished. In non electronic
               texts, we are familiar with structures defined in terms relating to each of the three
               levels defined above which function independently; we also have no difficulty in
               combining descriptions drawn from different domains. In a printed play, for example,
               we are aware of the pagination (level 1), the sentence or verse structure (level 2)
               and the dramatic structure implied by the alternation of speakers, the subjects of
               which they speak etc. (level 3). We can reasonably hope to contrast the syntactic
               structures employed by speakers on a given topic printed in one style with those
               printed in another. In a manuscript, we can equally wish to compare the vocabulary
               used by sections of a manuscript in one hand with those in another. </p>
            <p> There are those who argue, almost as a point of dogma, that electronic texts should
               be entirely innocent of structural indications or interpretation. This defeatist
               position seems to ignore important facts about the way people actually use texts,
               quite apart from undervaluing pragmatic considerations. Firstly any sort of storage
               or representation of a text necessarily imposes some kind of structure, whether at
               the gross level of files and bytes or the more advanced model of point to point
               addressing postulated by Nelson's Xanadu and the increasing number of distributed
               text architectures it has inspired. Secondly, in retrieval from texts, users
               invariably wish to specify (often independently) the scope or context of their query
               and of the sections of text to be returned by it: such queries are also frequently
               qualified by categorisation of some kind. In a bibliographic or other catalogue it is
               important to distinguish people's names from place names or topics (we do not want
               all books published in or about London when seeking for books by Jack London), and
               even to distinguish the roles of say author, illustrator or translator. Thirdly, in
               the creation of electronic texts, it is of immense value to distinguish elements
               which encode the matter of a text from those which encode its manner of presentation,
               wherever possible. A text in which headings or lists are explicitly flagged as
               headings or lists will be susceptible of many more uses than one in which the
               existence of such elements is simply implied by the use of an arbitrary (and
               polysemous) choice from the available typographic conventions for such things. Of
               course, there will be cases where both types of tagging are necessary, for example to
               answer such questions as `Which of the headings in this text are in italics?'. </p>
            <p> The kinds of texts to which present day software systems are best suited are those
               composed of discontinuous smaller texts, each with a set of attributes drawn from a
               common pool. Examples include the lists and catalogues that make up most original
               historical sources. Such things are easily decomposed into individual entries, each
               of which can be further decomposed into smaller components, the relationships between
               which will often be straightforwardly hierarchic. For example the port book entries
               in figure 1, where each entry concerns the arrival of a single ship, each ship
               carrying many cargoes, each cargo having a single owner and value, but many cargo-
               items, each cargo-item having at least a description, and optionally a quantity and
               units as well. In some cases, modelling the conceptual relationships between the
               various components of such an entry may be far more difficult than this simple
               example suggests. Figure 2, for example, is from a text in which each entry
               summarises a number of incidents in a judicial system, an understanding of which is
               essential before the roles associated with people's names or the judicial actions
               mentioned can be correctly interpreted. To assess the probability that `Richard
               Crouche' and `Richard Crowche' are references to the same person requires knowledge
               not only of 17th century orthography and phonology, but also of the exact nature of a
               `recognisance' </p>
            <p> The model of text which underlies such systems is of a collection of distinct text
               fragments, possibly ordered, each with identifiable and unambiguous subcomponents.
               Regrettably there are many types of texts which will not fit this model without some
               violence. As a transitional example, consider the kind of electronic text with which
               many of us first come into contact: the electronic mail message. This clearly has
               some identifiable and unambiguous subcomponents: its sender, perhaps the nodes
               through which it passed en route to its destination, its date and time at each, and
               its recipient. It is also conventional, but not obligatory, for a message to have an
               associated topic line in which a summary of the message can be inserted for the
               benefit of those e-mail systems which can use it, perhaps using a set of keywords
               known to both sender and recipient. The structure of the message itself however is
               not easily decomposable, except into a series of paragraphs or lines of 'free text',
               structured only by the exigencies of the communications system and the assumption of
               the recipient that it does in fact contain a meaning. Any electronic analysis of such
               messages must be done in linguistic terms, by indexing the whole text at the very
               least, before starting to look for higher level conceptual structures. </p>
            <p> Still more difficult to fit into the simple document structures described so far are
               the electronic versions of conventional texts which will (perhaps) one day replace
               books and offprints in the studies and libraries of the world. Representing the
               structure of a narrative text such as a play requires a consideration of many
               independent, yet interacting, hierarchies of description. As a simple example,
               consider the first scene of Hamlet, in which two sentries meet and discuss somewhat
               nervously the events of the previous night on watch in Elsinore. A textual scholar
               might wish to see a structure approximating as closely as possible to the original in
               order to tabulate and analyse the differences between the memorially reconstructed
               'bad quarto' text of 1603 and the edited text. Considerations of type fount and size,
               lineation, manuscript addition, even inking would all be involved. A scholar
               interested in the dramatic elements of the text would wish the text to be organised
               as a series of speeches and stage directions, and would wish (for example) to know
               that the speeches given to 'I' and '2' in the quarto are actually spoken by Barnardo
               and Francisco respectively. A scholar interested in the literary elements of the text
               would wish to know which parts of the text are prose and which verse. It is
               impossible to conceive of a single hierarchic structure which can cater for all these
               different viewpoints; and not easy to think of one which can cater for even those of
               one of my hypothetical scholars, particularly given the close interaction between the
               types of description involved. Plays may be divided into speeches, and speeches into
               lines, but verse lines may be both smaller than and larger than either, and it is a
               perfectly reasonable requirement to wish to select all speeches containing incomplete
               verse lines. </p>
            <p> A number of research projects have demonstrated the feasibility of representing such
               structures by a formal grammar, describing both the appearance of the text and its
               significance. Such a grammar can then be used to parse components of the text and tag
               them appropriately for complex retrieval or updating . A notably successful recent
               application of this approach has been the creation of the electronic version of the
               Oxford English Dictionary, undertaken at the University of Waterloo, which has
               permitted both the creation of a searchable electronic text and the automatic merging
               of the supplements with the main body of that monumental work , but few commercial
               products yet approach the sophistication of the tools developed for this purpose.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head> 3. Access to text</head>
            <p>In the absence of sophisticated grammars of this kind, which can guide the enquirer
               in terms of the innate structure of a text, how do we manage to search electronic
               texts at all? Fortunately, if we make a number of simplifying assumptions about
               natural language, the question "what is this text about?" can be answered quite
               simply for many of the types of electronic texts we wish to search. Document
               abstracts, story headlines, title pages etc. are all intended to convey information
               about the content, or at least the avowed topic, of the texts they identify;
               exceptions to this rule are as easy to create as `garden-path sentences', and perhaps
               equally relevant. For requirements such as literature searching - and wherever the
               matter is more important than its manner - keyword-based searching will generally
               offer excellent results. </p>
            <p> A number of techniques have been used to resolve the familiar problems of
               homography, ambiguity, polysemy etc. in natural language keyword-based searching
               systems. A thesaurus can be used to define a structure within which inter-term
               relationships such as generality, specificity, synonymy etc can be defined. A
               dictionary can be used to suggest alternative candidate terms related by significant
               overlaps in their defining vocabulary. A knowledge-based system can be used in which
               the rules implicit in the more traditional resources of dictionary and thesaurus are
               re-expressed in terms of predicate logic. Relevance feedback can be used to identify
               clusters of related terms independently of any formal semantic structure. Outlining
               techniques can be used to arrange texts into meaningful taxonomies derived from their
               keywords. All of these techniques, many of which have been discussed at this
               conference and in the literature are predicated on two assumptions: that the primary
               reason for wanting to search an electronic textbase is to recover texts which are
               'about' something, and moreover that whatever a text is 'about' can be summed up in a
               few dozen, or even a few hundred, keywords, either added by the author, or derived by
               some deterministic process from the text itself. Many in the humanities would
               question both of these assumptions. </p>
            <p> What (for example) is a novel `about'? Should it be keyworded to indicate its plot
               and characters? the literary tropes or allusions it contains? the themes or topoi
               identified by one or more schools of critics within it? the historical context within
               which it was first created or within which it has been regarded particularly highly
               (or poorly)? </p>
            <p> To cater for such questions, all that the conventional wisdom can offer is to extend
               the keywording principle to include the whole of the constituent tokens of the text
               itself. The focus of interest thus shifts from the `topic' of a text to its actual
               content. It is arguable that this approach introduces almost as many problems (by
               degrading precision) as it solves (by improving recall). Neither does this approach
               remove the need for both additional keywords (there is usually rather more to a text
               than the words of which it is composed) and for structural indications, as discussed
               above. Clearly, however, the same software tools can be used for either approach,
               though with varying success. </p>
            <p> Normally, in software-based systems depending on extensive file inversion
               techniques, indexing the whole of a text instead of simply its `keywords' increases
               the need for data compression or other ways of reducing the enormous storage
               overheads that may be involved. Because of the statistical properties of token usage
               in natural discourse great savings in storage may be made by suppressing high
               frequency tokens from an index. However this may be undesirable on a number of other
               grounds. In pathological cases, removing all `noise' words may have unexpected
               effects ("To be or not to be, that is the question" would be indexed by the word
               "question" only); in many cases, where indexing is undertaken to quantify variations
               in style or authorship, several studies have shown that is precisely the very high
               frequency terms whose relative frequencies are of most statistical significance . </p>
            <p> In continuous texts, selecting the unit of retrieval, display and context may be
               problematic. In stylistic investigations, for example, the ability to quantify term
               occurrences within arbitrary units (rates per verse line, rate per paragraph, rate
               per thousand tokens etc.) will not be catered for by software predicated on the
               document retrieval model. In lexical investigations, the ability to simply list all
               terms appearing before or after a given search expression, or to search for co-
               occurrence within a flexibly defined context unit may be equally hard to satisfy. To
               give one example, as a part of an evaluation carried out by a Working Party of the
               Inter University Computing Council, a play of Shakespeare's was converted to a
               textbase using each of three market leading commercial IR systems (BASIS, BRS/SEARCH
               and STATUS). In each case, the task of defining what was a `document' (a speech? a
               scene? the whole play?) involved compromises about the resulting searchability of the
               system. None of the three provided a fully satisfactory solution to such
               comparatively simple requirements as `Select all verse speeches of a given character
               containing at least two of a list of given terms'. </p>
            <p> To the list of methods of dealing with the ambiguity and imprecision of natural
               language already given, it is customary to add in a free text retrieval system
               extensive fuzzy matching capabilities. These will normally allow for retrieval by
               groups of tokens related morphologically, while more sophisticated systems also
               support retrieval by semantically related terms. A problem here, with continuous
               texts, is that the sheer quantitative difference in the occurrence of some terms
               approximates to a qualitative change in the effectiveness of such fuzzy matching
               techniques. Improving the recall may degrade the precision of such searches to the
               point of uselessness. It is also surprising how few commercial retrieval systems
               support the converse (or perverse) requirement of precise matching: for the IUSC
               report already alluded to we also attempted to make a text in Ancient Greek
               searchable accent-sensitive or accent-blind, a task which only one of the packages
               succeeded in doing satisfactorily. </p>
            <p> The document retrieval model of a textbase also poses problems to those working with
               very dynamic texts. The ability to annotate and tag texts on the fly, to add new
               encodings or re- interpretations into the body of a text is crucial to its usability.
               Few commercial document retrieval systems offer anything like the ability to cut and
               paste comments into individual texts, largely because updating an inverted file
               system is such a notoriously expensive operation. Indeed it has been shown that the
               marginal cost of adding more entries into very large systems such as are typically
               encountered in commercial online systems increases rapidly, to the point where it is
               more cost effective to rebuild the entire system. </p>
            <p> Hardware based systems typically aim to solve two major problems associated with the
               scale of the conceptually simple operations of searching for needles in haystacks.
               The first has to do with the simple logistics of identifying desired tokens in a
               text. Several special purpose pattern-matching hardware devices have been designed to
               perform such operations with varying capabilities. ; special purpose chips include
               the PF47 while ICL's CAFS is a well known mainstream commercial product with at least
               some pattern-matching capabilities. Unlike many other hardware search engines, CAFS
               does not require the text to be compressed or otherwise converted, except in so far
               as it requires the introduction of tags to identify and categorise individual tokens
               in the input stream, a feature which permits a high degree of structural complexity
               in the resulting textbase. </p>
            <p> The second area where hardware assistance has been shown to be of benefit is in
               exploiting parallel procesing techniques to rank texts by the extent to which their
               defining vocabularies overlap. Where text content is adequately expressed as a vector
               of terms occuring in the text, such vectors (or `fingerprints') can easily be reduced
               to long bit strings, which can then be compared very efficiently by SIMD
               architectures such as that of the DAP . It remains open to question whether such
               architectures offer significant performance improvements over the use of well tuned
               software indexes in the long term, and still more whether they are of any assistance
               in handling the more fundamental structural problems of analysing text. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head> 4. Interacting with text</head>
            <p> Most discussions of the problems of handling electronic text implicitly assume a
               model in which the user interacts with the text only by selecting from it. The
               textbase and its encoded meanings are essentially a passive cornucopia, which the
               user prods into delivering up relevant nuggets of information. However practical such
               a view may appear to be, it is essentially false to the experience of reading a
               non-electronic text, in which meaning emerges only as a result of a complex series of
               interactions between reader expectation and reader response, stimulated as much by
               associations between the text under examination and others as by its content or
               argument structure, and in which what is unstated may be as significant as what is
               not. By permitting the rearrangement of textual elements, and making explicit
               linkages between them, the infinite plasticity of electronic texts should encourage
               rather than discourage this kind of reading. Hypertext systems offer this promise,
               but have yet to fulfill it. </p>
            <p> Hypertextual and object-oriented approaches to text-management software seem to be
               rediscovering aspects of processing a text which scholars in the humanities have
               known for centuries. The description of the process of scholarly interaction with
               text given by Comenius in 1659 (figure 3) has many similarities with the process of
               browsing through an interactive electronic text: the scholar who `picketh all the
               best things out of them into his own Manual' (i.e. notebook) now `pastes them into
               the clipboard' but only the technology has changed. The structure of Comenius' work
               also has much in common with a hypertext, with its large macro-structure, and point
               to point linkage between three separate windows (graphic, Latin and vernacular). It
               can be read sequentially or by direct access. It contains pointers to other works and
               other sections of this work. </p>
            <p> In non electronic texts a whole series of conventions is already in place to cater
               for the process of interacting with many combined texts, by way of such devices as
               annotations, commentary and apparatus criticus (figure 4). Hypertextual analogues to
               these conventions are still being defined: when they do emerge they will offer
               exciting possibilities. As one example, consider the conventional apparatus criticus
               in which a 'master text' is associated with a set of notes summarising the variant
               states in other versions of the master text throughout the text. This complex textual
               object could be represented as a network in which each node is a variant state and
               the arcs represent the paths taken by one or more versions of the text through the
               possible states. It would then be possible to generate each state of the text
               independently (as a path through the network) and compare them side by side. It would
               also be possible to group versions together in terms of the number of nodes they
               share, automatically generating stemmata or minimum spanning trees.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head> 5. Conclusions</head>
            <p> Information technology is not inherently reductionist; on the contrary it is only
               the latest in a long series of methods used by applied hermeneutics, the explication
               of stored knowledge . To realise the full potential of electronic texts, we need to
               consider at least three aspects of a text in parallel: as well as concerning
               ourselves with its physical appearance, we need to recognise its uniquely linguistic
               properties and their semantics. Semantic considerations additionally imply a concern
               with the ways in which texts are read, for which our existing electronic models seem
               barely adequate. Market forces will doubtless insure that the electronic texts of the
               future will be protean in appearance; the importance which will be attached to
               considerations concerning their internal structure and functionality is less
               predictable. </p>
            <p> The meaning of a text is the product of a complex series of interactions between the
               words of which it is composed and the social, historical and literary contexts in
               which it was composed and is read. Combining texts with dictionaries and thesauri is
               one way of enhancing the retrieval capabilities of existing systems which takes
               advantage of this fact . Generalising this method to identify, for example, literary
               allusions is more problematic, but poses no additional technical problems, with the
               advent of cheap mass disk storage and efficient text search engines. </p>
            <p> An analysis of the full structural complexity of a text requires recognition of
               elements that may operate at many levels and sometimes simultaneously in many
               different descriptive or structural hierarchies. Tagging which is descriptive rather
               than narrowly functional is one step in the direction of supporting this requirement
               for electronic texts. Some aspects of the kind of text processing generally
               characterised as `object oriented', notably property inheritance, also facilitate
               this process, by enormously reducing the burden of type definition. Indeed, the
               object oriented approach, in which the processes that can be applied to an object are
               regarded as a part of the semantics of its datatype, approximates very closely to the
               way texts are read. This re-coupling of data and process may therefore prove to be of
               more consequence in the evolution of electronic text systems than those systems which
               require the definition of a `deep structure' or syntax for the texts to be processed
               independent of the processes to be carried out on them. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
