
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Historian and the Database</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>XML version for my archive</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Retagged in XML from old source file</p>
            <p>Text later published in :   <bibl n=""><date>1990</date>
      <title>The Historian and the Database</title>
      <title>Historians, Computers and Data: applications in research and training</title> ed
      E.Mawdsley, N. Morgan et al. Manchester: Manchester University Press </bibl>
</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2014-12-15">Initial conversion; added header</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>

<!--
OK, here it is, in all its unvarnished glory: the very original
text of my after dinner lucubrations as requested, unchanged from
the form in which I first typed them, except that I've changed the
spacing from double to single and converted from WP to ASCII. 
What's Rich G. doing up there? Would he like to visit the Oxford
Text Archive too? Would he like it to visit him? Give the man an
email account.

in haste

Lou
-->
<body>
<head>The historian and the database</head>
<quote>
<l>Hwaet! we Gar-Dena  in gear-dagum</l>
<l>theod-cyninga thrym gefrunon,</l>
<l>hu tha aethelingas  ellen fremedon.</l>
<l>Oft Scyld Scefing  sceathena threatum</l>
<l>monegum maegthum  meoda-setla ofteah;</l>
<l>egsode Eorle, syththan aerest wearth</l>
<l>feasceaft funden; he thaes frofre gebad:</l>
<l>weox under wolcnum, weorth-myndum thah</l>
<l>oththaet him aeghwylc thara ymb-sittendra</l>
<l>ofer hron-rade hyran scolde,</l>
<l>gomban gyldan:  thaet waes god cyning!</l>
</quote>
<p>These are the opening words of the Old English epic Beowulf, the
earliest literary masterpiece of our language, probably composed
in 8th century Mercia. When its unknown Christian author affected
as I have just done the imagined manner of the scop in the
ancestral mead-hall, he was of course almost as ignorant as I of
living conditions in the 5th century pagan courts of Hrothgar or
Hygelac, where the poem's action is set. He may even have been,
like me, somewhat skeptical about the objective existence of the
underwater monsters and dragon-guarded treasure-hoards which
provide the poem's hero with so much excitement. Yet he and his
audience still felt the need to take an ancient story and use it
as a vehicle for articulating a contemporary opposition: the
tension between atavistic pagan fatalism and optimistic Christian
perfectibilianism; a clash marvellously condensed in the  much-
quoted line "Wyrd oft neriath unfaegne eorl thonne his ellen
deah" (Fate will often spare the undoomed man whose courage is
good enough; though the ancient Germanic notion of Fate is not at
all the same as the ancient Greek notion now inextricably bound
up in the modern English word). </p>
<p>But reading Beowulf today is not entirely an exercise in
hermeneutics; to appreciate this poem, as to appreciate any epic,
we need only to recognise its historical purpose. Beowulf was
composed as a history book, even, I contend, a historical
database: we do it an injustice to treat it as anything less.
Its language is not that of everyday 8th century Mercia (as far
as other evidence shows): it is formally arranged; it uses the
metrical device of alliteration; it contains some phrases that
seem to be fossilised metaphors (such as "hron-rade" "whale-road"
for sea) and others that are clearly formulaic ("gomban gyldan"/
gift-giving); it is rich in near synonyms (there are I forget how
many different words for weapons and armour of various kinds); it
even contains phrases we would like to interpret as grim jokes
(in cataloguing Scyld's valorous deeds, the poet remarks that he
"deprived many princes of their mead-stools"). The artifice of
this language has two crucial functions: firstly it serves to
mark this text as belonging to a specific body of linguistic
productions, to categorise it, to locate it in another imagined
world; and secondly, precisely because it is so different from
the every-day tittle-tattle of 8th century Mercia, to make the
text itself memorable. The heroic style seems to have a pragmatic
function:  in  pre-technological, pre-literate society it
preserves that most precious of cultural artefacts, a society's
self-image. Orature prefigures literature as a way of preserving
speech.</p>
<p>In a somewhat mind-boggling book called "Worlds of Reference"
published two years ago, the distinguished linguist Tom McArthur
proposes that, provided we take a sufficiently broad perspective,
we will see there have been four great communicative shifts in
human history: each mediated by its characteristic enabling
technology: that of speech, of script, of print and of
electronics. Each of these technologies represents a better
attempt to satisfy the same fundamental human desire: not to be
forgotten, to step outside of time.</p>
<p>In the begining, he argues, there was only functional speech -
"Pass the burnt root dear" kind of stuff. But then, stuck as
human intelligence is with a strong sense of things not-having-
always-been quite as bad as they are now, (not to mention the
dour suspicion that they may well get quite a lot worse) there
evolved the concept of "Storage Speech" - language with quite
another type of function: that of preserving information. Special
techniques - such as the alliteration and kennings with which I
began - were invented for this purpose, to ensure the accuracy of
what was passed on. Other techniques, such as the shamanistic use
of fetishes, beads, knots and other non verbal signifiers seem to
have been less successful- at least in the European context -
than that satisfyingly recursive method of changing the nature of
the medium itself. And so, MacArthur says, the database came into
being, long even before writing, as a formalised narrative, an
oral repository of that information by which a culture defines
itself. And, the claim is, successive paradigmatic shifts have
not served to dislodge that primary atavistic function, of 
tieing down the here and now, locating it in a temporal nexus,
giving us a past, a present and a future. Instead they have
emphasised or facilitated different aspects of that primary urge
to a greater or lesser extent.</p>
<p>We have not yet drunk deeply enough (perhaps) to be overwhelmed
entirely by this sort of rapid canter through world history.
There comes a point of elevation (whether metaphorical or actual)
from which all details blur into one cosmic whole. And surely
there are at least as many differences between the secret
language of a priestly elite and the demotic of the electronic
bulletin board as there are similarities. Quite a good case (but
perhaps a bit too Marxist for this occasion) could be made for
the view that the shift from oral to written to printed to
electronic communication is a necessary consequence of the
progressive alienation of the individual: the whole paraphernalia
of copyright and ownership, the notion of authorship itself, seem
to be inextricably intertwined with a particular political system
rather than with any evolutionary necessity.</p>
<p>But it does no harm to look for similarities: indeed, it is a
very seductive notion, that of MacArthur's that "we have been
this way before". I wish I had some explanation to offer for the
pleasure with which I draw a parallel between the writer at his
word-processor cutting and pasting choice phrases from previous
compositions on the one hand, and the bard of yore picking and
recombining kennings and genealogies from his word-hoard on the
other. Is it an innate human characteristic, this desire to step
outside of time? is it a peculiarity of some times rather than
others? is it related to other phenomena? Before this audience I
will not presume to provide answers to these essentially
historiographical questions. </p>
<p>Instead, let me focus more precisely on the topic of this
conference: the use of this latest version of "storage speech" in
making sense of the products of earlier versions of the same.
When a new technology emerges, an under-valuing of its
predecessor is commonplace. Thus, we are told that some
renaissance printers, having set Carolingian manuscripts into
type, tended to use the originals as fire-lighters. And the metal
plates from which the last edition of the OED was printed     
proved such an embarassment to the Oxford University Press that
many of them have been given away as trendy ornaments.  As this
last example shows, it is also easy to over-value an outmoded
technology  - to be sentimental about steam trains or red phone-
boxes is no less an intellectual weakness because it is an
officially sanctioned one.  Let me parenthetically remark on how
frequently we find various forms of sentimentality being
officially sanctioned these days. As good historians, I hope you
will all be on your guard against the current insidious attempts
to manufacture national memory as a means of fuelling the
xenophobia on which governments such as the present one depend.
The word has gone out somewhere in the corridors of power that
Britain is ripe for "theming-up" and we look to the professional
guardians of the past (that's you lot) to thwart it: please read
Robert Hewison's book on the Heritage Industry for further
information.</p>
<p>Surprisingly perhaps, the computer might just provide you with
the tools to do it. Sentimentality is a form of storage speech in
which all the rich awkwardnesses of actuality have been
conveniently smoothed away, to serve some polemical end. It is
typified by the artefact-free museum, the theme park, the digest.
It avoids controversy and thrives on passive acceptance. But we
don't have to be sentimental in our attitudes to the past. The
past is actually still there to be discovered, encapsulated in
all those other undervalued forms of storage speech, buried in
local archives and other forms of distributed database such as
human memory. What the computer gives us is a new way of gaining
access to that information, efficient ways of storing it, of
searching and re-presenting it. It enables us to combine
information from a variety of sources in ways so quantitatively
different as to approximate a qualitative change. And it enables
us to add interpretations to the store of information,
automatically or mediated by as many editorial processes as there
are editors, without however significantly changing the original
stored form of the data. Simply, it lets us form our own
conclusions from the available data. As such, it is as potent and
as subversive a tool as ever the printing press was. </p>
<p>This may sound implausible to those whose view of this technology
was formed in the days when the machine was called a "giant
brain" and was tended by serious people in white coats. It may
also sound absurdly optimistic to those who fear (perhaps justly)
that deprivation of access to information will become a new
instrument of class oppression. But the cat is already out of the
bag. The micros are already in the classrooms - perhaps small,
under-funded and over-used, but they are there; and what has once
been learned cannot easily be unlearned. </p>
<p>My title, "The historian and the database", suggests an
opposition, but my theme is one of synthesis. Whether or not we
accept the Californian millenarianism which loudly proclaims the
death of the printed book, it is clear that the written word has
at least found a new home. As a way of marshalling concepts and
modelling our understanding of them, the formal structures of
language have served us very well for centuries. But in order to
store and analyse those linguistic productions themselves, it has
become necessary to define a new sort of storage speech. Now, the
most productive way of processing a text by computer turns out to
entail additional interpretative information about it, either
separately in some sort of database structure, or embedded within
it as markup or tagging. It looks as if we are making up for the
computer's lack of innate intelligence by supplying rules for
interpretation and categorisation, sometimes of the most
rudimentary sort - such as where one word stops and the next
begins. But what we are actually doing is representing both data
and meta-data: storing both information and guidance on its
interpretation. Let me conclude by suggesting that this double
focus has always characterised what I earlier called "storage
speech" and that consequently to perceive it as a limitation is
to miss the point - in rather the same way as it would be to miss
the point to say of the storage speech with which I began that it
is repetitive or cliche-ridden. </p>
<p>
---------------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>Lou Burnard is currently receiving therapy at a private
institution on the South Coast.</p>
</body></text></TEI>