<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="teixlite.css"?>
<!--DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI//DTD TEI Lite XML ver. 1//EN"
"/home/lou/TEI/web/Software/tei-emacs/xml/dtds/tei/teixlite.dtd"
[<!ATTLIST figure file CDATA #IMPLIED>
]-->
<!-- NOTATION PNG SYSTEM "foo.bar"><!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM "silfi-fig1.png" NDATA PNG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM "silfi-fig2.png" NDATA PNG>
-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Where did we go wrong? A retrospective look at the design of the BNC
</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
<p>Unpublished draft</p>    <!-- one of (publisher distributor authority pubPlace address idno availability date p) -->
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
<p>Derived from presentations at SILFI (Duisburg, 1999) and TALC
      (Graz, 1999)</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <!-- one of (change list) -->
   <change>
    <date>Nov 23</date>
    
<name>LB</name>     <!-- one of (anchor gap pb milestone lb interpGrp interp index name resp) -->
    
  Continued, on the way back from Leicester
   </change>
<change>    <date>June 18</date>
   
<name>LB</name>     <!-- one of (anchor gap pb milestone lb interpGrp interp index name resp) -->
    Continued, on the way back from New York
   </change>
   <change>
    <date>May 22</date>
   
<name>LB</name>     <!-- one of (anchor gap pb milestone lb interpGrp interp index name resp) -->
    Continued, on the way to Bergen via Oslo
   </change>
<change>    <date>May 11</date>
    
<name>LB</name>     <!-- one of (anchor gap pb milestone lb interpGrp interp index name resp) -->
   Started draft
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text><front><titlePage><docTitle><titlePart>Where did we go wrong? A
  retrospective look at the British National Corpus
</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor>Lou Burnard, Humanities Computing Unit, Oxford University
</docAuthor></titlePage>
<div type="abstract">
<p>The British National Corpus (BNC) has been  a major influence on
the construction of language corpora during the last
decade, if only as a significant reference point.  This corpus may be seen as the culmination of a research
tradition going back to the one-million word Brown corpus of
     1964, but its
constitution and  its industrial-scale production techniques look
forward to a new world in which language-focussed engineering and
software development are at the heart of the information society
instead of lurking on its academic fringes.
</p><p>
This paper attempts to review the design and management issues and decisions
taken during the construction of the BNC and to suggest what lessons have been learned
over the last five years about how such corpus building exercises can
most usefully be extended into the new century. 
</p>
</div>
   </front><body>

<div1><head>What, exactly, is the BNC?</head>

<p>The British National Corpus (BNC) is a 100 million word corpus of
   modern British English, originally produced by a consortium of
   dictionary publishers and academic researchers in
   1990-1994. The Consortium brought together as members  dictionary publishers OUP,
   Longman, and Chambers, and research centres at the Universities of
   Lancaster and Oxford, and at the British Library. The project was originally funded under
   the Joint Framework for Information Technology, a
   British Government initiative designed to facilitate
   academic-industrial co-operation in the production of what were
   regarded as <soCalled>pre-competitive</soCalled> resources, whereby the
   Department of Trade and Industry provided 50 percent funding to
   commercial partners, and the Science and Engineering Research
   Council funded 100 percent of the academics' costs. </p>

<p>The nineties have been called many things in social history: as far
   as computing facilities are concerned however, I suggest that
   an appropriate epithet
   might well be <term>neotenous</term>. It is salutary to remember that
   in computer magazines of the early nineties, the big debate was
   about the relative merits of word processors WordPerfect release 5
   and WinWord (an ancestor of the now ubiquitous Microsoft Word). On
   your desktop, if you were a reasonably well-funded academic, you
   might have a <soCalled>personal computer</soCalled> with a fast Intel 386 processor,
   and as much as 50 Mb of diskspace — just about enough to run
   Microsoft's new-fangled Windows 3.1 operating system. But your real
   computing work would be done in your laboratory or at your centralised
   computing service, where you would probably have shared use of a
   Unix system of some kind or a VAX minicomputer. This was also a
   period in which a few people were starting to talk about a new
   hypertext concept called the World Wide Web, a few of whom might
   even have tried an impressive new interface program called
   Mosaic...</p>

<p>The art of corpus building was however already well understood in
   the nineties, at least by its European practitioners. <q>Corpora are
   becoming mainstream</q> declared Leech, with palpable surprise, in
   the preface to the ICAME proceedings volume of 1990. We may discern
   three intellectual currents or differences of emphasis already
   becoming clear at this period: the traditional school initiated by
   the Brown Corpus, institutionalised in LOB, and perpetuated through
   ICAME; the Birmingham school, which had been building up ever
   larger collections of textual material as part of the COBUILD
   project throughout the late eighties<note place="foot">For a summary of this highly
   influential work, prefiguring that of the BNC in many regards, see
   <ref target="Renouf">Renouf 1986</ref>, and the many
   publications of its intellectual centre, J. McH. Sinclair,
   e.g. <ref>Sinclair 1987</ref></note>; and the American view most
   famously expressed by Mitch Marcus as <q>there's no data like more
   data</q>. The locale in which these traditions most visibly began
   to combine into a new form was in computer aided lexicography,
   partly as a consequence of 
   the availability of computer-held representations of traditionally
   organised dictionaries, such as  Longman's
   Dictionary of Contemporary English, and of course the
   computerization of the Oxford English Dictionary itself, partly as
   a result of an upsurge of interest amongst the computational
   linguistics community (see for example <ref>Atkins92</ref>). </p>

<p>At the same time, the early nineties were an exciting period for
   synergy in research applications of information technology. <soCalled>Humanities Computing</soCalled> and
   <soCalled>Computational Linguistics</soCalled> were pulling together in their first
   (and to date only) joint success, the establishment of Text
   Encoding standards appropriate to the dawning digital age.<note place="foot">The
   introduction to <ref target="Zampolli">Zampolli 1994</ref> makes
   this connexion explicit.</note> 
The term <term>language engineering</term> was being used to
   describe not a dubious kind of social policy, but a sexy new
   sort of technology. It is in this context that we should place the
   fact that production of the BNC was funded over three  years, with
   a budget of over  GBP 1.5 million. </p>

<p>The project came into being through an unusual coincidence of
   interests amongst lexicographic publishers, government, and
   researchers. Amongst the publishers, Oxford University Press and Longman were at that time
   beginning to wake up to the possible benefits of corpus
   use in this field. One should point also to the success of the Collins COBUILD
   dictionaries, (first published in 1987, and probably the first major
   language-learner dictionary whole-heartedly to embrace corpus
   principles) as a
   vital motivating factor for rival publishers OUP and
   Longman.  For
   the government, a key factor was a desire to stimulate a UK
   language engineering industry in the climate of expanded interest
   in this field in Europe. For researchers at Oxford and Lancaster,
   this unlikely synergy was a golden opportunity to push further the
   boundaries of corpus construction, as further discussed below. And
   for the British Library, the corpus was one of a number of
   exploratory projects being set up to experiment with new media at
   the beginning of the age of the digital library (for other
   examples, see the essays in <ref target="Carpenter">Carpenter 1998</ref>)
  </p>

<p>The stated goals of the BNC project were quite explicit: it would
   create a language corpus at least an order of magnitude bigger than
   any freely available hitherto<note place="foot">Though incontestably larger, the
   Bank of English corpus developed as part of the Cobuild project was
   not originally designed for distribution or use by anyone outside that
   project; to this day, IPR and other restrictions have effectively
   limited access to it by the research community at large.</note>The new corpus would be synchronic
   and contemporary and it would comprise a range of samples from the
   full range of British English language production, both spoken and
   written. Considerable debate and discussion focussed on the notion
   of sampling, and in particular of corpus design. Unlike some other
   collections of language data then popular, the BNC would be of
   avowedly non-opportunistic design.  In order to make the corpus
   generally applicable, it would contain automatically-generated word
   class annotation, and it would also include very detailed
   contextual information. These three features, together with its
   general availability and large size, would make the BNC unique
   amongst available collections of language data, and would also
   justify the <soCalled>national</soCalled> part of its title (originally included
   simply in recognition of the fact that the project was partly
   government funded).</p>

<p>Unstated, but clearly implicit in the project design, were other
   goals. For the commercial partners, the major reason for their 
   substantial investment of time and money was of course the
   production of better ELT dictionaries, plus, perhaps some regaining
   of competitive position by the authoritative nature of the
   resulting corpus. For the academic partners, an unstated goal was
   to provide a new model for the development of corpora within the
   emerging European language industries, and to put to the test
   emerging ideas about standardization of encoding and text
   representation and documentation. But over-riding all there was the
   simple desire to build a really big corpus!</p>

   </div1>
<div1><head>Organization of the project</head>

<p>An interesting and unanticipated consequence of the academic -
   industrial co-operation was the need for some accomodation between the
   academic desire for perfection and the commercial imperatives of
   delivering a pre-defined product on time and not too far over
   budget (see further <ref target="Burnard">Burnard 1999</ref>).
In setting up an
   industrial scale text production system, the project found itself
   inevitably making compromises in both design and execution. The
   production line itself, dubbed by project manager Jeremy Clear the
   <term>BNC Sausage machine</term> is shown in the following
   figure:<figure>
       <graphic url="media/silfi-fig1.png" width="40%"/><head>The BNC Sausage Machine</head></figure>
    </p>

    <p>As this figure demonstrates, production of different types of
    material was shared out amongst a number of different agencies:
    Longman focussed on the collection and transcription of spoken
    materials, and OUP on the transcription of written materials,
    using a mixture of OCR, rekeying, and processing of materials
    already in digital form. Conversion of all materials to a single
    consistent format and validation of its structure was carried out
    at OUCS, which also maintained a database of contextual and
    workflow information. Linguistic annotation of the material was
    carried out at Lancaster, using the well-established CLAWS tagger
    (discussed below and in <ref target="Garside96">Garside
    1996</ref>, and the resulting texts then combined with standard
    metadata descriptions extracted from the database to form a single
    document conformant (insofaras these were already published) to the
    recommendations of the Text Encoding Initiative (<ref
    target="TEI-P3">Sperberg-McQueen 1994</ref>). </p>


<p>As might be expected, the rate with which the sausage machine
turned was far from constant over the life of the project, and there
     were inevitably temporary blockages and hold ups. The figure
below demonstrates through-put (in millions of words per quarter) over
     the life time of the project:
<figure><graphic url="media/silfi-fig2.png" width="40%" /><head>BNC Through-put</head></figure>
Through-put is shown separately for each of: material
       received from the data preparation agency; texts validated against
       the DTD; and texts annotated with POS codes.
</p>

<p>The work of developing the corpus was shared out amongst five task
   groups, on which staff from each of the consortium members
   participated to varying extents. These task groups and their
   responsibilities may be summarised as follows:

<list type="gloss"><label>permissions </label><item>design and implementation of
a standard permissions letter for use with all those owning IPR in the
      materials to be included in the corpus;</item>
<label>design criteria</label><item>definition of the range
       of text types to be included in the corpus and of their target proportions; </item>
<label>enrichment and annotation</label><item>implementation of
       linguistic and contextual annotation of the corpus texts; </item>
<label>encoding and markup</label><item>definition of the 
       markup scheme to be applied in the final reference form of the
       corpus, and of procedures for mapping to it from a variety of
       data capture formats;</item>
<label>retrieval software</label><item>definition and implementation
       of simple retrieval software able to make use of the detailed
       corpus encoding.</item>
			</list>
Each of these topics is further discussed in the following sections.
     </p>

<div2><head>Permissions issues</head>

<p>As noted above, the BNC was the first corpus of its size to be made
    widely available. This was possible largely because of the work
    done by this task group in  successfully defining standard
    forms of agreement, between rights owners and the Consortium on the
    one hand, and between corpus users and the Consortium on the
    other. IPR owners were requested to give permission for the
    inclusion of their materials in the corpus free of charge, and
    shown the standard licence agreement which is still used today.
    Acceptance of this arrangement was perhaps to some extent
    facilitated by the relative novelty of the concept and the
    prestige attached to the project; however by no means every rights
    owner approached was immediately ready to assign rights to use
    digital versions of their material for linguistic research purpose
    indefinitely and free of charge. Some chose to avoid
    committing themselves at all, and others refused any non-paying
    arrangements. </p>
<p>Two specific problems attached to  permissions issues relating to
    the spoken materials. Because participants had been assured that their
    identies would be kept secret, much effort was put into pondering
    how best to anonymise the their contributions, without unduly
    compromising their linguistic usefulness. Specific references to
    named persons were in many cases removed; the option of  replacing
    them by alternative (but linguistically similar) names was briefly
    considered but felt to be impractical. </p>
<p>A more embarassing problem derives from the fact that participants
    in the demographically sampled part of the corpus had been asked
    (and had therefore given)
    permission only for inclusion of transcribed versions of their
    speech, not for inclusion of the speech itself. While such
    permission could in principle be sought again from the original
    respondents, the effectiveness of the anonymization procedures
    used now makes this a rather difficult task.
     </p>
     <p>Two additional factors affected the willingness of IPR owners
     to donate materials: firstly, that no complete texts were to be
     included; secondly, that there was no intention of commercially
     exploiting or distributing the corpus materials themselves. This
     did not however preclude commercial usage of derived products,
     created as a consequence of access to the corpus. This
     distinction, made explicit in the standard User Licence, is
     obviously essential both to the continued availability of the corpus
     for research purposes, and to its continued usefulness in the
     commercial sector, for example as a testbed for language products
     from humble spelling correction software to sophisticated
     translation memories. <!--Such of the corpus materials itself,
     this licence permits commercial exploitation of derived works,
     i.e. products created with its aid. --> To emphasize the
     non-commercial basis on which the corpus itself was to be
     distributed, one of the academic members of the consortium,
     OUCS, was appointed sole agent for licensing its use, reporting
     any dubious cases to the Consortium itself. Initially restricted
     to the EU, distribution of the corpus outside Europe was finally
     permitted in 1998.
   </p>
    </div2>

<div2><head>Design Criteria</head>

<p>I referred above to the BNC's <q>non-opportunistic design</q>. A
      sense of the historical context is also perhaps helpful to
      understand the singling out of this aspect of the design as
      noteworthy. During the mid-nineties, although textual materials
      of all kinds were increasingly being prepared in digital form as
      a precursor to their appearance in print, the notion that the
      digital form might itself be of value was not at all
      widespread. Moreover, digitization in those pre-e-commerce days
      was far from uniform either in coverage or in format. As a
      consequence, there was a natural tendency in the research
      community to snap up such unconsidered trifles of electronic
      text as were available without considering too deeply their
      status with respect to the language as a whole. Because, to take
      one notorious example, large quantities of the <title>Wall
      Street Journal</title> were widely available in digital form,
      there was a danger that the specific register typified by that
      newspaper would increasingly serve as a basis for
      computationally-derived linguistic generalisations about the
      whole language.  </p>

<p>As a corrective, therefore, the BNC project established at its
      outset the goal of sampling materials from across the language
      with respect to explicit design criteria rather than simply
      their contingent availability in machine-readable form. These
      criteria (usefully summarized in  <ref target="Atkins92">Atkins 1992</ref>) defined a
      specific range of text characteristics and target proportions
      for the material to be collected. The goal of the BNC was to
      make it possible to say something about language in general. But
      is language that which is <term>received</term> (read and heard)
      or that which is <term>produced</term> (written and spoken)? As
      good Anglo-Saxon pragmatists, the designers of the BNC chose to
      ignore this classic Saussurian dichotomy by attempting to take
      account of both perspectives.</p>

<p>The objective was to define a stratified sample according to stated
      criteria. While one might hesitate to claim that the
      corpus was statistically representative of the whole language in
      terms either of production or reception, at least the corpus
      would represent the degree of variability known to exist along
      certain specific dimensions, such as mode of production (speech
      or writing); medium (book, newspaper, etc.); domain
      (imaginative, scientific, leisure etc.); social context (formal,
      informal, business, etc.)  and so on.
     </p>

<p>This is not the place to rehearse in detail the motivations for the
    text classification scheme adopted by the BNC<note place="foot">These are
    exhaustively discussed in e.g. <ref target="Atkins92">Atkins 1992</ref> for the
    written material, and <ref target="Crowdy95">Crowdy 1995</ref> for the spoken
    material; discussion and detailed tables for each classification
    are also provided in the <title>BNC User Reference Guide</title> (<ref
    target="Burnard95">Burnard 1995, revised 2000</ref>).  </note>. For example, spoken texts may be
    characterized by age, sex, or social class (of respondent, not
    speaker), or by the domain, region, or type of speech captured;
    written texts may also be characterized by author age, sex, type,
    by audience, circulation, status, and (as noted above) by medium
    or domain. Some of these categories were regarded as
    <term>selection criteria</term>, i.e. the domain of values for
    this category was predefined, and a target proportion identified
    for each; while others were regarded as <term>descriptive
    criteria</term>, i.e. while no particular target was set for the
    proportion of material of a particular type, other things being
    equal, attempts would be made to maximize variability within such
    categories.  It should be stressed that the purpose of noting
    these variables was to improve coverage, <emph>not</emph> to
    facilitate accessibility or subsetting of the corpus. </p>

<p>Inevitably, the design goals of the project had to be tempered by
      the realities of economic life. A rough guess suggests that the
      cost of collecting and transcribing in electronic form one
      million words of naturally occurring speech is at least 10 times
      higher than the cost of adding another million words of
      newspaper text: the proportion of written to spoken material in
      the BNC is thus 10:1, even though many people would suggest that
      if speech and writing are of equal significance in the language,
      they should therefore be present in equal amounts in the
      corpus. Within the spoken corpus, an attempt is made to
      represent equally the production of different speech types (in
      the context-governed part) and its reception (in the
      demographically sampled part). </p>

<p>Similarly pragmatic concerns lead to the predominance within the
     written part of the corpus of published books and
     periodical. However, while text that is published in the form of
     books, magazines, etc., may not be representative of the totality of
     written language that is produced, (since writing for publication
     is a comparatively specialized activity in which few people
     engage), it is obviously representative of the written language
     that most people receive. In addition, it should be noted that
     significant amounts of other material (notably unpublished
     materials such as letters or gray literature) are also
     included. And even within a readily accessible text-type such as
     newspapers, care was taken to sample both broadsheet and tabloid
     varieties, both national and regional in such a way that the
     readily available (national broadsheet) variety did not drown out
     the other, less readily found, variants.</p>


<p>In its final form, the BNC World Edition contains 4054 texts and
      occupies (including SGML markup) 1,508,392 Kbytes, or about 1.5
      Gb. In total, it comprises just over 100 million orthographic
      words (specifically, 100,467,090), but the number of w-units
      (POS-tagged items) is slightly less: 97,619,934. The total
      number of s-units identified by CLAWS is just over 6 million
      (6,053,093).  The following table shows the breakdown in terms
      of <list>
<item>texts : number of distinct samples not exceeding 45,000 words
</item>
<item>S-units: number of <gi>s</gi> elements identified by the CLAWS system
(more or less  equivalent to sentences)
</item>
<item>W-units: number of <gi>w</gi> elements identified by the CLAWS system
(more or less  equivalent to words)
</item> </list>
</p>

<p><table xml:id="alltyp" rend="inline">
<head>Composition of the BNC World Edition</head>
<row>
<cell>Text type</cell>
<cell>Texts</cell>
<cell>Kbytes</cell>
<cell>W-units</cell>
<cell>S-units</cell>
<cell>percent</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>Spoken demographic</cell><cell>153</cell><cell>4206058</cell><cell>4.30</cell><cell>610563</cell><cell>10.08</cell></row>
<row><cell>Spoken context-governed</cell><cell>757</cell><cell>6135671</cell><cell>6.28</cell><cell>428558</cell><cell>7.07</cell></row>
<row><cell>All Spoken</cell><cell>910</cell><cell>10341729</cell><cell>10.58</cell><cell>1039121</cell><cell>17.78</cell></row>
<row><cell>Written books and periodicals</cell><cell>2688</cell><cell>78580018</cell><cell>80.49</cell><cell>4403803</cell><cell>72.75</cell></row>
<row><cell>Written-to-be-spoken</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>1324480</cell><cell>1.35</cell><cell>120153</cell><cell>1.98</cell></row>
<row><cell>Written miscellaneous</cell><cell>421</cell><cell>7373707</cell><cell>7.55</cell><cell>490016</cell><cell>8.09</cell></row>
<row><cell>All Written</cell><cell>3144</cell><cell>87278205</cell><cell>89.39</cell><cell>5013972</cell><cell>82.82</cell></row>
</table></p>

<p>Within the written part of the corpus, target proportions were
      defined for each of a range of types of media, and subject
      matter. Here for example are the counts for written domain:
<table xml:id="wridom" rend="inline">
<head>Written domain</head>
<row><cell>Domain</cell><cell>texts</cell><cell>w-units</cell><cell>%</cell>
<cell>s-units</cell><cell>%</cell></row>
<row><cell>Applied science</cell><cell>370</cell><cell>7104635</cell><cell>8.14</cell><cell>357067</cell><cell>7.12</cell></row>
<row><cell>Arts</cell><cell>261</cell><cell>6520634</cell><cell>7.47</cell><cell>321442</cell><cell>6.41</cell></row>
<row><cell>Belief and thought</cell><cell>146</cell><cell>3007244</cell><cell>3.44</cell><cell>151418</cell><cell>3.01</cell></row>
<row><cell>Commerce and finance</cell><cell>295</cell><cell>7257542</cell><cell>8.31</cell><cell>382717</cell><cell>7.63</cell></row>
<row><cell>Imaginative</cell><cell>477</cell><cell>16377726</cell><cell>18.76</cell><cell>1356458</cell><cell>27.05</cell></row>
<row><cell>Leisure</cell><cell>438</cell><cell>12187946</cell><cell>13.96</cell><cell>760722</cell><cell>15.17</cell></row>
<row><cell>Natural and pure science</cell><cell>146</cell><cell>3784273</cell><cell>4.33</cell><cell>183466</cell><cell>3.65</cell></row>
<row><cell>Social science</cell><cell>527</cell><cell>13906182</cell><cell>15.93</cell><cell>700122</cell><cell>13.96</cell></row>
<row><cell>World affairs</cell><cell>484</cell><cell>17132023</cell><cell>19.62</cell><cell>800560</cell><cell>15.96</cell></row>
</table>

     </p>

<p>The spoken part of the corpus is itself divided into two.
      Approximately half of it is composed of informal conversation
      recorded by nearly 200 volunteers recruited for the
      project by a market research agency and forming a balanced
      sample with respect to age, gender, geographical area, and
      social class. This sampling method reflects the demographic
      distribution of spoken language, but (because of its small size)
      would have excluded from the corpus much
      linguistically-significant variation due to context. To
      compensate for this, the other half of the spoken corpus
      consists of speech recorded in each of a large range of
      predefined situations (for example public and semi-public
      meetings, professional interviews, formal and semi-formal
      proceedings in academia, business, or leisure contexts).
     </p>

     <p>In retrospect, some text classifications (author ethnic origin for example)
    were poorly
    defined and many of them were only partially or unreliably
    populated. Pressures of production and lack of ready
    information  seriously affected the accuracy and
    consistency with which all these variables were actually recorded in
    the text headers. Even such a
    seemingly neutral concept as dating is not unproblematic for
    written text — are we talking about the date of the copy used or of the first
    publication? Similarly, when we talk of <q>Author age</q> do we
    mean age at the time the book was published, or when it was
    printed?   </p>

<p>Of course, corpora before the BNC had been designed according to
    similar methods, though perhaps not on such a scale. In general,
    however, the metadata associated with such corpora had been
    regarded as something distinct from the corpus itself, to be
    sought out by the curious in the <soCalled>manual of information
    to accompany</soCalled> the corpus. One innovation due to the Text
    Encoding Initiative, and adopted by the BNC, was the idea of an
    integrated <term>header</term>, attached to each text file in the corpus, and
    using the same formalism. This header
    contains information identifying and classifying each text, as
    well as additional specifics such as demographic data about the
    speakers, and housekeeping information about the size, update
    status, etc. Again following the TEI, the BNC factors out all
    common date (such as documentation and definition of the
    classification codes used) into a header file applicable to the
    whole corpus, retaining within each text header only the specific
    codes applicable to that text.<note place="foot">For further description of the way TEI Headers
    are used by the BNC see <ref target="Dunlop">Dunlop 1995</ref></note> </p> 

<p>During production, however,
    classificatory and other metadata was naturally gathered as part
    of the text capture process by the different data capture agencies
    mentioned above and stored locally before it was integrated within
    the OUCS database from which the TEI headers were generated. With
    the best will in the world, it was therefore difficult to avoid
    inconsistencies in the way metadata was captured, and hence to
    ensure that it was uniformly reliable when combined. This is a
    problem which we did not have leisure to address during production
    of BNC1.
     </p>
    </div2>

<div2><head>Annotation</head>

<p>Word tagging in the BNC was performed automatically, using  CLAWS4,
 an automatic tagger developed at
 Lancaster University from the CLAWS1
 tagger originally produced to perform a similar task on
 the one million LOB Corpus. The system is described more fully in  <ref
 target="Leech">Leech 1994</ref>; its theory and practice are explored
 in <ref target="Garside97">Garside 1997</ref>, and full technical
 documentation of its usage with the BNC is provided in the Manual
 which accompanies the BNC World Edition (<ref>Leech 2000</ref>). </p> 
<p>CLAWS4 is a <term>hybrid</term> tagger, employing a mixture of
 probabilistic and non-probabilistic techniques. It assigns a
 part-of-speech code (or
 sometimes two codes) to a word as a result of four main processes: 
<list>
<item>tokenization into words (usually marked by spaces) and
	orthographic sentences (usually marked by punctuation);
	enclitic verbs (such as <mentioned>'ll</mentioned> or
	<mentioned>'s</mentioned>), and negative contractions (such as
	<mentioned>n't</mentioned>) are regarded as special cases, as are some common
	merged forms such as <mentioned>dunno</mentioned> (which is
	tokenized as <q>do + n't + know</q></item>
       <item>initial POS code assignment: all the POS codes which
	might be assigned to a token are retrieved, either by lookup from a
	50,000 word lexicon, or by application of some simple
	morphological procedures; where more
	than one code is assigned to the word, the relative
	probability for each code is also provided by the lexicon
	look-up or other procedures. Probabilities are also adjusted
	on the basis of word-position within the sentence.
       </item>
       <item>disambiguation or code selection is then applied, using a
       technique known as <term>Viterbi alignment</term> which chooses the
       probabilities associated with each code to determine the most
       likely path through a sequence of ambiguous codes, in rather
       the same way as the text messaging applications found on many
       current mobile phones. At the end of this stage, the possible
       codes are ranked in descending probability for each word in its
       context</item>
       <item>idiom tagging is a further refinement of the procedure,
       in which groups of words and their tags are matched against
       predefined idiomatic templates, resembling finite-state
       networks.  </item>
      </list>
     </p>
<p>With these procedures, CLAWS was able to achieve over 95% accuracy
      (i.e. lack of indeterminacy) in assigning POS codes to any word
      in the corpus. To improve on this, the Lancaster team developed
      further the basic ideas of  <soCalled>idiom
      tagging</soCalled>, using a template tagger which could be
      taught more sophisticated contextual rules, in part derived by
      semi-automatic procedures from a sample set of texts which had
      previously been manually disambiguated. This process is further
      described in the Reference Manual cited.
     </p>

    </div2>
<div2><head>Encoding</head>
<p>The markup scheme used by the BNC was defined at the same time as
      the Text Encoding Initiative's work was being done (and to some
      extent by the same people); the two schemes are thus
      unsurprisingly close, though there are differences. Since this
      SGML-based scheme has been so widely taken up and is well documented
      elsewhere, we do not discuss it further here.</p>
<p>As some indication of the extent and nature of the markup in the BNC, here is the start
			 of a typical written text:
<eg><![CDATA[
<text complete=Y decls='CN000 HN001 QN000 SN000'>
<div1 complete=Y org=SEQ>
<head type=MAIN>
<s n=001>
<w NP0>CAMRA <w NN1>FACT <w NN1>SHEET
<w AT0>No <w CRD>1 </head>
<head r=it type=SUB>
<s n=002><w AVQ>How <w NN1>beer <w VBZ>is
<w AJ0-VVN>brewed </head>
<p><s n=003>
<w NN1>Beer <w VVZ>seems <w DT0>such
<w AT0>a <w AJ0>simple <w NN1>drink <w CJT>that
<w PNP>we <w VVB>tend <w TO0>to <w VVI>take
<w PNP>it <w CJS-PRP>for <w VVD-VVN>granted
<c PUN>.
]]></eg>

The start of each <soCalled>word</soCalled> identified by CLAWS is
      marked by an SGML <gi>w</gi> tag, which also contains the POS
      code or codes allocated to it. The start of each
      <soCalled>sentence</soCalled> is similarly marked by an SGML
      <gi>s</gi> element, carrying the sentence number of this
      sentence within the text. SGML elements such as <gi>head</gi>
      and <gi>p</gi> are used to mark larger structural components of
      the text such as headings and paragraphs.  </p>

<p> The User
      Reference Guide (<ref target="Burnard95">Burnard 1995</ref>)
      delivered with the corpus contains a detailed discussion of the
      scope and significance of this markup system. As the above
      example shows, it relies on the minimization features of SGML to
      reduce the quantity of markup: in XML, which lacks this
      facility, the last few words of the above example would read:

<eg><![CDATA[
... <w type="VVI">take</w> <w type="PNP">it</w> 
<w type="CJS-PRP">for</w> <w type="VVD-VVN">granted</w><c type="PUN">.
</s>
]]></eg>

representing an additional overhead of approximately 10 bytes per
 token, or approximately 1000 Mb for the whole corpus — not an
 attractive thought, even with plummeting disk space prices and
 increasingly effective compression algorithms.
</p>

<p>In marking up the spoken part of the corpus, many different
    technical issues had to be addressed. As noted above, this was the
    first time SGML markup of transcribed speech on such a scale had
    been attempted. The transcription itself was carried out by staff
    who were not linguistically trained (but who were however familiar
    with the regional variation being transcribed — staff
    recruited in Essex for example were not required to transcribe
    material recorded in Northern Ireland). Transcribers added a
    minimal (non-SGML) kind of markup to the text, which was then
    normalized, converted to SGML, and validated by special purpose
    software (see further <ref target="Burnage">Burnage
    1993</ref>). The markup scheme made explicit a number of features,
    including changes of speaker and quite detailed overlap; the words
    used, as perceived by the transcriber; indications of false
    starts, truncation, uncertainty; some performance features
    e.g. pausing, stage directions etc.  In addition, of course,
    detailed demographic and other information about each speaker and
    each speech context was recorded in the appropriate part of the
    Header, where this was available.
   </p>

<p>Here is a sample from a transcribed spoken text:

<eg><![CDATA[

<u who=PS04Y>
<s n=01296><w ITJ>Mm <pause> <w ITJ>yes <pause dur=7>
<w PNP>I <w VVD>told <w NP0>Paul <pause>
<w CJT>that <w PNP>he <w VM0>can <w VVI>bring
<w AT0>a <w NN1>lady <w AVP>up <pause> <w PRP>at
<w NN1>Christmas-time<c PUN>.</u>
<u who=PS04U>
<s n=01297><w VBZ>Is <w PNP>he <w XX0>not
<w VVG>going <w AV0>home <w AV0>then<c PUN>?</u>
<u who=PS04Y>
<s n=01298><w ITJ>No <pause dur=8> <w CJC>and
<w UNC>erm <pause dur=7> <w PNP>I<w VBB>'m
<w VVG>leaving <w AT0>a <w NN1>turkey <w PRP>in
<w AT0>the <w NN1>freezer
<event desc="kettle boils">
<s n=01299><w NP0>Paul <w VBZ>is <w AV0>quite
<w AJ0>good <w PRP>at <w NN1-VVG>cooking <pause>
<w AJ0>standard <w NN1>cooking<c PUN>.</u>
]]></eg>
   </p>
<p>Words and sentences are tagged as in the written example
      above. However, sentences are now grouped into
      <term>utterances</term>, marked by the SGML <gi>u</gi> element,
      each representing an unbroken stretch of speech, and containing
      withing its start tag a code (such as <ident>PS04Y</ident>)
      which acts as a key to access the more detailed information
      about the speaker
      recorded in the TEI Header for this text. Note also the
      <gi>pause</gi> and <gi>event</gi> elements used to mark
      paralinguistic features of the transcribed speech. 
     </p>

     <p>As can readily be seen in the above example, the intention of
     the transcribers was to provide a version of the speech which was
     closer to writing than to unmediated audio signal. Thus, the
     spelling of filled pauses such as <mentioned>erm</mentioned> or
     <mentioned>mmm</mentioned> is normalised, and there is even use
     of conventional punctuation to mark intonation patterns
     interpreted as questions. For more discussion of the rationale
     behind this and other aspects of the speech transcription see
     <ref target="Crowdy94">Crowdy 1994</ref>. </p>

</div2>


<div2><head>Software and distribution</head>

<p>In 1994, it was not entirely obvious how one should distribute a corpus the
    size of the BNC on a not-for-profit basis. Low-cost options such
    as anonymous ftp seemed precluded by the scale of the
    data. Our initial policy was to distribute the text compressed to
    the extent that it would fit on a set of three CDs,
    together with some simple software system which could be installed by
    suitably skilled personnel to provide departmental access over a
    network to the local copy of the corpus. Development of such a
    software system was undertaken, with the aid of additional funding
    from the British Library, during the last year of the project. The
    software, named SARA (for SGML Aware Retrieval Application), has
    since been further developed as discussed below, but remains
    essentially unchanged in its mode of usage: in particular, it
    remains a client-server application, not well suited to small
    memory-intensive operations.</p>

<p>It was always intended that access to the BNC should not be
    contingent on the use of any particular software  —
    this was after all the main rationale behind the use of the
    international standard SGML as a means of encoding the corpus,
    rather than a system tailored to any particular software tool. To
    demonstrate this software independence, a small (two million word)
    extract from the corpus was also produced which included with it
    on a single CD customised versions of three other software
    systems: Mike Scott's WordSmith, Oliver Mason's Qwick, and the
    Corpus Workbench software developed at Stuttgart, as well as an
    enhanced version of SARA. This <soCalled>BNC Sampler</soCalled>
    proved very popular in introducing the BNC to a wider audience; it
also clearly demonstrated that there was a large demand for such corpora in 
standalone  computing environments, such as individual desktop machines. </p>

<p>As noted above, the BNC dates from the pre-World Wide Web era.
    <note place="foot">The phrase <mentioned>world wide
    web</mentioned> in fact appears only twice in the corpus, in both
    cases as part of a brief exchange about the feasibility of
    publicizing the Leeds United football club which occurred on an
    email discussion list in January 1994. The most frequent
    collocates for the word <mentioned>web</mentioned> in the corpus
    are <mentioned>spider</mentioned>, <mentioned>tangled</mentioned>,
    <mentioned>complex</mentioned>, and
    <mentioned>seamless</mentioned>. In this respect at least the BNC
    is definitely no longer an accurate reflection of the English
    language.</note> However, within a year of its publication, it was
    apparent that web access would be the ideal way of making it
    available, if only because this would enable us to provide a
    service to researchers outside the European Union, who were still
    at this time unable to obtain copies of the corpus itself because
    of licencing restrictions. The British Library generously offered
    the project a server for this purpose, and a simple web interface
    to the corpus was developed. This service, still available at the
    address <ref>http://sara.natcorp.ox.ac.uk</ref> allows anyone to
    perform basic searches of the corpus, with a restricted range of
    display options; those wishing for more sophisticated facilities
    can also download a copy of the SARA client program to access the
    same server: a small registration fee is charged for continued use
    of the service beyond an initial trial period. </p>

<p>To complement this service, and in response to the demand for help
    in using the BNC from the language teaching community, a detailed
    tutorial guide (<ref target="Aston">Aston 1999</ref>) was written, introducing the various facilities of
    the software in the form of focussed and linguistically-motivated
    exercises.  The Online service
    remains very popular, receiving several thousand queries each month.
      </p>
<!--<p><figure><head>BNC Online accesses per month (1999-2000)</head></figure>
      </p>
--><p>Further evidence of the benefits of the software-independent
      approach taken in designing the corpus is provided by the
      success of the BNCweb project at the University of Zurich (<ref
      target="Hoffman">Lehmann 1999</ref>), which has developed an entirely
      web-based approach to searching the BNC using the SARA server as
      a back end together with a database of associated word-frequency
      data. </p>
</div2>
</div1>

<div1><head>The BNC World Edition</head>

<p>The much-delayed BNC World Edition (also known as BNC2) was
     published in December 1999, five years after the first appearance
     of the BNC. A small number (less than 50) texts for which world
     rights could not be obtained were removed from the corpus so that
     it could, at last, be distributed worldwide.</p>

<p>Desirable though it might be, the scale of the BNC precludes any
complete proof reading of it. The BNC's function as a snapshot of
British English in the mid-nineties also precludes adding more
material to it.  Nevertheless, we were able to make several revisions
and corrections, described briefly below. In preparing this new
edition, we were also able to catch up with standards established
after (and to some extent by) the BNC itself, and to provide a new
enhanced version of SARA. </p>

<p>Despite the growing popularity of XML the BNC World Edition is still in SGML, for reasons referred to
 above, but the DTD it uses is now TEI-conformant, and there is
 a section in the manual which defines formally its relationship with
both the published TEI specification, and its derivative Corpus Encoding
 Scheme (<ref target="Ide">Ide 1996</ref>). In practice, the differences are very slight — a
 few elements have different names, and the content model used by the
 BNC is simpler and more restrictive than that of CES. Although the
 text remain in SGML, the headers of the World Edition are now
 expressed in XML, which means that they can be processed by standard
 XML software to create for example an XML database.
	     </p>

<p>Trying to correct the errors in the
 BNC is not unlike the task of sweeping a beach clear of sand, as imagined by the Walrus and the Carpenter:
<q rend="display"><l>"If seven maids with seven mops swept it for half a year</l>
<l>Do you suppose," the Walrus said, "that they would get it clear?"</l>
<l>"I doubt it," said the Carpenter and shed a heavy tear.</l>
</q>

There is a sense in which any transcription of spoken text is
inevitably indeterminate. Even for written texts deciding what
counts as an error is not always obvious: mis-spelled words do appear
     in published material, and should therefore also be expected to
     appear in a corpus. Where corrections have been made during the
     process of corpus construction, they are sometimes noted in the
     markup in such a way as to preserve both the original error and
     its correction: this provides some indication at least of the
     kinds of error likely to be encountered. However, it is
     impossible reliably to assess the extent of such errors, nor
     precisely to locate their origin, because of the varied processes
     carried out on the source texts. In principle, it is impossible
     to distinguish an error introduced by (for example) inaccurate
     OCR software from an error which was present in the original,
     without doing an exact proof reading of the text against its
     original source<note place="foot">Such a task would however be feasible, since the
      original paper sources for the majority of the written parts of
      the corpus is still preserved at OUCS</note>; the
     use of automatic spelling-error detection software also somewhat
     muddies the water. 
	     </p>

<p>One kind of systematic correction is however possible, and has been
 applied. In part because of the availability of the BNC
 Sampler, it was possible to improve greatly the rules used by CLAWS,
 and thus to significantly reduce both the error rate and the degree
 of indeterminacy in the POS codes for BNC world. This work, carried
 out at Lancaster with funding from the Engineering and Physical
 Sciences Research Council (Research Grant No. GR/F 99847), is
 described in detail in the Manual supplied with the corpus (<ref
 target="Leech20">Leech 2000</ref>), which estimates that the error
 rate in the whole corpus following the automatic procedures applied
 is now reduced to approximately 1.15 percent of all words, while the
 proportion of ambiguous codes is now reduced to approximately 3.75
 per cent<note place="foot">These estimates are derived from manual inspection of a
 50,000 word sample taken from the whole corpus, as further discussed
 in the Tagging Manual cited.</note> </p>

<p>At the same time, a number of semi-systematic errors were
 fixed. These ranged from duplicate or wrongly labelled texts to a
 complete check of the demographic data associated with the speakers
 in each text, which had been found to contain many errors in BNC1. In
 addition, we were able to include the results of a systematic
 investigation of the text classifications carried out at Lancaster
 (reported in <ref target="Lee">Lee 2001</ref>); this means that each
 text now carries not only a somewhat more reliable version of its
 original classification criteria, but also a completely new
 classification carried out in terms of a more delicate taxonomy
 defined by Lee for the corpus.  Similarly, whereas in BNC-1 a rather
 unsystematic method had been employed to associate descriptive topic
 keywords with each text, in the new version, each written text has
 additionally been given the set of descriptive keywords associated
 with it in standard library catalogues.<note place="foot">These were obtained from
 the UK joint COPAC for the bulk of the written published
 material</note> The typos, however remain... and will continue to do so!</p>

<p>The new version of SARA distributed with the BNC World has five
important new features, four of them suggested by user feedback on the
original version. It is now possible to define subcorpora, using the
improved classification codes for example, though this is not the only
method. It is possible to carry out proper collocation analyses:
finding (for example) all the words that collocate with a given
term. It is possible to perform lemmatized searches, for example
finding all morphologically related forms of a given word. And perhaps
most important, the new version of SARA can be used with any
TEI-conformant corpus. More information on each of these facilities,
together with practical information on how to install and use the new
version is available from the website
<ref>http://www.hcu.ox.ac.uk/SARA</ref>. </p> <p>The fifth new
feature of this release of the BNC is a consequence of the changing
technical environment in which the corpus is now used. It is simply
that the corpus can now be installed at low cost for personal use on a
single standalone workstation running any version of the Windows
operating system. This continues the trend initiated by the
development of the BNC Online service towards making the corpus more
accessible to a wider community of users.
     </p>
     </div1>

<div1><head>What lessons have we learned?</head>

<p>Everyone knows you should research the market before distributing
any kind of project, especially one with the level of initial
investment needed by the BNC. But, as with some other things that
everyone knows, this common-sense wisdom turns out to have been somewhat
misleading in the case of the BNC. When the original project
partners discussed the likely market for copies of the BNC, it seemed
quite clear where and how small it would be. In the mid-nineties, it was
obvious that only a specialist research community, with a clear focus
on Natural Language Processing, and of course the research and
development departments of businesses engaged in NLP or in
lexicography would be in the least interested in a 100 million word
collection of English in what was then still called machine-readable
form. Both the rights framework for distribution of copies of the
corpus and the methods of distribution chosen clearly reflect this
<soCalled>obvious</soCalled> model: the licence which all would-be
purchasers must sign (in duplicate) for example talks about the
licensees's <q>research group</q> and is quite belligerent about the
need to monitor networked usage of the corpus within an institution
— but nowhere entertains the notion that an individual might buy
a copy for their own personal use, or for use with a group of
students. </p>


<p>In fact however, we rapidly discovered that the market was both
much larger, and quite different in nature. The major users of the BNC
turn out to be people working in applied linguistics, not
computational linguistics, and in particular those concerned with
language learning and teaching. Their computational expertise is rather
less than expected, their enthusiasms more wide-ranging. They include not only
computational linguists and NLP researchers but also cultural historians and even language learners.
	   </p>

<p>In retrospect, the BNC project also had the same technological
    blind spots as others at the time. Curiously, we did not expect the
    success of the XML revolution!  So we wasted time in format
    conversion and compromises. Equally, because we did not foresee
    standalone computers running at 1 Ghz with 20 gigabyte disks as
    standard home equipment, we did not anticipate that it might one
    day be feasible to store the digital audio version of the texts we
    transcribed along with their transcriptions.  Consequently, we
    never even considered whether it would be useful to try to get
    rights to distribute the digital audio, and our software
    development efforts focussed on developing a client/server
    application, a system predicated on the assumption that BNC usage
    would be characterized by a single shared computing resource, with
    many entry points, rather than by the massive duplication of
    standalone machines. </p>

<p>What other opportunities did we miss? In the original design, there
    is a clearly discernible shift from the notion of
    <soCalled>Representativeness</soCalled> to the idea of the BNC as
    a <term>fonds</term>: a source of specialist corpora. From being a
    sample of the whole of language, the BNC was rapidly re-positioned
    as a repository of language variety. This was in retrospect a
    sensible repositioning; a more divers collection of materials than
    the BNC is hard to imagine. Handling this diversity effectively
    however requires a clearer and better agreed taxonomy of text
    types than currently exists, and better access facilities for
    subcorpora. The BNC World edition tries to address this need by
    expanding the provision of classificatory data attached to each
    text. However, although the encoding scheme adopted  allows for the
    addition of any number of arbitrary classifications for each text
    (or, indeed, for each textual component), there still remains the
    disagreeable necessity of first defining and then applying such
    classications by hand in a consistent and defensible manner. A
    rapid scan of most corpus-related discussion lists shows that
    close to the top of most frequently asked question lists is a
    question of the form <q>I am looking for a collection of texts of
    type X</q> (recent values for X I have noticed include
    doctor-patient interaction, legal debate, arguments,
    flirtation...); in almost every case, the answer to such a request
    is <q>There is some, somewhere in the BNC, but it's up to you to
    find it...</q>.</p>

<p>Clearly, the design of the BNC entirely missed the opportunity to
    set up a grand monitor corpus, one which could watch the river of
    language flow and change across time. It is a rather depressing
    thought that linguists of this century may continue to study the
    language of the nineties for as long as those of the preceding one
    were constrained to study that of the sixties. It would be
    interesting, of course, to build a series of BNC-like corpora at
    regular intervals, say every decade, if only there were an
    unlimited supply of funding for such an enterprise. Instead,
    however, we will have a different kind of large scale corpus of
    language production at our disposal for at least the foreseeable
    future. How best to manage the diversity and unpredictability of
    the Web as our future source of linguistic information is another,
    and quite different, story.
   </p>

   </div1>
   <div1><head>Works cited</head>
<listBibl>

<bibl xml:id="Aston">Aston, G. and Burnard, L. (1998),  <title
       level="m">The BNC handbook: exploring the British National
       Corpus with SARA</title>. Edinburgh: Edinburgh University
       Press.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Atkins92">Atkins, B.T.S., Clear, J., and Ostler, N. (1992),
<title level="a">Corpus Design Criteria</title>, <title level="s">Literary and Linguistic
Computing,</title> 7, pp. 1-16.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Atkins94">Atkins, B.T.S., and Zampolli, A. (1994) eds. <title>Computational
Approaches to the Lexicon</title>, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Burnage">Burnage, G. and  Dunlop, D. (1992) <title level="a">Encoding
the British National Corpus</title> in Aarts et al, eds.
<title>English language corpora: design, analysis and
exploitation</title> Amsterdam: Rodopi, pp 79-95 </bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Burnard95">Burnard, L. (1995) ed. <title>Users' Reference
Guide for the British National Corpus, version 1.0</title>. Oxford:
Oxford University Computing Services.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Burnard">Burnard, L. (1999) <title level="a">Using SGML for linguistic
       analysis: the case of the BNC</title> in <title
       level="s">Markup languages theory and practice</title>. I.2
      pp. 31-51. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press. Also published in
       <title>Maschinelle Verarbeitung altdeitscher Texte V</title>,
       pp 53-72. Tuebingen: Max Niemeyer, 2001.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Carpenter">Carpenter, L., Shaw, S., and Prescott,
      A. (1998), eds.  <title>Towards the Digital Library: the
      British Library's Initiatives for Access programme</title>
      London: British Library. </bibl>


<bibl xml:id="Clear">Clear, J. H. (1993) <title level="a">The British National
Corpus</title> in Delany, P. and Landow, G., ed. <title>The
Digital Word : text-based computing in the
humanities</title>. Cambridge (Mass), MIT Press, pp. 163-187. </bibl>


<bibl xml:id="Crowdy94">Crowdy, S. (1994) <title level="a">Spoken Corpus
Transcription</title> <title level="s">Literary &amp; Linguistic
Computing</title> 9:1 (1994), pp. 25-28. </bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Crowdy95">Crowdy, S. (1995) <title level="a">The BNC spoken corpus</title>
in Leech, G., Myers, G.  and Thomas, J., eds. <title>Spoken
English on computer: transcription, mark-up and application</title>
Harlow: Longman, pp. 224-235.  </bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Dunlop">Dunlop, D. (1995) <title level="a">Practical
considerations in the use of TEI headers in large corpora</title> in
Ide, N. and Veronis, J. eds. <title>Text Encoding Initiative:
background and context</title>. Dordrecht: Kluwer, pp 85-98.  </bibl>

<bibl>Garside, R. (1995) <title level="a">Grammatical tagging of the
spoken part of the British National Corpus: a progress report</title>
in Leech, G., Myers, G. and Thomas, J. , eds. <title>Spoken English on
computer: transcription, mark-up and application</title> Harlow:
Longman, pp. 161-7.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Garside96">Garside, R. 1996. <title level="a">The robust tagging of
unrestricted text: the BNC experience</title> in Thomas, J. and Short,
M., eds. <title>Using corpora for language research: studies
in the honour of Geoffrey Leech</title> Harlow: Longman, pp.
167-180. </bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Garside97">Garside, R., Leech, G., and McEnery, T. (1997)
      <title level="a">Corpus Annotation: Linguistic Information from
      Computer Text Corpora</title> London: Longman, chapters
      7-9.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Ide">Ide, N., Priest-Dorman, G., Véronis, J. (1996)
      <title>Corpus Encoding Standard</title>. [available from
      <ref>http://www.cs.vassar.edu/CES/</ref>]</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Lee">Lee, D. (2001) <title level="a">Genres, registers, text types and styles: clarifying
the concepts and navigating a path through the BNC Jungle</title> in
<title level="s">Language Learning and Technology</title>,
      5.3. [available from <ref>http://llt.msu.edu/</ref>]</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Leech">Leech, G., Garside, R., and Bryant, M. (1994). <title
       level="a">CLAWS4: The tagging of the British National
       Corpus</title> in <title level="m">Proceedings of the 15th
       International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING
       94)</title>. Japan: Kyoto, pp. 622-628.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Leech20">Leech, G and Smith, N. (2000) <title>Manual to
       accompany The British National Corpus (Version 2) with Improved
       Word-class Tagging</title>. Lancaster: UCREL. [Supplied in
       digital form as part of the BNC World Edition].</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Hoffman">Lehmann, H., Schneider, P., Hoffmann,
       S. (1999) <title level="a">BNCweb</title> in Kirk,
       J. ed. <title>Corpora galore: analysis and techniques in
       describing English</title>. Amsterdam: Rodopi, pp. 259-266. </bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Renouf">Renouf, A. (1986) <title level="a">Corpus
       development at Birmingham University</title> in Aarts, J., and
       Meijs, W., eds. <title level="m">Corpus Linguistics II: New
       Studies in the Analysis and Exploitation of Computer
       Corpora</title>, Amsterdam: Rodopi, pp. 7-23</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Sinclair">Sinclair, J. McH. (1987) <title>Looking
       Up</title>. London: Collins.</bibl>

<bibl xml:id="TEI-P3">Sperberg-McQueen, C.M., and Burnard,
      L. (1994) <title>Guidelines for electronic text encoding and
      interchange (TEI P3). Chicago and Oxford: ACH-ALLC-ACL Text
      Encoding Initiative.</title>
     </bibl>

<bibl xml:id="Zampolli">Zampolli, A., Calzolari, N., Palmer, M. (1994) eds.
      <title level="a">Current
Issues in Computational Linguistics: In Honour of Don Walker</title>,
<title level="s">(Linguistica Computazionale IX-X)</title>. Pisa: Giardini.</bibl>


</listBibl>
   </div1>
</body></text></TEI>