<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Metadata for corpus work</title>
<author>Lou Burnard</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p>XML version for my archive</p>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Drafted in TEI P5; subsequently published as <bibl><title level="a">Metadata
for Corpus Work</title> in Martin Wynne (ed) <title level="m">Developing
Linguistic Corpora: A guide to good practice</title>. <title level="s">AHDS
Guides to Good Practice.</title>. <date>2005</date>
<idno type="isbn">1 84217 205 0</idno> Oxford: Oxbow Books, pp 30-46.
</bibl></p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date>10 aug 2014</date>LB made TEI P5 version</change>
<change><date>31 oct 04</date><name>LB</name> revised following martin's
suggestions</change>
<change><date>2 jan 04</date>LB first moderately complete draft</change>
<change><date>11 feb 03</date>LB first draft</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>

<body>
<div>
<head>What is metadata and why do you need it? <note place="foot">Originally published as <bibl><title level="a">Metadata
for Corpus Work</title> in Martin Wynne (ed) <title level="m">Developing
Linguistic Corpora: A guide to good practice</title>. <title level="s">AHDS
Guides to Good Practice</title>. ISBN  
<idno type="isbn">1 84217 205 0</idno> Oxford: Oxbow Books, <date>2005</date>, pp 30-46.</bibl></note></head>
<p>Metadata is usually defined as <q>data about data</q>. The word appears only
six times in the 100 million word British National Corpus (<ref
target="http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk">BNC</ref>), in each case as a technical
term from the domain of information processing. However, all of the material
making up the British National Corpus predates the whole-hearted adoption of
this word by the library and information science communities. Since the BNC was
first published in 1994, <q>metadata</q> has come to be used most frequently for
one very specific kind of data about data: the kind of data that is needed to
describe a digital resource in sufficient detail and with sufficient accuracy
for some agent to determine whether or not that digital resource is of relevance
to a particular enquiry. This so-called <q>discovery metadata</q> has become a
major area of concern with the expansion of the World Wide Web and other
distributed digital resources, and there have been a number of attempts to
define standard sets of metadata for specific subject domains, for specific
kinds of activity (for example, digital preservation) and more generally for
resource discovery. The most influential of the generic metadata schemes has
been the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative (<ref target="http://dublincore.org"
>DCMI</ref>), which (in 1995, the year after the BNC was first published),
proposed 15 metadata categories which it was felt would suffice to describe any
digital resource well enough for resource discovery purposes. For the
linguistics community, more specific and structured proposals include those of
the Text Encoding Initiative (<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org">TEI</ref>), the
Open Language Archive Community (<ref target="http://www.language-archives.org"
>OLAC</ref>), and the ISLE Metadata Initiative (<ref
target="http://www.mpi.nl/IMDI/">IMDI</ref>). </p>
<p>These and other initiatives have as a common goal the definition of agreed
sets of metadata categories which can be applied across many different
resources, so that potential users can assess the usefulness of those resources
for their own purposes. The theory is that in much the same way that domestic
consumers expect to find standardized labelling on their grocery items (net
weight in standard units, calorific value per 100 grams, indication of country
of origin, etc.), so the user of digital resources will expect to find a
standard set of descriptors on their data items. While there can be no doubt
that some information, however limited, about a resource is more useful than
none, and that some metadata categories are of more general interest than
others, it is far less clear on what basis or authority the definition of a
standard set of metadata descriptors should proceed. Digital resources,
particularly linguistic corpora, are designed to serve many different
applications, and their usefulness must thus be evaluated against many different
criteria. A corpus designed for use in one context may not be suited to another,
even though its description suggests that it will be.</p>
<p> Nevertheless, it is no exaggeration to say that without metadata, corpus
linguistics would be virtually impossible. Why? Because corpus linguistics is an
empirical science, in which the investigator seeks to identify patterns of
linguistic behaviour by inspection and analysis of naturally occurring samples
of language. A typical corpus analysis will therefore gather together many
examples of linguistic usage, each taken out of the context in which it
originally occurred, like a laboratory specimen. Metadata can restore that
context by supplying information about it, thus enabling us to relate the
specimen to its original habitat. Furthermore, since language corpora are
constructed from pre-existing pieces of language, questions of accuracy and
authenticity are all but inevitable when using them: without metadata, the
investigator has no way of answering such questions. Without metadata, the
investigator has nothing but disconnected words of unknowable provenance or
authenticity. </p>
<p>In many kinds of corpus analysis, the objective is to detect patterns of
linguistic behaviour which are common to particular groups of texts. Sometimes,
the analyst examines occurrences of particular linguistic phenomena across a
broad range of language samples, to see whether certain phenomena are more
characteristic of some categories of text than others. Alternatively, the
analyst may attempt to characterize the linguistic properties or regularities of
a particular pre-defined category of texts. In either case, it is the metadata
which defines the category of text; without it, we have no way of distinguishing
or grouping the component texts which make up a large heterogenous corpus, nor
even of talking about the properties of a homogenous one. </p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Scope and representation of metadata</head>
<p>Many different kinds of metadata are of use when working with language
corpora. In addition to the simplest descriptive metadata already mentioned,
which serves to identify and characterize a corpus regarded as a digital
resource, we discuss below the following categories of metadata, which are of
particular significance or use in language work: <list>
<item>editorial metadata, providing information about the relationship between
corpus components and their original source (<ptr target="#EDIT"/>)</item>
<item>analytic metadata, providing information about the way in which corpus
components have been interpreted and analysed (<ptr target="#ANAL"/>) </item>
<item>descriptive metadata, providing classificatory information derived from
internal or external properties of the corpus components (<ptr target="#HDR"
/>)</item>
<item>administrative metadata, providing documentary information about the
corpus itself, such as its title, its availability, its revision status, etc.
(this section)</item>
</list></p>
<p>In earlier times, it was customary to provide corpus metadata in a
free-standing reference manual if at all. Early corpora such as the Brown or LOB
were always accompanied by a large A4 volume of typescript. It is now more usual
to present all metadata in an integrated form, together with the corpus itself,
often using the same encoding principles or markup language. This facilitates
automatic validation of the accuracy and consistency of the documentation,
simplifies the development of user-friendly access software the data, and helps
ensure that corpus and metadata are kept together, and can be distributed as a
single unit. </p>
<p>A major influence in this respect has been the Text Encoding Inititiative
(TEI), which in 1994 first published an extensive set of Guidelines for the
Encoding of Machine Readable Data. (TEI P1). These recommendations have been
widely adopted, and form the basis of most current language resource
standardization efforts. A key feature of the TEI recommendations was the
definition of a specific metadata component known as the <term>TEI
Header</term>. </p>
<p>The TEI Header was first thought of as a kind of electronic title page, which
could be prefixed to a computer file (or a collection of such files) to supply
the same kind of information as is provided by the title page and other front
matter of a conventional book. Thus, it has four major parts, derived originally
from the International Standard Bibliographic Description (<ref
target="http://www.ifla.org/VII/s13/pubs/isbd.htm">ISBD</ref>): <list>
<item>a <term>file description</term>, identifying the computer
file<!-- note place="foot">In ISBD, the term
<term>computer file</term> is used to refer to any
computer-held object, such as a language corpus, or a component of one.</note-->
itself and those responsible for its authorship, dissemination or publication
etc., together with (in the case of a derived text such as a corpus) similar
bibliographic identification for its <term>source</term>;</item>
<item>an <term>encoding description</term>, specifying the kinds of encoding
used within the file, for example, what tags have been used, what editorial
procedures applied, how the original material was sampled, and so forth;</item>
<item>a <term>profile description</term>, supplying additional descriptive
material about the file not covered elsewhere, such as its situational
parameters, topic keywords, descriptions of participants in a spoken text
etc.</item>
<item>a <term>revision description</term>, listing all modifications made to the
file during the course of its development as a distinct object.</item>
</list></p>
<p> In this way, the TEI sought to extend the well-understood principles of
print bibliography to the (then!) new world of digital resources. The TEI
recommendations, initially expressed as an application of the Standard
Generalized Markup Language (SGML: ISO 8879), proved very influential, and have
since been re-expressed as an application of the current <foreign>de
facto</foreign> standard language of the internet: the W3C's extensible markup
language (<ref target="http://www.w3.org/XML/">XML</ref>), information on which
is readily available elsewhere.</p>
<p>The scope of this article does not permit exhaustive discussion of all
features of the TEI Header likely to be of relevance to corpus builders or
users, but some indication of the range of metadata it supports is provided by
the summary below (<ref target="#OVU"/>). For full information, consult the
online version of the TEI Guidelines (<ptr
target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/HD.html"/>), or the Corpus Encoding
Standard (<ptr target="http://www.cs.vassar.edu/CES"/>), which is a
specialization of them for corpus work. <ref target="#DUN95">Dunlop 1995</ref>
and <ref target="#BUR99">Burnard 1999</ref> describe the use of the TEI Header in
the construction of the BNC.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="EDIT">
<head>Editorial metadata</head>
<p>Because electronic versions of a non-electronic original are inevitably
subject to some form of distortion or translation, it is important to document
clearly the editorial procedures and conventions adopted. In creating and
tagging corpora, particularly large ones assembled from many sources, many
editorial and encoding compromises are necessary. The kind of detailed
text-critical attention possible for a smaller literary text may be
inappropriate, whether for methodological or financial reasons. Nevertheless,
users of a tagged corpus will not thank the encoder if arbitrary editorial
changes have been silently introduced, with no indication of where, or with what
regularity. Corpora encoded in such a way can mislead the unwary or partially
informed user. </p>
<p> A conscientious corpus builder should therefore take care to consider making
explicit in the corpus markup at least the following kinds of intervention:
<list type="gloss">
<label>addition or omission</label>
<item>where the encoder has supplied material not present in the source, or
(more frequently in corpus work) where material has been omitted from a
transcription or encoding. </item>
<label>correction</label>
<item>where the encoder has corrected material in the source which is judged
erroneous (for example, misprints);</item>
<label>normalization</label>
<item>where, although not considered erroneous, the source material exhibits a
variant form which the encoder has replaced by a standardized form.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The encoder may simply record the fact that such interventions have taken
place by making a note of this in the corpus header, possibly describing their
scope and nature. Alternatively, assuming that the corpus uses a sufficiently
powerful markup language, each such intervention may be explicitly signalled
within the encoded text. In the latter case, it may be possible to retain both
original and corrected (or normalized) form, so that the corpus user can decide
for themselves on whether or not to accept the intervention. We give some simple
examples below.</p>
<p>The explicit marking of material missing from an encoded text may be of
considerable importance as a means of indicating where non-linguistic (or
linguistically intractable) items such as symbols or diagrams or tables have
been omitted: <eg>&lt;gap desc="diagram"/></eg> Such markup is useful where the
effort involved in a more detailed transcription (using more specific elements
such as <gi>figure</gi> or <gi>table</gi>, or even detailed markup such as SVG
or mathml) is not considered worthwhile. It is also useful where material has
been omitted for sampling reasons, so as to alert the user to the dangers of
using such partial transcriptions for analysis of text-grammar features:
<eg>&lt;div type="chapter"> &lt;gap extent="100 sentences" cause="sampling
strategy"/> &lt;s>This is not the first sentence in this chapter.&lt;/s></eg>
</p>
<p>As these examples demonstrate, the tagging of a corpus text encoded in XML is
itself a special and powerful form of metadata, instructing the user how to
interpret and reliably use the data. For example, in transcribing a spoken
English text, a word that sounds like `skuzzy' is encountered by a transcriber
who does not recognize this as one way of pronouncing the common abbreviation
`SCSI' (small computer system interface). The transcriber might simply encode
his or her uncertainty by marking an omission in the following way: <eg>&lt;gap
extent="two syllables" cause="unrecognizable word"></eg>
</p>
<p>Alternatively, the transcriber might wish to allow for the possibility of
`skuzzy' as a lexical item while registering doubts as to its correctness:
<eg>&lt;sic>skuzzy&lt;/sic> </eg></p>
<p>Now consider the case where the transcriber finds in the source something
that clearly reads <q>wierd stuff</q>. Again, the transcriber can simply flag
that this is probably an error: <eg>&lt;sic>wierd&lt;/sic> stuff</eg> Or they
might decide both to correct the error and also to record that they have done
so: <eg>&lt;corr>weird&lt;/corr> stuff</eg>. </p>
<p>Corrections of orthographic error like this help the corpus user find word
forms even when they happen to have been mis-spelled. On the other hand, such
corrections are a little annoying for the corpus user who is interested in the
study of orthographic error itself. For such users, an ideal encoding would
preserve both the error and its correction, perhaps like this: <eg>&lt;choice>
&lt;sic>wierd&lt;/sic> &lt;corr>weird&lt;/corr> &lt;/choice> stuff</eg>
</p>
<p>The same range of possibilities might be needed in the treatment of handling
of historical, regional, or other kinds of variant forms. For example, in modern
British English, contracted forms such as `isn't' exhibit considerable regional
variation, with forms such as `isnae', `int' or `ain't' being quite
orthographically acceptable in certain contexts. An encoder might thus choose
any of the following to represent the Scots form `isnae':
<eg>&lt;reg>isn't&lt;/reg> &lt;orig>isnae&lt;/orig> &lt;choice>
&lt;reg>isn't&lt;/reg> &lt;orig>isnae&lt;/orig> &lt;/choice></eg>
</p>
<p>Which of these different encoding styles will be appropriate is a function of
the intentions and policies of the encoder: these, and other aspects of the
encoding policy, should be stated explicitly in the corpus documentation, or the
appropriate section of the encoding description section of a TEI Header.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="ANAL">
<head>Analytic metadata</head>
<p>A corpus may consist of nothing but sequences of orthographic words and
punctuation, sometime known as <term>plain text</term>. But, as we have seen,
even deciding on which words make up a text is not entirely unproblematic. Texts
have many other features worthy of attention and analysis. Some of these are
structural features such as text, text subdivision, paragraph or utterance
divisions, which it is the function of a markup system to make explicit, and
concerning which there is generally little controversy. Other features are
however (in principle at least) recognizable only by human intelligence, since
they result from an understanding of the text.</p>
<p>Corpus-builders do not in general have the leisure to read and manually tag
the majority of their materials; detailed distinctions must therefore be made
either automatically or not at all (and the markup should make explicit which
was the case!). In the simplest case, a corpus builder may be able reliably to
encode only the visually salient features of a written text such as its use of
italic font or emphasis. In documents produced by modern word processors
particular combinations of such features may be encoded in the document as
<q>style</q> markers, which can easily be automatically converted to a more
semantically useful markup. Similarly, a more explicit markup (for example, of
sentences) might be derived by the application of probabilistic rules derived
from surface features such as punctuation, capitalization, and white space
usage. </p>
<p>At a later stage, or following the development of suitably intelligent tools,
it may be possible to review the elements which have been marked as visually
highlighted, and assign a more specific interpretive textual function to them.
Examples of the range of textual functions of this kind include quotation,
foreign words, linguistic emphasis, mention rather than use, titles, technical
terms, glosses, etc. </p>
<p>The performance of such tools as morpho-syntactic taggers may occasionally be
improved by pre-identification of these, and of other kinds of textual features
which are not normally visually salient, such as names, addresses, dates,
measures, etc. It remains debatable whether effort is better spent on improving
the ability of such tools to handle any text, or on improving the performance of
pre-tagging tools. Such tagging has other uses however: for example, once names
have been recognized, it becomes possible to attach normalized values for their
referents to them, thus facilitating development of systems which can link all
references to the same individual by different names. This kind of <term>named
entity recognition</term> is of particular interest in the development of
message understanding and other Natural Language Processing (NLP) systems. </p>
<p>The process of encoding or tagging a corpus is best regarded as the process
of making explicit a set of more or less interpretive judgments about the
material of which it is composed. Where the corpus is made up of reasonably well
understood material (e.g. contemporary newspaper texts), it is reasonably easy
to distinguish such interpretive judgments from apparently objective assertions
about its structural properties, and hence convenient to represent them in a
formally distinct way. Where corpora are made up of less well understood
materials (for example, in ancient scripts or languages), the distinction
between structural and analytic properties becomes less easy to maintain. Just
as, according to some theories, a text triggers meaning but does not embody it,
so a text triggers multiple encodings, each of equal formal validity, if not
utility.</p>
<p><term>Linguistic annotation</term> of almost any kind may be attached to
components at any level from the whole text to individual words or morphemes. At
its simplest, such annotation allows the analyst to distinguish between
orthographically similar sequences (for example, whether the word `Pat' at the
beginning of a sentence is a proper name, a verb, or an adjective), and to group
orthographically dissimilar ones (such as the negatives `not' and `-n't'). In
the same way, it may be convenient to specify the base or lemmatized version of
a word as an alternative for its inflected forms explicitly, (for example to
show that `is', `was' `being' etc. are all forms of the same verb), or to
regularize variant orthographic forms, (for example, to indicate in a historical
text that `morrow', `morwe' and `morrowe' are all forms of the same word). More
complex annotation will use similar methods to capture one or more syntactic or
morphological analyses, or to represent such matters as the thematic or
discourse structure of a text.</p>
<p> Corpus work requires a modular approach in which basic text structures are
overlaid with a variety of such annotations. These may be thought of as a
distinct layers or levels, or as a complex network of descriptive pointers, and
a variety of encoding techniques may be used to express them. Ideas from
mathematics, formal language theory, and computer science have been particularly
influential in the development of techniques for this purpose, for example in
RDF or <q>annotation graphs</q>; most such techniques rely on the use of XML as
their basic means of expression however. We discuss some of the implications of
this in the next section. </p>
<div xml:id="SEGCAT">
<head>Categorization</head>
<p>In the TEI and other XML markup schemes, a corpus component may be
categorized in a number of different ways. At the simplest level, its category
is explicitly stated by the XML tag used to delimit it: a <q>text</q> is
everything found between the start-tag <gi>text</gi> and the end-tag
<tag>/text</tag>; a <q>sentence</q> within that text is everything found between
the start-tag <gi>s</gi> and the end-tag <tag>/s</tag>, and so on. An element
may also have an implied categorization, derived from information in the header
associated it (see further <ptr target="#HDR"/>), or inherited from a parent
element occurrence, or explicitly assigned by an appropriate attribute. The
latter case is the more widely used, but we begin by discussing some aspects of
the former.</p>
<p>If we say that a text is a <term>newspaper</term> or a <term>novel</term>, it
is self-evident that journalistic or novelistic properties respectively are
inherited by all the components making up that text. In the same way, any
structural division of an XML-encoded text can specify a value which is
understood to apply to all elements within it. As an example, consider a corpus
composed of small ads which are grouped into sections, each section having a
distinguishing heading: <eg>&lt;adSection> &lt;s>For sale&lt;/s> &lt;ad>
&lt;s>Large French chest available ... &lt;/s> &lt;/ad> &lt;ad> &lt;s>Pair of
skis, one careful owner...&lt;/s> &lt;/ad> &lt;/adSection></eg>
</p>
<p>In this example, the element <gi>s</gi> has been used to enclose all the
textual parts of a corpus, irrespective of their function. However, an XML
processor is able to distinguish <gi>s</gi> elements appearing in different
contexts, and can thus distinguish occurrences of words which appear directly
inside an <gi>adSection</gi> (such as <q>for sale</q>) from those which appear
nested within an <gi>ad</gi> (such as <q>large French chest</q>). In this way,
the XML markup provides both syntax and semantics for corpus analysis.</p>
<p>Attribute values may be used in the same way, to assert properties for the
elements to which they are attached, and for their children. For example:
<eg>&lt;div type="section" lang="FRA"> &lt;head>Section en français&lt;/head>
&lt;s xml:id="S1">Cette phrase est en français.&lt;/s> &lt;s
xml:id="S2">Celle-ci également.&lt;/s>/div> &lt;div type="section"
lang="ENG">&lt;head>English Section /head> &lt;s xml:id="S3">This sentence is in
English.&lt;/s> &lt;s xml:id="S4">As is this one.&lt;/s> &lt;s xml:id="S5"
lang="FRA">Celle-ci est en français.&lt;/s> &lt;s xml:id="S6">This one is
not.&lt;/s> &lt;/div> </eg>
</p>
<p>An XML application can correctly identify which sentences are in which
language here, by following an algorithm such as <q>the language of an
<gi>s</gi> element is given by its <code>lang</code> attribute, or (if no lang
is specified) by that of the nearest parent element on which it is
specified</q>.</p>
<p>As noted above, many linguistic features are inherent to the structure and
organization of the text, indeed inseparable from it. A common requirement
therefore is to associate an interpretive category with one or more elements at
some level of the hierarchy. The most typical use of this style of markup is as
a vehicle for representation of linguistic annotation, such as morphosyntactic
code or root forms. For example: <eg>&lt;s ana="NP"> &lt;w ana="VVD"
lemma="analyse">analysed&lt;/w> &lt;w ana="NN2" lemma="corpus">corpora&lt;/w>
&lt;/s></eg>
</p>
<p>From a formal point of view, XML is a simple kind of labelled bracketting,
which represents the structure of a document as a hierarchy in which each
component fits neatly inside another so that the whole document can be regarded
as a singly-rooted tree. However, it is often the case that the analytic
structures to be represented do not conform to this model. For example, a spoken
text might be analysed as in terms of its syntactic structure (clauses, phrases
etc.) or in terms of its performance structure (turns, back-channelling, etc).
As soon as one person interrupts another, or completes another's sentences, it
becomes impossible to represent both structures within a single hierarchy. </p>
<p>A number of XML techniques have been developed to facilitate the
representation of multiple hierarchies, most notably
<soCalled>standoff</soCalled> markup, in which the categorizing tags are not
embedded within the text stream (as in the examples above) but in a distinct
data stream, linked to locations within the actual text stream by means of
hypertext style pointers. This technique enables multiple independent analyses
to be represented, at the expense of some additional complexity in programming.
</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Validation of categories</head>
<p>A major advantage of using a formal language such as XML to represent
analytic annotation within a text is its support for automatic validation. By
this, we mean specifically checking that the annotation used in a document
conforms to a previously-defined model of which kinds of annotation are
permitted, and in which contexts. Checking that the annotation has been
<emph>correctly</emph> applied, i.e. that for example the thing tagged as a foo
actually <emph>is</emph> a foo, is not in general an automatable process since
it depends on human judgment, and we do not consider it further here. Where the
annotation is represented by means of specific XML elements, the XML system
itself can validate the markup, using a <term>schema</term> or <term>document
type declaration</term>. Validation of attribute values or element content
requires additional processing, for which analytic metadata is particularly
important.</p>
<p>As an example, consider the following markup: <eg>&lt;s>&lt;w
type="VVD">analysed&lt;/w> &lt;w type="NN2">corpora&lt;/w> &lt;w
type="VV2">are&lt;/w> &lt;w type="JJ1">cool&lt;/w>.&lt;/s> </eg>
</p>
<p>An XML schema can check that <gi>w</gi> elements occur only within <gi>s</gi>
elements, and that each <gi>w</gi> element carries a <ident>type</ident>
attribute. It could also check that the values of this attribute (the codes
<code>VVD</code>
<code>NN2</code> etc.) come from some pre-defined list of legal values, perhaps
giving a gloss to each, as follows: <eg>&lt;interp xml:id="VVD" value="past
tense adjectival form of lexical verb"/> &lt;interp xml:id="NN2" value="plural
form of common noun"/></eg>
</p>
<p>The availability of this kind of metadata, even a simple list like this,
increases the sophistication of the processing that can be carried out with the
corpus, supporting both documentation and validation of the codes used. If the
analytic metadata is further enhanced to reflect the internal structure of the
analytic codes, yet more can be done.
<!--
: for
example, one could
construct a typology of word class codes along the following lines:
<eg>&lt;interpGrp xml:id="NN" value="common noun">
&lt;interp xml:id="NN1" value="singular common noun"/>
&lt;interp xml:id="NN2" value="plural common noun"/>
&lt;interpGrp></eg>
</p>
<p>The hierarchy could  obviously be extended by nesting groups of the
same kind. We might for example  mark the grouping of common (NN) and
proper (NP)  nouns in the following way:
<eg>&lt;interpGrp value="nominal">
&lt;interpGrp xml:id="NN">
&lt;interp xml:id="NN1" value="singular common noun"/>
&lt;interp xml:id="NN2" value="plural common noun"/>
&lt;/interpGrp>
&lt;interpGrp xml:id="NP">
&lt;interp xml:id="NP1" value="singular proper noun"/>
&lt;interp xml:id="NP2" value="plural proper noun"/>
&lt;/interpGrp>&lt;/interpGrp></eg>
</p>-->
For example, one could unbundle the morpho-syntactic codes used here by
regarding them as a set of typed <term>feature structures</term>, a popular
linguistic formalism which is readily expressed in XML. This approach permits an
XML processor automatically to identify linguistic analyses where features such
as number or properness are marked, independently of the actual category code
(the <code>NN1</code> or <code>NP2</code>) used to mark the analysis. </p>
</div>
</div>
<div xml:id="HDR">
<head>Descriptive metadata</head>
<p>The social context (that is, the place, time, and participants) within which
each of the language samples making up a corpus was produced or received is
arguably at least as significant as any of its intrinsic linguistic properties —
if indeed the two can be entirely distinguished. In large corpora which sample
language characteristic of many different social contexts such as the BNC, it is
of considerably more importance to be able to identify with confidence such
information as the mode of production or publication or reception, the type or
genre of writing or speech, the social class or occupation, gender, or age of
the producers or recipients of the speech, and so on. Even in smaller or more
narrowly focussed corpora, such variables and a clear identification of the
domain which they are intended to typify are of major importance for comparative
work.</p>
<p>At the very least, a corpus text should indicate its provenance, (i.e. the
original material from which it derives) with sufficient accuracy that the
source can be located and checked against its corpus version. Existing
bibliographic descriptions are easily found for conventionally published
materials such as books or articles and the same or similar conventions should
be applied to other materials. In either case, the goal is simple: to provide
enough information for someone to be able to locate an independent copy of the
source from which the corpus text derives. Because such works have an existence
independent of their inclusion in the corpus, it is possible not only to verify
but also to extend their descriptive metadata.</p>
<p>For fugitive or spoken material, where the source may not be so easily
identified and is less likely to be preserved independently of the corpus, this
is less feasible. It is correspondingly important that the metadata recorded for
such materials should be as extensive as feasible. When transcribing spoken
material, for example, such features as the place and time of recording, the
demographic characteristics of speakers and hearers, the social context and
setting etc. are of immense value to the analyst, and cannot easily be gathered
retrospectively. </p>
<p> The text-type or genre labels used in a given corpus may sometimes be drawn
from an open ended set, but it is also convenient for them to be taken from a
predefined set of values, or <term>taxonomy</term>. Sometimes both approaches
may be taken: for example in the BNC, each text is associated with an open ended
set of descriptive keywords relating to its subject matter and also with one of
a set of pre-defined <q>domain</q> codes. Thus, text B1G in the BNC baby corpus,
which is an extract from a textbook on Geographical Information Systems,
contains (amongst other things) the following information in its header: <eg>
&lt;catRef target="alltim3 acad wriase0 wridom3 wrista2 "/> &lt;classCode
scheme="DLee">W ac soc science&lt;/classCode> &lt;keywords scheme="COPAC">
&lt;term>Geography - Methodology - Addresses, essays, lectures&lt;/term>
&lt;term> Geographical information systems.&lt;/term> &lt;term> Geography -
Computer programs&lt;/term> &lt;/keywords> </eg> The first line here indicates
how the text is classified according to the classification defined for the whole
corpus, and consists of a series of codes (<code>alltim3</code>,
<code>acad</code>, etc.) each of which is further defined in the corpus header.
The second line indicates how the text was classified in a scheme defined by
David Lee for the BNC as a whole, again using predefined codes such as
<code>W</code> for written, <code>ac</code> for academic prose etc. The
remaining part of the example however shows how the source text is classified by
the COPAC (a major UK online library catalogue), using a sequence of descriptive
cataloguing terms.</p>
<p>When a corpus is constructed according to a pre-defined set of selection
criteria, as was the BNC, it is essential to provide both definitions of the
criteria concerned and an indication of which criteria apply to each text, but
even where this is not the case, documentation and definition of any
classification scheme used is essential if the user is to make full use of the
material.</p>
<p>It will rarely be the case that a corpus uses more than one reference or
segmentation scheme. However, it will often be the case that a corpus is
constructed using more than one editorial policy or sampling procedure and it is
almost invariably the case that each corpus text has a different source or
particular combination of text-descriptive features or topics. To cater for this
variety, the TEI scheme allows for contextual information to be defined at a
number of different levels. Information relating, either to all texts, or
potentially to any number of texts within a corpus is held in the overall corpus
header, while information relating either to the whole of a single text, or to
potentially any of its subdivisions, should be held in a single text header.</p>
<p>It is also often necessary to classify textual components smaller than the
whole of a text. For example, in transcriptions of spoken language, it is often
desirable to identify speech produced by particular individuals, for example to
distinguish the speech of women and men, or of members of different
socio-economic groups. Here the key concept is the provision of a means by which
information about individual speakers can be recorded once for all in the header
of the texts they speak. For each speaker, a set of elements defining a range of
such variables as age, social class, sex etc. might be defined and grouped
together within a <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> element, like the following: <eg><![CDATA[
<person xml:id="S1">
  <occupation>student</occupation>
  <sex>male</sex>
  <ageGroup>15-20</ageGroup>
</person>
<person xml:id="T3">
  <occupation>instructor</occupation>
  <sex>female</sex>
  <ageGroup>30-35</ageGroup>
</person>
]]></eg> Within the body of the text, each utterance can then identify its
speaker using the identifiying code given as the value of the <ident>id</ident>
attribute above: <eg><![CDATA[
<u who="T3">Good morning class</u>
<u who="S1">I didn't do it</u>
]]></eg> The <code>who</code> attribute supplied on each <code>&lt;u&gt;</code>
element is sufficient to identify which speaker is concerned. To select
utterances by speakers according to specified participant criteria (for example
to find all male speech, or all speech by an instructor in a specific age
group), the equivalent of a relational join between utterance and participant
must be performed, using the value of this identifier. This method simplifies
the encoding of the text, since there is no need to supply (say) age or sex
information for each utterance, and also makes it extensible: if a new category
of information becomes available about a given speaker, it need only be added to
the <gi>speaker</gi> element for it to be usable in queries across the whole
existing corpus. </p>
<p>The same method might be used to select speech within particular social
contexts or settings, given the existence in the header of a
<code>&lt;settingDesc&gt;</code> element defining the various contexts in which
speech is recorded, which can be referenced by the <code>decls</code> attribute
attached to an element enclosing all speech recorded in a particular setting.
For example, a text or corpus header might contain entries like the following: <eg><![CDATA[<settingDesc>
  <setting type="informal" xml:id="SCA"> 
    Southside Cafe, South Quad
  </setting>
  <setting type="formal" xml:id="R11"> 
    Instructors Room, Regius Building
  </setting>
</settingDesc>
]]></eg> while each conversation transcribed in the corpus might be marked as a
distinct <gi>div</gi> element like this: <eg>&lt;div where="SCA"> &lt;u
who="T1">Skinny cap no sugar please&lt;/u> &lt;u who="XX">You got it&lt;/u>
&lt;/div> </eg> As before, the identifier <code>SCA</code> can be used to
associate the content of this <gi>div</gi> element with the metadata describing
it in the <gi>setting</gi> element, so that an XML query engine can answer
questions such as <q>is the phrase <q>skinny cap</q> used in formal or informal
sitations?</q></p>
</div>
<div xml:id="OVU">
<head>Metadata categories for language corpora: a summary</head>
<p>As we have noted, the scope of metadata relevant to corpus work is extensive.
In this final section, we present an overview of the kinds of <q>data about
data</q> which are regarded as most generally useful. </p>
<p>Multiple <term>levels</term> of metadata may be associated with a corpus. For
example, some information may relate to the corpus as a whole (for example, its
title, the purpose for which it was created, its distributor, etc); other
information may relate only to individual components of it (for example, the
bibliographic description of an individual source text), or to groups of such
components (for example, a taxonomic classification).</p>
<p>In the following lists, we have supplied the TEI element corresponding with
the topic in question. This is not meant to imply that all corpora should
conform to the TEI Recommendations, but simply to give examples taken from a
widely used implementation of the the topics addressed. </p>
<div xml:id="D1iden">
<head>Corpus identification</head>
<p>Under this heading we group information that identifies the corpus, and
specifies the agencies responsible for its creation and distribution. <list>
<item>name of corpus (<gi>title</gi> within <gi>titleStmt</gi>)</item>
<item>producer (<gi>respStmt</gi> within <gi>titleStmt</gi>). The agency
(individuals, research group, "principle investigator", company, institution
etc.) responsible for the intellectual content of the corpus should be
specified. This may also include information about any funding body or sponsor
involved in producing the corpus.</item>
<item>distributor (<gi>publicationStmt</gi>). The agency (individual, research
group, company, institution etc) responsible for making copies of the corpus
available. The following information should typically be provided: <list>
<item>name of agency <gi>publisher</gi>, <gi>distributor</gi>
</item>
<item>contact details (postal address, email, telephone, fax)
(<gi>pubPlace</gi>)</item>
<item>date first made available by this agency (<gi>date</gi>)</item>
<item>any specific identifier (e.g. a PURL or ISBN ) used for the published
version (<gi>idno</gi>)</item>
<item>availability: a note summarizing any restrictions on availability, e.g.
where the corpus may not be distributed in some geographic zones, or for some
specific purposes, or only under some specific licencing conditions
(<gi>availability</gi>). </item>
</list></item>
</list></p>
<p>If a corpus is made available by more than one agency, this should be
indicated, and the information above supplied for at least one of them. </p>
<p>If specific licencing conditions apply to the corpus, a copy of the licence
or other agreement may be included in the <gi>availability</gi> element, or it
may be referenced by means of a link.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="D1srce">
<head>Corpus derivation</head>
<p>Under this heading we group information that describes the sources sampled in
creating the corpus. </p>
<p>Written language resources may be derived from any of the following: <list>
<item>books, newspapers, pamphlets etc. originally printed</item>
<item>unpublished, handwritten or <soCalled>born-digital</soCalled>
materials</item>
<item>web pages or other digitally distributed materials</item>
<item>recorded or broadcast speech or video</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>A description of each different source used in building a corpus should be
supplied. This may take the form of a full TEI <gi>sourceDesc</gi> attached to
the relevant corpus component, or it may be supplied in ancillary printed
documentation, but its presence is essential. In a language corpus, samples are
taken out of their context; the description of their source both restores that
context and enables a degree of independent verification that the sample
correctly represents the original.</p>
<div>
<head>Bibliographic description</head>
<p>For conventionally printed and published material, a standard bibliographic
description should be supplied or referenced, using the usual conventions
(author, title, publisher, date, ISBN, etc.), and using a standard citation
format such as <ref target="#TEIP3">TEI</ref>, <ref target="#bibtex">BibTeX</ref>, <ref target="#MLA">MLA</ref>
etc. For other kinds of material, different data is appropriate: for example, in
transcripts of spoken data it is customary to supply demographic information
about each speaker, and the context in which the speech interaction occurs.
Standards defining the range of such information useful in particular research
communities should be followed <!--(for example <ptr target="#dspex"></ptr>)--> where
appropriate. </p>
<p>Language corpora are generally created in order to represent language in use.
As such, they often require more detailed description of the persons responsible
for the language production they represent than a standard bibliographic
description would provide. Demographic descriptions of the participants in a
spoken interaction are clearly essential, but even in a work of fiction, it may
also be useful to specify such characteristics for the characters represented.
In both cases, the <soCalled>speech situation</soCalled> may be described,
including such features as the target and actual audience, the domain, mode,
etc. </p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Extent</head>
<p>Information about the size of each sample and of the whole corpus should be
provided, typically as a part of the metadata discussed in <ptr target="#D1sam"
/>.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Languages</head>
<p>The natural language or languages represented in a corpus should be
explicitly stated, preferably using a standard language identification code such
as the three letter codes of ISO 639. (Full information and links to current
resources on language identification codes is available from <ptr
target="http://xml.coverpages.org/languageIdentifiers.html"/>). Where more than
one language is represented, their relative proportions should also be stated.
For multilingual aligned or parallel corpora, source and target versions of the
same language should be distinguished. (<gi>langUsage</gi>)</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Classification</head>
<p>As noted earlier, corpora are not haphazard collections of text, but have
usually been constructed according to some particular design, often related to
some kind of categorization of textual materials. Particularly in the case where
corpus components have been chosen with respect to some predefined taxonomy of
text types, the classification assigned to each selected text should be formally
specified. (The taxonomy itself may also need to be defined, in the same way as
any other formal model; see further <ptr target="#D1class"/>). </p>
<p>A classification may take the form of a simple list of descriptive keywords,
possibly chosen from some standard controlled vocabulary or ontology.
Alternatively, or in addition, it may take the form of a coded value taken from
some list of such values, standard or non-standard. For example, the Universal
Decimal Classification might be used to characterize topics of a text, or the
researcher might make up their own <foreign>ad hoc</foreign> classification
scheme. In the latter case an associated set of definitions for the
classification codes used must be supplied.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div xml:id="D1enc">
<head>Corpus encoding</head>
<p>Under this heading we group the following descriptive information relating to
the way in which the source documents from which the corpus was derived have
been processed and managed: <list>
<item>Project goals and research agenda (<gi>projectDesc</gi>; <ref
target="#D1proj"/>); </item>
<item>Sampling principles and methods employed (<gi>samplingDecl</gi>; <ref
target="#D1sam"/>);</item>
<item>Editorial principles and practices (<gi>editorialDecl</gi>; <ref
target="#D1ed"/>);</item>
<item>XML or SGML tagging used (<gi>tagsDecl</gi>; <ref target="#D1tags"
/>)</item>
<item>Reference scheme applied (<gi>refsDecl</gi>; <ref target="#D1refs"
/>)</item>
<item>Classification scheme used (<gi>classDecl</gi>; <ref target="#D1class"
/>)</item>
</list>
</p>
<div xml:id="D1proj">
<head>Project Goals</head>
<p>Corpora are usually designed according to some specific design criteria,
rather than being randomly assembled. The project goals and research agenda
associated with the creation of a corpus should therefore be explicitly stated.
The persons or agencies directly responsible will already have been mentioned in
the corpus identification; the purpose of this section is to provide further
background on such matters as the purposes for which the corpus was created, its
design goals, its theoretical framework or context, its intended usage, target
audience etc. Although such information is of necessity impressionistic and
anecdotal, it can be very helpful to the user seeking to determine the potential
relevance of the resource to their own needs. </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="D1sam">
<head>Sampling and extent</head>
<p>Where a corpus has been made (as is usually the case) by selecting parts of
pre-existing materials, the sampling practice should be explicitly stated. For
example, how large are the samples? what is the relationship between size of
sample and size of original? were all samples taken from the beginning, middle,
or end of texts? on what basis were texts selected for sampling? etc. </p>
<p>The corpus metadata should also include unambiguous and verifiable
information about the overall size of the corpus, the size of the sources from
which it was derived, and the frequency distribution of sample sizes. Size
should be expressed in meaningful units, such as orthographically defined words,
or characters. </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="D1ed">
<head>Editorial practice</head>
<p>By editorial principles and practices we mean the practices followed when
transforming the original source into digital form. For textual resources, this
will typically include such topics as the following, each of which may
conveniently be given as a separate paragraph. <list type="gloss">
<label>correction </label>
<item>how and under what circumstances corrections have been made in the
text.</item>
<label>normalization</label>
<item>the extent to which the original source has been regularized or
normalized.</item>
<label>segmentation</label>
<item>how has the text has been segmented, for example into sentences,
tone-units, graphemic strata, etc.</item>
<label>quotation</label>
<item>what has been done with quotation marks in the original? have they been
retained or replaced by entity references, are opening and closing quotes
distinguished, etc.</item>
<label>hyphenation</label>
<item>what has been done with hyphens (especially end-of-line hyphens) in the
original? have they been retained, replaced by entity references, etc.</item>
<label>interpretation</label>
<item>what analytic or interpretive information has been added to the text? only
a brief characterization of the scope of such annotation is needed here; a more
formal specification for such annotation may be usefully provided elsewhere
however.</item>
</list></p>
<p>There is no requirement that <emph>all</emph> (or any) of the above be
formally documented and defined. It is however, very helpful to identify whether
or not information is <emph>available</emph> under each such heading, so that
the end user for whom a particular category may or may not be significant can
make an informed judgment of the usefulness to them of the corpus. </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="D1tags">
<head>Markup scheme</head>
<p>Where a resource has been marked up in XML or SGML, or some other formal
language, the markup scheme used should be documented in full, unless it is an
application of some publicly defined markup vocabulary such as TEI, CES,
Docbook, etc. Non XML or SGML markup is not generally recommended. </p>
<p>For XML or SGML corpora not conforming to a publicly available schema, the
following should be made available to the user of the corpus: <list>
<item>a copy in electronic form of a DTD or XML Schema which can be used to
validate each resource supplied </item>
<item>a document providing definitions for each element used in the DTD or
schema (The TEI element definitions may be used as a model, but any equivalent
description may be used) </item>
<item>any additional information needed to correctly process and interpret the
markup scheme</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>For XML or SGML which does conform to a publicly available scheme, the
following information should be supplied: <list>
<item>name of the scheme and reference to its definition</item>
<item>whether the scheme has been customized or modified in any way</item>
<item>where modification has been made, a description of the modification or
customization made, including any ancillary documentation, DTD fragments,
etc.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>For schemes permitting user modification or extension (such as the TEI),
documentation of the additional or modified elements provided must also be
provided. </p>
<p>Finally, for resources in XML or SGML, it is useful to provide a list of the
elements actually marked up in the resource, indicating how often each one is
used. This can be used to validate the coverage of the category of information
marked up within the corpus. Such a list can then be compared with one generated
automatically during validation of the corpus in order to confirm integrity of
the resource. The TEI <gi>tagsDecl</gi> element is useful for this purpose. </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="D1refs">
<head>Reference Scheme</head>
<p>By <term>reference scheme</term> we mean the recommended method used to
identify locations within the corpus, for example text identifier plus
sentence-number within text, physical line number within file, etc. Reference
systems may be explicit, in that the reference to be used for (say) a given
sentence is encoded within the text, or implicit, in that, if sentences are
numbered sequentially, it is sufficient only to mark where the next sentence
begins. Reference systems may depend upon logical characteristics of the text
(such as those expressed in the mark up) or physical characteristics of the file
in which the text is stored (such as line sequence); clearly the former are to
be preferred as they are less fragile. </p>
<p>A corpus may use more than one reference system concurrently, for example it
is often convenient to include a referencing system defined in terms of the
original source material (such as page number within source text) as well as one
defined in terms of the encoded corpus. </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="D1class">
<head>Classification (etc.) Scheme</head>
<p>As noted above, a classification scheme may be defined externally (with
reference to some pre-existing scheme such as bibliographic subject headings) or
internally. Where it is defined internally, a structure like the TEI
<gi>taxonomy</gi> element may be used to document the meaning and structure of
the classifications used.</p>
<p>Exactly the same considerations apply to any other system of analytic
annotation. For example in a linguistically annotated corpus, the classification
scheme used for morphosyntactic codes or linguistic functions may be defined
externally, by reference to some standard scheme such as EAGLES or the ISO Data
Category Registry, or internally by means of an explicit set of definitions for
the categories employed. </p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div>
<head>Conclusions</head>
<p>Metadata plays a key role in organizing the ways in which a language corpus
can be meaningfully processed. It records the interpretive framework within
which the components of a corpus were selected and are to be understood. Its
scope extends from straightforward labelling and identification of individual
items to the detailed representation of complex interpretive data associated
with their linguistic components. As such, it is essential to proper use of a
language corpus. </p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Bibliography</head>
<listBibl>
<bibl xml:id="me_BUR99"><author>Burnard, L.</author><date>(1999)</date>
<title level="a">Using SGML for linguistic analysis: the case of the BNC</title>
in <title level="s">Markup languages theory and practice</title>. I.2 pp. 31-51.
Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press. </bibl>
<bibl xml:id="me_DUN95"><author>Dunlop, D.</author> (1995) <title level="a"
>Practical considerations in the use of TEI headers in large corpora</title> in
Ide, Nancy and Jean Veronis (1995) <title level="m">Text Encoding Initiative:
background and context</title>
<publisher>Kluwer</publisher>
<date>1995</date><idno type="isbn">0-7923-3704-2</idno></bibl>
<bibl xml:id="me_TEIP3">Sperberg-McQueen, C.M. and Burnard, L. (1994)
<title>Guidelines for electronic text encoding and interchange (TEI P3)</title>
Chicago and Oxford: ACH-ALLC-ACL Text Encoding Initiative.</bibl>
<bibl xml:id="me_dspex"><author>van den Heuvel, Henk, Louis Boves and Eric
Sanders</author> (2000). <title>Validation of content and quality of existing
SLR: overview and methodology</title> Available from <ptr
target="http://www.spex.nl/validationcentre/d11v21.doc"/>
</bibl>
<bibl xml:id="me_ide98">Ide, Nancy (coordinator) (1998) <title level="a">Corpus
Encoding Specification</title> Available from <ptr
target="http://www.cs.vassar.edu/CES"/></bibl>
<bibl xml:id="me_MLA"><author>Gibaldi, Joseph</author> (1998) <title>MLA Style
manual and Guide to Scholarly Publishing</title> (2nd ed). </bibl>
<bibl xml:id="me_bibtex"><author>Lamport, L.</author> (1986) <title>Latex: a
document preparation system</title>. Addison-Wesley. </bibl>
</listBibl>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
