<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="ab-479">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Future Developments for TEI ODD</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Cummings, James</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Oxford, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>James.Cummings@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Rahtz, Sebastian</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Oxford, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>Sebastian.Rahtz@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Burnard, Lou</name>
                    <affiliation>TGE-Adonis, France</affiliation>
                    <email>lou.burnard@tge-adonis.fr</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Bauman, Syd</name>
                    <affiliation>Brown University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>Syd_Bauman@Brown.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Gaiffe, Bertrand</name>
                    <affiliation>ATILF, France</affiliation>
                    <email>bertrand.gaiffe@atilf.fr</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Romary, Laurent</name>
                    <affiliation>INRIA, France</affiliation>
                    <email>laurent.romary@inria.fr</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Bański, Piotr</name>
                    <affiliation>HUB &amp; IDS, Poland</affiliation>
                    <email>bansp@o2.pl</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="session">
        <body>
            <p>The purpose of this panel is to look at the application and future development of the
                literate programming system known as ODD which was developed for the Text Encoding
                Initiative (TEI) and underlies every single use of the TEI.</p>
            <p>Though strongly influenced by data modelling techniques characteristic of markup
                languages such as SGML and XML, the conceptual model of the Text Encoding Initiative
                is defined independently of any particular representation or implementation. The
                objects in this model, their properties, and their relationships are all defined
                using a special TEI vocabulary called ODD (for One Document Does-it-all); in this
                way, the TEI model is used to define itself and a TEI specification using that model
                is, formally, just like any other kind of resource defined using the TEI.  An
                application selects the parts of the TEI model it wishes to use, and any
                modifications it wishes to make of them, by writing a TEI specification (a TEI ODD
                document), which can then be processed by appropriate software to generate instance
                documents relevant to the given application. Typically, these instance documents
                will consist of both user documentation, such as project manuals for human use, and
                system documentation, such as XML schemas or DTDs, sets of Schematron constraints
                etc. for machine use. In this respect ODD is a sophisticated re-implementation of
                the ‘literate programming’ paradigm developed by Don Knuth in the 1970s reimagined
                as ‘literate encoding’. </p>
            <p>One of the requirements for TEI Conformance is that the TEI file ‘is documented by
                means of a TEI Conformant ODD file which refers to the TEI Guidelines’. In many
                cases users employ pre-generated schemas from exemplar customizations, but they are
                usually better served if they use the TEI ODD markup language, possibly through the
                Roma web application, to constrain what is available to them thus customizing the
                TEI model to reflect more precisely their encoding needs.</p>
            <p>Some of the mechanisms supporting this extensibility are relatively new in the TEI
                Guidelines, and users are only now beginning to recognize their potential. We
                believe that there is considerable potential for take-up of the TEI system beyond
                its original core constituencies in language engineering, traditional philology,
                digital libraries, and digital humanities in general. Recent additions to the TEI
                provide encoding schemes for database-like information about persons and places to
                complement their existing detailed recommendations for names and linguistic
                structures; they have always provided recommendations for software-independent means
                of authoring scientific documentation, but the ODD framework makes it easier for TEI
                documents to coexist with other specialist XML vocabularies as well as expanding it
                to encompass the needs of new specialised kinds of text. It has been successfully
                used for describing other XML schemas, notably the W3C ITS (Internationalisation
                Tagset) and ISO TC37 SC4 standards documents; more recently its facilities have
                greatly simplified the task of extending the TEI model to address the needs of other
                research communities, such as musicologists and genetic editors.</p>
            <p>We believe that the current ODD system could be further enhanced to provide robust
                support for new tools and services; an important step is to compare and contrast its
                features with those of other ‘meta-encoding’ schemes and consider its relationship
                to ontological description languages such as OWL. The potential role of ODD in the
                development of the semantic web is an intriguing topic for investigation. </p>
            <p>This panel brings together some of the world’s most knowledgeable users and
                architects of the TEI ODD language, including several who have been responsible for
                its design and evolution over the years. We will debate its strengths, limitations,
                and future development.  Each speaker will focus on one aspect, problem, or possible
                development relating to TEI ODD before responding to each others suggestions and
                answering questions from the audience.</p>
            <p>Lou Burnard will introduce the history and practical use of ODD in TEI, and describe
                its relevance as a means of introducing new users to the complexity of the TEI.
                Sebastian Rahtz will talk about the processing model for ODD, and the changes
                required to the language to model genuinely symmetric, and chainable,
                specifications. Bertrand Gaiffe will look at some of the core mechanisms within ODD,
                and suggest that model classes that gather elements (or other model classes) for
                their use into content models could be better as underspecified bags instead of
                sets. Syd Bauman will discuss co-occurrence constraints, pointing out that ODD’s
                lack of support for this feature is a significant limitation, but also that it can
                often be worked around by adding Schematron to an ODD. Laurent Romary and Piotr
                Banski will describe issues in drafting ODD documents from scratch, in particular in
                the context of ISO standardisation work, introducing proposals to make ODD evolve
                towards a generic specification environment.</p>
            <p>We believe that the DH2012 conference offers a useful outreach opportunity for the
                TEI to engage more closely with the wider DH community, and to promote a greater
                awareness of the power and potential of the TEI ODD language. We also see this as an
                invaluable opportunity to obtain feedback about the best ways of developing ODD in
                the future, thereby contributing to the TEI Technical Council’s ongoing
                responsibility to maintain and enhance the language.</p>
            
                
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Organization</hi></p>
                    <p>The 5 speakers will each give a 15-minute introduction to a problem or
                possible development that relates to TEI ODD. After this the organizer will moderate
                discussion between members of the panel on a number of questions before opening the
                discussion to questions from the audience.</p>
                
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Speakers</hi></p><xmt:uList>
            <item>Lou Burnard, lou.burnard@tge-adonis.fr, TGE-Adonis  </item>
            <item>Syd Bauman, syd_bauman@brown.edu, Brown University Center for Digital Scholarship  </item>
            <item>Bertrand Gaiffe, bertrand.gaiffe@atilf.fr, ATILF  </item>
            <item>Sebastian Rahtz, sebastian.rahtz@oucs.ox.ac.uk, University of Oxford  </item>
            <item>Laurent Romary &amp; Piotr Bański (Piotr speaking), laurent.romary@inria.fr,
                bansp@o2.pl, Inria, HUB &amp; IDS </item></xmt:uList>
            <p/>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Organizer</hi> James Cummings, james.cummings@oucs.ox.ac.uk,
                University of Oxford</p>
                
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Burnard, L., and R. Rahtz</hi> (2004). RelaxNG with Son of
                        ODD. <hi rend="italic">Extreme Markup Languages 2004</hi>, <ref target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.124.7139&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf" type="external">http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.124.7139&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf</ref></p><p><hi rend="bold">Romary, L.</hi> (2009). ODD as a generic
                        specification platform, <hi rend="italic">Text encoding in the era of mass
                            digitization – Conference and Members’ Meeting of the TEI
                            Consortium</hi>  <ref target="http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00433433" type="external">http://hal.inria.fr/inria-00433433"</ref></p><p><hi rend="bold">TEI By Example</hi> (2010). Customising TEI, ODD, Roma. <hi rend="italic">TEI By Example</hi>,  <ref target="http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm" type="external">http://tbe.kantl.be/TBE/modules/TBED08v00.htm</ref></p><p><hi rend="bold">TEI Consortium, eds.</hi> (2007). TEI P5 Guidelines Chapter
                        on “Documentation Elements”. <hi rend="italic">TEI P5: Guidelines for
                            Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</hi>. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html" type="external">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html</ref></p><p><hi rend="bold">TEI Consortium, eds.</hi> (2007). TEI P5 Guidelines Section on “Implementation of
                    an ODD System”. <hi rend="italic">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text
                        Encoding and Interchange</hi>. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM" type="external">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/USE.html#IM</ref></p><p><hi rend="bold">TEI Consortium, eds.</hi> (2007). Getting
                        Started with TEI P5 ODDs. <hi rend="italic">TEI-C Website</hi>. <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml" type="external">http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/odds.xml</ref>
                            
                </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>