<div><p>Four years into a five-year COST Action seems a good point to attempt a little retrospective evaluation, particularly when face-to-face meetings are impossible.  By this stage in the Action’s history, we have made good progress towards our stated goal of creating a unique European Literary Text Collection, following specific design and selection criteria agreed upon by a broad community of European researchers. We have also developed a reasonably stable method of evaluating the balance of a given collection with respect to those design criteria (note). As of  December 2020, 15 of the ELTeC’s 18 individual language collections had exceeded the goal of 50 texts and achieved a  “conformance score” of over 70, while 12 of them have 75 or more texts and a score in excess of 75.   A certain amount of self-congratulation might reasonably be in order but the leaders of Work Group 1 wished to go beyond that by facilitating a broader discussion around the accumulated experience of all the collection builders, not simply the “successful” ones. Such a discussion might seek to explain why in some cases the stated design criteria could not be achieved, possibly leading to a reappraisal of the assumptions about a common European literary culture underlying the whole  project.
</p><p>
Late 2020 was not of course a propitious time in which to organise an international discussion meeting. However, although the ability to meet and discuss research priorities and methodologies informally over shared meals and at social gatherings was no longer available to  us,  we could take advantage of distanced conference facilities to  review progress collectively, using a semi formal virtual meeting format in which each participant presented their experience following a predefined template. The present document is an attempt to synthesize those presentations, derived from the slides used by participants (note): its author is responsible – and apologizes in advance – for any inadvertently introduced misrepresentations of their content.
</p>
</div>
