<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Festina Lente </title>
<author>louburnard</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Self-published (WordPress)</publisher>
<idno type="URL">https://louburnard.wordpress.com/2013/06/01/festina-lente-1/</idno>
<date when="2013-06-01">2013-06-01</date>
<availability>
<p>Originally published on WordPress.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from WordPress WXR export.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="category">
<term>Biographical</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="tag">
<term>autobiographical</term>
<term>trains</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>

<head>Festina Lente : June 2013</head>
<p>If you have to get from Oxford to Caen and then to Grenoble, there are several possibilities. You could fly, but the cheap flights are all on the wrong days, or leave from the wrong airports. You could Eurostar and TGV it. Now, it's a commonly believed falsehood, probably fostered by the SNCF, that you cannot get anywhere in France without travelling (a) by TGV (b) via Paris. I plan to prove them wrong by doing this whole trip without doing either.</p>
<div>
<head>STEP ONE</head><p>
Oxford to Caen is a journey I have done several times. A 10 am departure from Oxford will just get the 1315 Eurostar, and then it's a matter of schlepping across Paris in the rush hour to St Lazare in time for the 1810 Intercites, arriving in Caen at 20h00. Total cost, if you care, about 250 euro. OR, you could start at the same time and take a slightly slower but more direct route. A Virgin train from Manchester links Oxford to Southampton, which connects with another to Portsmouth, and then due south again by ferry to Oustrehan, which Brittany Ferries persist in pretending is actually Caen's harbour. If everything connects, you leave Oxford at 1015 and arrive at Caen at 2100.
</p><p> This being Bank Holiday Tuesday and a school holiday I was anticipating
trains crowded with families on their way to Bournemouth, but the current
British climate (both spiritual and meteorological) seems to have dampened
popular enthusiasm for such a projects. I set off in a determined drizzle and
spent most of the journey revising a paper for the Document Engineering
conference. It was still raining every time I looked out of the window. And
still when I changed trains at Southmapton Central. And still when my train
finally pulled in to Portsmouth and Southsea station, which seemed the best bet
for a taxi to the ferry port. Like the airports favoured by budget airlines,
ferry ports are never where you might expect them to be. Brittany Ferries do not
operate their services from Portsmouth harbour, oh no. They have their own
purpose built ferryport which is 5 quids worth of taxi away. I arrive much too
early, as usual, and spurn the offer of wifi for 5 quid an hour. <!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/p1030910.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/p1030910.jpg" width="650px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/p1030910.jpg?w=650--></graphic>
<head> It's a BOAT. It's HUGE.</head></figure>
</p><p> Me and a dozen or so other intrepid
pedestrians climb aboard, where we are affably greeted by REAL FRENCH SAILORS.
I'd forgotten how much fun this is, provided the sea isn't misbehaving (it
wasn't) and there are not too many other people having it (there weren't). I had
a slap up late lunch of roast lamb and proper french fries, with drinkable wine,
and proper cheese, before retiring to my cabin for a couple of hours snooze.
Wifi only works on the upper decks,which is slightly annoying, since that is
also where someone is also trying hard to entertain us with a general knowledge
quiz, followed by larks for the kids, but what the hay. It's a relaxing
experience, and I disembark in such a relaxed state at Oustrehan I am happy to
wait 15 mins for a taxi to come and take me to my appointed hotel in downtown
Caen (40 euro, gulp) far too late for any dinner, The next three days are spent
in a meeting of the Conseil Scientifique de la MRSH, and involved no rail
travel, nor indeed much travel except for one surprise outing. Since last year,
this committee has lost a couple of members, and gained a couple more, but
otherwise it was much as last year (see previous report), except of course that
both we and the MRSH itself now have last year's experience under our
metaphorical belts and know what to expect from the meeting.</p></div>
<div>
<head>
<hi rend="bold">STEP TWO</hi>
</head><p>
I make my excuses and leave the MRSH in good time to squeeze myself and my bags onto the tram down to the station. In fact, much too good time, since I then have to wait around for 20 minutes. But eventually...
</p><p>
15h45 : Train Express Regionale no. 57210 heads out of Caen and across the Lower Norman countryside in a southerly direction at a stately pace. There are many many stations to come.... indeed, before you can say Jacques Robinson we are pulling in to...

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130531_161200.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130531_161200.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130531_161200.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>20130531_161200</head>
</figure>
</p><p>

15h58 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Mezidon">Mezidon</ref>!  Never heard of it, but the sun is shining and the platform is covered with cheerful looking young people. A portly SNCF person approaches to ask whether anyone fancies getting off at the next stop, but seems uninterested in checking tickets.
</p><p>
16:06 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Saint-Pierre-sur-Dives">St Pierre Sur Dive</ref>s  is a tiny halt, but the train still waits there hopefully for a few minutes. No one gets off, or on. It barely has a presence even on Wikipedia. The countryside remains green, with ancient looking stone barns and farmhouses. And occasional rows of cottages with their backs to the railway. There's a general air of nothing much happens here. I realize how pleasant it is to be able to actually see the countryside I am travelling through, even though there really isn't much to see except huge expanses of greenery interspersed with trees, with occasional clumps of stone cottages. You get the idea: la Basse Normandie is very very rural. It also has railway stations so rural even this train doesn't stop at them. Oooh horses!
</p><p>
17h27 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_d%27Argentan">Argentan</ref>  looks like a bigger place. For one thing it has a tennis court, and something that looks suspiciously like a factory, to say nothing of a dual highway rushing alongside, a huge multistory carpark, and a nice big newish railway station. More students pile on , though not of course into 1st class. A second cheminot, sporting a proper peaked hat rather than a mere beret, joins the first one on the train and starts checking the tickets; mine is now satisfactorily punched.
</p><p>
17h43 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_S%C3%A9es">Sées</ref>  (apparently pronounced “say”) is bosky on the approach. An old station building in brick and stone, with a greatly expanded platform. A main road beyond it along which trundle 2cvs and huge lorries. Yellow gorse on the hedgerows. <hi rend="italic">L’opposition de ses habitants à la ligne de chemin de fer Paris-Granville a contribué à faire stagner la ville lors de la révolution industrielle au profit d’Argentan</hi> (Wikipedia) A motorway snarls alongside, parallel to the railway between here and the next stop
</p><p>
17h56 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_d'Alencon">Alencon</ref>. This is actually a city: its station has more than one platform, a plethora of platforms indeed, as well as a new building (the old one was flattened during WW2), a  carrefour market, a proper 19c cemetery, and an agglomeration. It doesn't last. We're back in large green fields, trees, hills, horse and cow country pretty soon.
</p><p>
18h12 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Vivoin_-_Beaumont">Vivoin - Beaumont </ref> is approached via a deep green cutting and is of the type charmingly known in French as a PANG (<hi rend="italic">un point d'arrêt non géré</hi> ) . It has a level crossing, where the traffic is held up, and a much graffitoed old shed for its station building. But people get off all the same. Not much of a conurbation, and leaving it all I notice are distant hills, topped with castles. The fields seem to be getting bigger too. A couple of stations flash by.
The first clear sign that a big city approaches is an Auchan supermarket...followed by row upon row of factory style prefab sheds. Yes, it's...
</p><p>
18h29 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_du_Mans">Le Mans </ref> a major railway junction and city as any fule kno. It even has trams, a tasteful brown colour. And of course acres of HLMs and row upon row of terraces, multistorey car parks, a bus station, a taxi rank, shops and bars... a proper big city railway station where TGVs stop. Lots of people get off, not many get on. We have now entered a new TER district. After sneaking away through vast expanses of marshalling yards, my train settles down for the last hour of its journey. Out into the countryside again, but seemingly more wooded and agricultural than Normandy: we are in the pays de la Loire.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130531_180655_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130531_180655_v1.jpg" width='231px'/>
</figure></p><p>
18h50: <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_d%27%C3%89commoy">Ecommoy</ref> is another place whose station is much too small to accommodate this train (I am sitting at the back of it), having hardly changed since it opened in 1858. The village looks much the same too. There's lumberjacks round here somewhere, judging by the freight yard full of sliced up tree.

1908 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Ch%C3%A2teau-du-Loir">Chateau du Loir</ref> another small place with a big disused freight yard, nothing to see of station. Can't see any chateau, but it could be anywhere, hidden away in these wooded hills. Almost everyone has left the train and all is quiet, as those who have not left are mostly contemplating their laptops playstations or mobile phones. The scenery outside the window remains charming, varied rural, as the train skirts some river, zips through some forest, passes the edge of a hamlet, rumbles through some station not worth stopping at. Finally it crosses a huge river which I take to be the Loire and pulls into the majestic <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Tours">Gare de Tours</ref>, <hi rend="italic">notre terminus</hi> and offficially a historic monument.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130531_185149.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130531_185149.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130531_185149.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>Gare de Tours</head>
</figure>
I check into my favourite Tourangellian hotel, and then go in search of dinner at <hi rend="italic">le Chien Jaune</hi>. This used to be a somewhat chaotic bistrot, but has now (I learn from a fellow diner) been bought by the owner of the Odeon, so the food is much better, but the prices have gone up. And so to bed, well pleased with my first day's <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi>.</p></div>

<div>
<head>STAGE THREE</head><p>
It's 09h00 on the 1st June and the sun is shining into the familiar breakfast room at the Grand Hotel de Tours, where I am enjoying my familiar breakfast and the headlines in <hi rend="italic">Le Monde</hi>. And so to the 09h58 departure for Bourges. Two nice SNCF ladies are running this, and I seem to have installed myself in their private first class compartment, ah well.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_093423.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130601_093423.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_093423.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>SNCF ladies taking a brief and well deserved rest</head>
</figure>
</p><p>

10h02: <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Saint-Pierre-des-Corps">St Pierre de Corps</ref> is a SNCF “technopole”, i.e. major junction, marshalling yard, engine shed, repair centre, graveyard. Rows of passenger units varyingly disfigured by graffiti or overgrown by weeds, old shunting engines shunted together, modern ones amusingly labelled “FRET”. The TGV to and from Paris stops here, which is why I know it all too well. If it were in England it would be called Tours Parkway. Speeding through its associated industrial wasteland, my train swings off to the right on <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ligne_de_Vierzon_%C3%A0_Saint-Pierre-des-Corps">the line to Vierzon</ref>  and Bourges.
</p><p>
10h24: <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Chenonceaux">Chenonceax</ref> Maybe it;s the weather but everything looks lovely, even though this is another PANG barely known to wikipedia. As we proceed, I notice that people in these parts seem to be into building houses as developments from existing limestone caves. And then of course there are also rich folks' chateaux, poking their turrets out of the woods here and there.
</p><p>
10h29:<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Montrichard"> Montrichard</ref>  has a full-on iron passenger bridge, dating from 1869 when they doubled the number of tracks on this line. It is followed by a couple of quite respectable tunnels. The stations on this line have rather nice red brick stripes set into white.
</p><p>
10h43: <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Saint-Aignan_-_Noyers">Saint-Aignan-Noyers</ref>  is in the middle of some flat farmland, so boasts some cereal silos and other rather unimproved old industrial architecture. There is a long long straight road leading from here to the horizon, on which you can just see the outline of one of those famous castles of the loire.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_100355.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130601_100355.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_100355.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>20130601_100355</head>
</figure></p><p>
10h50:<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Selles-sur-Cher"> Selles-sur-cher</ref> (87) . Well preserved old style station. No-one gets on or off, this saturday morning, but we still sit and wait for a few minutes. Industrial buildings, some abandoned, some not, line the edge of the track for a while, until the woods reassert themselves
</p><p>
11h00 :<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Gi%C3%A8vres"> Gievres</ref> (96) is a junction station with a branch line heading somewhere called Romorartin. Splashes of yellow gorse here and there. Muddy tracks enticing the eye into woodland
</p><p>
11h10 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Villefranche-sur-Cher">Villefranche-sur-Cher</ref> (98) has an overgrown ambitious marshalling yard. This place maybe was somewhere once, or had ambitions to be. I am guessing that Cher is the name of that river we crossed a while back.
</p><p>
11h30 : Some even more extensive marshalling yards announce the arrival of <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Vierzon">Vierzon ville </ref>(122), which is a major junction, it seems, at the intersection of several routes, as well as a decent sized town. The junior of my two train ladies gets off here leaving her colleague to manage alone for the last part of this train's run, past two radio masts, and a parc eolienne of the type my Norman colleagues get so cross about.
</p><p>
11h47 into<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Bourges"> Bourges</ref>  (130) , in plenty of time for a coffee before the next train. If only there were a bar in the station, or a functioning toilette. But there is neither, just a horrid supermarket. Outside the sun is still shining and there are numerous hopeful hotels, none of which will offer anything short of a large lunch at this time on a saturday, so I settle for a quick coffee in the only baker who's still open before inspecting the riverside formal gardens and accompanying war memorial.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_111805.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130601_111805.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_111805.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>Formal garden at Bourges</head>
</figure></p><p>
I see from the map that Bourges has a large area called Le Marais, which actually consists of marsh rather than narrow twisted picturesque old streets. And so back in time for my next train, the 12h30 departure for Nevers. This is an almost identical Bombardier unit, in the care of another nice SNCF lady.

 </p><p>

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_114723_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130601_114723_v1.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_114723_v1.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>Quondam station at </head>
</figure>
 12h35 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Saint-Germain-du-Puy">Saint Germain du Puy</ref> The station building has been thoughtfully transformed into a bar where I could get another coffee if we stopped for more than 2 minutes. Ah well, off we go again past nice little homes with nice little gardens into rich fertile farmland... and industrial scale agro-factories, reasuringly mixed with acres of woodland and wheat, or maybe it's hay. A man, appropriately dressed, sprints very slowly past on the track beside our train
</p><p>
1245<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_d'Avord"> Avord</ref>. The stations on this line are a different design from those on the line to Vierzon, but clearly of the same period. And equally clearly, not a lot has happened to disturb them between the mid 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century and the start of the 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> (when the line was electrified).
</p><p>
12h51 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Bengy-sur-Craon">Bengy sur Craon</ref>  has a rather pretty church visible from the station as well as a really silly name.
</p><p>
12h56 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_N%C3%A9rondes">Nerondes</ref> The station is fairly clearly unused. This is farming country. Grain silos.A tunnel!
</p><p>
130h7 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_La_Guerche-sur-l%27Aubois">La guerche sur laubois</ref> seems like a pleasantly sleepy country town, prosperous enough to maintain three trains a day, and a street full of small shops.
</p><p>
13h20 into<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Nevers"> Nevers</ref> (186). A large station, with its own fancy subway, and all the trappings of modernity. I was a bit worried about having only ten minutes between trains, but the connexion was easy. Here we leave the Central Region and enter Burgundy, home of <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/TER_Bourgogne">http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/TER_Bourgogne</ref>. The 13h30 train to Dijon is (as they say) <hi rend="italic">labellisé </hi>as belonging to the Conseil Regionale de Bourgogne as well as the SNCF, though the rolling stock appears to be identical (Alston, TER for the use of).
</p><p>
1340 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_d'Imphy">Imphy station</ref> is dwarfed by surrounding old engine shed, scrap metal sheds. Once it had a proper station but now it's just another PANG.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_123051_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130601_123051_v1.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_123051_v1.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>20130601_123051_v1</head>
</figure></p><p>
 1353 At Décize I woke from my snooze to see that we are travelling alongside a river, or maybe a canal, and that most of the waterlogged fields around here also sport big crowds of white foraging beasts which are not sheep but cows. This must be were they grow the active ingredient in <hi rend="italic">steack frites</hi>.
</p><p>
1404 Cercy la Tour No sign of a tower unless you count agricultural silos
</p><p>
1424<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Luzy"> Luzy </ref>(271m) Nothing to see except sheds. Purpose of station is to load goods trains, really More fields of white cows, woods, wooded hills and rivers.
</p><p>
1439 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_d%27%C3%89tang-sur-Arroux">Etang sur arroux</ref> (277)  There's a fair going on here, but my train is slowing down, and then enters a tunnel. From which eventually we emerge, some 70 metres higher, into the little town of ...
</p><p>
15h00 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_du_Creusot">Le creusot</ref> (352) : lots (well five) people get on! On tother side of the mountain there is a conurbation of sorts, and then we start going down hill again alongside the river. Sky clouds over for first time today, boo.
</p><p>
1505: Montchanin has a smart new signal box and shunting yard but its wikipedia entry is entirely vacuous. The fields hereabouts are not full of cows any longer, but instead what looks very much like vines. We must be nearly arrived at this train's terminus:<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Beaune"> Beaune </ref>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_155741.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130601_155741.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_155741.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>Subway, Beaune</head>
</figure>
This is a large station with a much decorated subway. I am surprised to learn from it that the true father of cinematography was not a Bristolian called Friese Greene as I had always supposed, nor the American Eadweard Muybridge, but in fact some French chap called <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89tienne-Jules_Marey">Etienne-Jules Marey </ref> – apparently Beaune's most celebrated son.
</p><p>
I have a 90 minutes between trains here, which is a good thing since the walk into the centre of town in search of a nice cup of tea takes rather longer than anticipated. The town centre, when I find it, is picturesque, and full of people on holiday enjoying the sunshine and buying large amounts of interesting wine. My luggage is heavy enough, so I content myself with some nice biscuits to go with the tea.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_161253_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130601_161253_v1.jpg" width='262px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130601_161253_v1.jpg?w=262--></graphic><head>20130601_161253_v1</head>
</figure></p><p>
Last train of the day is the stopping train from Paris Bercy to Lyon, which pauses briefly at 16h59 in Beaune. This is a cut above your average local regional TER: it is a real train with a locomotive and carriages that at least pretend to have compartments. Like other long distance trains, it proceeds in occasional rapid spurts, interspersed with patches of dawdling. Sitting on it is quite a different experience from the Bombardiers I have been on all day. The countryside looks further away, and not just because the windows are dirtier I think. There are three stops (17h15: Chagny, 17h25: Chalon sur Saone, and 17h45 Tournus) before we arrive at my final destination for the day, Macon.
</p><p>
I have booked into a <hi rend="italic">chambre d'hote</hi> I found on the web: an old house opposite the Police Station and just ten minutes walk from the station. The lady who runs it helps me and my suitcase up the stairs to a very smartly renovated <hi rend="italic">mansard</hi>, offers me home made orange wine, and wifi, and is generally welcoming. She also confirms that<ref target="http://www.lacouronne-macon.com/"> La Couronne restaurant</ref> just up the road is quite <hi rend="italic"> acceptable </hi>and even books me a table, where I subsequently enjoy solid Burgundian dinner and a decent glass of wine (their specialty is frogs, but I decline the offer)  And then   a little stroll along the banks of the river, and so to bed.</p>
</div>


<div>
<head>STAGE 4</head><p>
A leisurely breakfast after a good night's sleep. The sky outside is very gray, and I did my tourism yesterday, so I spend the hour or so before my train is due to go sitting in the very comfortable salon and banging my head against the agora stylesheet, to little avail alas.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_110918_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130602_110918_v1.jpg" width='700px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_110918_v1.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>20130602_110918_v1</head>
</figure>
Back to the station in plenty of time for the 11h59 which turns out to be the same style TER as yesterday, i.e. a real loco with one 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> class carriage containing some fairly unkempt compartments without doors ... one is empty for me.
</p><p>
12h10 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Belleville-sur-Sa%C3%B4ne">Belleville sur Saone.</ref> People stand in the station and wave us off, how charming. The old engine shed has been turned into a functioning car park. Large industrial sheds alternate with an English style countryside complete with gray sky. The towns seem to be coming more frequently round these parts, but maybe it's just because the train's going faster.
</p><p>
12h20 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Villefranche-sur-Sa%C3%B4ne">Villefranche sur saone</ref> for example
</p><p>
12:28 : <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Saint-Germain-au-Mont-d%27Or">St Germain au mont d'or</ref> has a rather impressive re-constructed station with some fancy brickwork. The train from here on is following the Saone river, which means glimpses of holiday homes, posh hotels, and speedboats for a change. After a few more miles flirtation with it, the train metaphorically takes a deep breath and zooms across the river, into a tunnel, back over the river again and so eventually into the proud city of Lyon, where it is time for lunch.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_125034.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130602_125034.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_125034.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>Lyon Part Dieu</head>
</figure>
I'm too lazy to leave the immediate surroundings of <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Lyon-Part-Dieu">Part Dieu</ref>, so I chomp my way through a <hi rend="italic">bavette frites</hi> at the Cafe des Vosges, sitting in the shade and ignoring a really bad street musician outside the station which (I discover after lunch) has now installed a free wifi service. Which is nice, though it takes me about 15 minutes to get connected and send a status update to Fessebouqe, before reluctantly concluding that it's also a bit crap.
</p><p>
My 14h38 departure turns out to be another proper train with a locomotive. It even has a modern first class carriage with comfy seats, and a scattering of prises electriques, though the windows are grimy and small.
</p><p>
15h01: <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Bourgoin-Jallieu">Bourgoin Jallieu</ref>  (altitude 254 m) is already up in the hills and boasts an immense locable bike shed, as well as a fine graveyard. The terrain constrains the train to follow the same route as the motorway  A43: there is a mountain to the right and this is becoming alpine country, trees everywhere, villages on the hillside. The train slows down with the gradient and crawls up the side of the mountain. You can see why the tgvs dont come this way.
</p><p>
1517 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_La_Tour-du-Pin">La tour du pin </ref> (altitude 339 m) looks as if it should be in Italy, and the sun comes out to underline the fact. The train picks up speed over the mountain top pastures and little villages. There's grazing land here, and also I think some vines. A herd of goats. Beehives. Carefully enclosed sheep. The train takes a sharp right turn onto <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ligne_Saint-Andr%C3%A9-le-Gaz_-_Chamb%C3%A9ry">a branch-line </ref> and continues to descend, through deep cuts, and now we have some fairly spectacular views or would do if the windows were cleaner and the sky less overcast.
</p><p>
1533: <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Pont-de-Beauvoisin">Pont de Beauvoisin</ref>  (altitude 277 m ) is another Italian style station mysteriously transported to the french alps, affording delightful prospects over the river valley below, not to mention the occasional lake. Some serious looking mountains loom ahead, but the train is going down a steep gradient, through cuttings and past neglected stations. On the mist-topped mountains above there are occasional little villages. There seems to have been a major outbreak of scenic cuteness hereabouts, with added lakes and chalets. I expect Julie Andrews to start singing at any moment. It's a sunny Sunday afternoon so people are out walking their dogs and their families. A couple more tunnels, and we are through the mountain that has been looming ahead all this time, emerging into a deep cutting that leads down the valley, past the timber yards, the allotments, the sportive centre, a quick glimpse of<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rotonde_ferroviaire_de_Chamb%C3%A9ry"> the celebrated round engine shed</ref>, and here we are at the rather unprepossessing <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Chambery">Gare de Chambery</ref>
 Challes les eaux.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_150859_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130602_150859_v1.jpg" width='300px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_150859_v1.jpg?w=300--></graphic><head>Famous round engine shed at Chambery</head>
</figure>
</p><p>

The short walk to my chambre d'hote starts off with some unpromising road works (they're installing a new tramline here too) but my opinion of the town takes a sudden leap upwards on my first glimpse of its celebrated elephants, known locally (I later learn) as the <hi rend="italic">quatre sans q</hi>.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_153646.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130602_153646.jpg" width='700px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_153646.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>20130602_153646</head>
</figure>
These adorn a monument to the memory of local benefactor <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beno%C3%AEt_de_Boigne">Benoît de Boigne </ref> (whose biography is worth a read). Benoit is on top of the tower, and there are four elephants at its base, spouting water magnificently from their trunks. It stands at one end of a fine colonnaded street leading to the ducal castle and definitely <hi rend="italic">vaut le détour</hi>.
</p><p>
Tonight I am staying in the next best thing to a château:<ref target="http://www.booking.com/hotel/fr/de-sautet-les-suites.en.html"> a carefully restored 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c hotel</ref>. My room is huge: all parquet and antique furniture, and includes (amonst others) a painting of supercilious 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c lady who clearly thinks I don't belong here. But my hundred euros are as good as the next man's ma'am, so I spread my goods and chattels around the room, and check out the wifi.
</p><p>
Chambery's old town is also famous for its<hi rend="italic">
<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traboule"> traboules </ref>
</hi>– unexpected little passageways and courtyards linking the narrow twisty streets – so I have a nice evening wandering around exploring them until my feet say it is dinner time. I dine at <ref target="http://lesporting-chambery.com/">Le Sporting </ref>on a rather disappointing <hi rend="italic">tartiflette</hi> (potatoes a bit dry) washed down with an interesting local white wine and find my way back to my immense <hi rend="italic">chambre</hi>
</p><p>


<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130602_185732.jpg" width='700px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130602_185732.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>JeanJacques Rousseau wuz ere</head>
</figure>
</p><p>


Jean-Jacques Rousseau stayed here in 1732, with Mme Warens across the way, and they don't seem to have done much to clean up his digs since he left. All very pleasant.</p></div><div>
<head>STAGE  5</head><p>
A lovely sunny morning. Sit in my salon for an hour or so after breakfast trying to deal with some minor domestic crises by wifi, then a pleasant stroll through Chambery, which I now know almost by heart (it's a VERY SMALL TOWN).... <ref target="http://bit.ly/16yzHUe">see photos</ref>. Last night's dinner weighs heavy, so I pause at the Café du Théatre for a<hi rend="italic"> tarte aux oignons</hi> and a glass of a different local white wine before strolling back to the station in good time for the 14h24 departure.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130603_131637.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130603_131637.jpg" width='700px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130603_131637.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>20130603_131637</head>
</figure>
The last TER of my trip is more like what might have been expected: about four elderly much graffitoed carriages being shunted between Annecy and Grenoble by an old fashioned loco. Hey, these carriages are so old they actually have windows that you can open. Which I do, since the sun is still shining brightly as we rumble out of the tunnel and gingerly start advancing back up the hill.
</p><p>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130603_134555.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130603_134555.jpg" width='700px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130603_134555.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>20130603_134555</head>
</figure>
As it picks up speed the train starts shaking about in an appropriate way. Yesterday was quite mountainous, but this line (the alternative approach to Grenoble) is the real alpine thing. The semi-vertical fields we pass are planted with young vines in rows like cornrows.
</p><p>
14h35 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Montm%C3%A9lian">Montmelian</ref>  (285m) is evidently a wine growing centre, but the main crop in the areas beyond it is tree. The mountains looming to left and to right as we rattle on are snow topped and imposing.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130603_134717.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130603_134717.jpg" width='700px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130603_134717.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>20130603_134717</head>
</figure></p><p>
14h42 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_pontcharra-sur-br%C3%A9da">Pontcherra sur breda</ref> (256m) has a <hi rend="italic">grand marché bio</hi> and a scattering of alpine houses.
</p><p>
14h:49 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Goncelin">Goncelin</ref> (242) has a nice new station with some fancy lampposts. There are just a few houses on the lower part of the mountains to the left, linked by a line of electric pylons to the valley below.
</p><p>
14h58 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Brignoud">Brignoud</ref>. (229) Another typical tiny halt, this one with a lockable bike shed, and a nice pink station.
</p><p>
This train doesnt start smoothly like others. It gives a warning siren call, lurches into motion, honks defiantly, and then starts picking up speed. This end of the valley is mostly planted with young trees, though I did see a few cows.
</p><p>
1503 <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Lancey">Lancey</ref> (229) seems to have more houses, but its station looks just the same, Big timber yard, followed by quite a lot of recent housing development. Do people retire to Lancey in the heart of the Savoie to enjoy the mountain air? Presumably so. Or maybe there are jobs here? Certainly there are quite a few nice new clean factory buildings as we approach the Grenoblois conurbation. All very green and geo-thermal of course.
</p><p>
15h08 We stop at <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Grenoble-Universit%C3%A9s-Gi%C3%A8res">Gières,</ref> (216) which is also the station for Grenoble university. The train on the opposite platform is a TER bound for Geneve – nearer than you might think. Modern high rise buildings, presumably associated with the University campus, shoot by. We're still surrounded by mountains, but they no longer dominate the view, as the city of Grenoble rushes up to engulf us. Here's a motorway. Here's ...</p><p>15h16: <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_d'Echirolles">Echirolles</ref> a typical suburban station surrounded by tall blocks of flats. Could be anywhere in France, except for the mountain backdrop. And so to <ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gare_de_Grenoble">Grenoble</ref> proper.
</p><p>



<figure>
<graphic url="media/20130605_081251_v1.jpg" width='700px'><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/06/20130605_081251_v1.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>Grenoble: view from my hotel window</head>
</figure>
Grenoble: view from my hotel window

</p><p>
I am here to attend the newly constituted <hi rend="italic">conseil scientifique</hi> of the MSH de Rhones-Alpes, which is due to meet tomorrow afternoon (and not morning as I thought when planning this trip). But that's another and quite boring story. My heroic journey from the top left corner of the hexagon to the bottom right corner has been successfully accomplished, without taking a TGV or passing through Paris. Total travel cost 108.6 euros in first class (where available). Total time sitting on a train 11 and a half hours.
</p><p>
And the return journey you cry? OK, I confess. I took the TGV from Grenoble to Paris (3 hours non-stop) the Eurostar ftrom Paris to London (2.5 ditto). Total cost 172 euros. Total time sitting on a train 5.5 hours. But time isn't everything, is it... </p></div>

</body>
</text>
</TEI>
