<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>21 Days in Mauritius</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/> using CETEICEAN</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-02-02">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/mauritianMap.png"/>
    <head>Mauritian end of my timeline</head>
   </figure>
   <p>Those unfortunates unacquainted with the geography of Mauritius, an island in the Indian
    ocean, may find the above map helpful. We spent most of this trip in the bottom right hand
    corner, more specifically in the quiet old town of Mahébourg, named for Mahé de la Bourdonnais
    (1699-1753), a product of the age of reason who liked towns to be laid out on a grid pattern,
    and hardly at all in the top left hand corner, which is where the government and the tourist
    hotels and beaches hang out. In the middle, and considerably further from sea level, is the
    urban sprawl of Curepipe where Lilette's family lives, where it rains most of the time.
    <!-- https://www.mauritiuslyyours.com/post/did-mark-twain-really-say-this-about-mauritius--></p>
   <p>On this visit, I kept a handwritten diary, from which I have polished up the following choice
    extracts. </p>
   <div type="div3" rend="P11">
    <head>27 November</head>
    <p>This date, formerly known as Oblivion Monday, fell this year on a Sunday. An auspicious day,
     then, to get up infeasibly early and catch a pre-ordered taxi, with enough spare time to get
     half way there and then go back to recover at least some of the essential items we’d forgotten
     to pack. And so to Bristol Bus and Coach Station, unrecognisable since the sixties when last I
     frequented it. A pre-booked and very bored shuttle bus to Heathrow Airport through gloomy
     morning weather. Two hours along the motorway, enlivened only by eating a banana and reading
     the LRB.</p>
    <p>LHR recognisably much the same as when I used to do the transatlantic commute from here. From
     the central bus station, now somewhat reduced in facilities, we collect trolleys and descend to
     the bowels of what is now rebranded as the Elizabeth line. Tickets are free to T4 but
     automation requires that you have one. The tunnels are brightly lit, but still too big and
     vaguely threatening in the way that the approach to airport land should be. We trundle our
     trolleys out of the lift, and yes, here it is: Airportland. Home of benign repetitious public
     announcements and dreary repetitious music, populated by a different world of nationalities all
     on their best behaviour, cowed into consumerist submission by a steady drizzle of shops filled
     with things you can’t afford and don’t need, and of which you are in any case unworthy, as the
     new underclass of serving staff populating them strongly suspects. Ever wondered what it must
     have felt like to be Leonard Bast shopping up West? Never mind, it’s time for lunch. </p>
    <p>T4 is still basically a long corridor of unappealing boutiques once you have been processed
     through the security checks (on this occasion less awful than Eurostar, and much better than
     Stansted). We walk resolutely to Carluccio’s in the far corner where the muzak is almost
     painfully loud, but the food is tolerable. And so, eventually, to boarding time, getting into
     my airplane socks, and stowing myself away in my limited piece of personal space where I am to
     be confined for the next eleven hours. Let us pass in silence over the dull food and duller
     discomfort of a day-long journey confined to cattle class, noting only that it could have been
     worse. Possibly. What do you expect for £780?</p>
    <p>The whole process of landing, de-planing, rediscovering luggage, being processed by
     immigration, tracking down the taxi which is supposed to meet us, deciding what to do about it,
     all takes an hour or more, but passes for the most part in some sort of daze. A big sigh of
     relief and a gradual relaxation as we realise that, yes, we have made it, and here is
     Mahébourg, nestling in the unmistakeable lap of a sleeping lion. What’s more, it’s Monday and
     the sun is shining and … isn’t this the road to the market place ? Do I recognise this
     restaurant from years ago? Is it too late to get a bol renversé? Apparently not. What did you
     say the date was?</p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>28 November </head>
    <p>We are staying at the Auberge le Saladier on rue de la Chaux, a charming b&amp;b I found on
     le Booking. We have a large airy room on the ground floor, with comfortable bedding, functional
     plumbing, and a rather noisy fan. Our hosts are charming, chatty, and very patient. There is an
     outside terrace where we can sit and take breakfast in the fresh air, watching the other guests
     coming and going. There is fresh fruit salad, dreadful coffee, and delicious <hi>pain
     maison</hi> for breakfast, whenever we feel like having it. Supermarkets, the market, and the
     seaside promenade are within 5 minutes walk and the buses to Curepipe stop just round the
     corner. Really all rather satisfactory. The first day passes in slow motion as we recover from
     the journey, readjusting and rediscovering the tempo of Mauritian life, in which (I realise)
     hanging about waiting for something to happen is core to most experiences. The nearest
     supermarket has everything, including expensive French jam, and curious Indian convenience
     foods. And drinking water, which is currently in short supply in Maurititius, it seems.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3" rend="P12">
    <head>29 November</head>
    <p>We are not here simply to eat expensive French jam, nor indeed simply to bask in the
     sunshine. We are here also on a family visit and grand Toussaint reunion. Which means getting
     up early-ish and catching the express bus to Curepipe, so called because it takes advantage of
     a couple of bits of motorway in between the long suburban crawl through the noisy but
     picturesque streets of Rose Belle. Like her sister Nicole, Lilette has a Mauritian id card
     which entitles her to free bus travel, but I have to fork out some rupees to the bus conductor
     when he passes by.</p>
    <p>The Jan Palach bus station at Curepipe is unchanged from the last time I was here, if a
     little dingier, though its front end has been transformed by the arrival of a spanking new tram
     terminal high above our heads. The marketplace is still there and just as colourful and noisy
     as a tropical market place should be. The posh shopping arcade for the upwardly mobile is also
     still there, serving proper coffee and nice cakes, which we indulge in before Jef and Nicole
     appear, and we all then go in search of the local bus out to Les Casernes, and the first of
     several visits to the house where Lilette’s mum used to live, now occupied by her brother Alain
     alone, in the garden of which her other surviving brother Roger has built his own house. Lots
     of waiting and some domestic drama ensued (we had arrived too early, and Olive was not well)
     but family affairs are like that. For lunch, we went for a walk down the road and caught some
     delicious fresh <hi rend="italic">farata</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">snack</hi>which has
     recently opened just down the street. And we eventually got back to Mahébourg, just before
     nightfall. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3" rend="P13">
    <head>30 November</head>
    <p>A repeat of yesterday’s expedition to Curepipe, but this time we are expected. Roger has
     arranged a copious lunch for us, though we are of course late because Alain also wants to talk
     to us in his house. I am delighted to renew my acquaintance with Phoenix beer and <hi
     rend="italic">mine frit</hi> accompanied by lots of salad and washed down with very strong
     espresso. We take the bus all the way to the Mahébourg bus station on our return, which gives
     an opportunity to stroll through the market, mostly closed by now, and along the waterfront.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3" rend="P14">
    <head>1 December</head>
    <p>Today we did not go to Curepipe. Instead we took the bus to Blue Bay, or would have, had a
     taxi not appeared first. Blue Bay still closely approximates to a tropical paradise. Jef and I
     splash about in the water a bit; Nicole and Lilette natter and gossip about the creole families
     all around us. A dodgy geezer with a mobile gets soundly cussed by a young heavy who, probably
     justly, suspects him of secretly taking snaps of his bikini-clad companion. No violence, but
     lots of shouting, so we walk off in search of lunch. It’s further away than I remember it, but
     the Blue Bamboo is still in business and still does a respectable lunch. Jef and I have <hi
     rend="italic">cari cerf</hi>; Nicole has a disgusting veggie pizza; Lilette has <hi
     rend="italic">cari poisson</hi>. Of course our finances won’t permit such extravagance every
     day, but for once in a while... And then, in due course, the bus back to the market where we
     bought fruit for dinner. This could become a routine.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>2 December</head>
    <p>We stayed in bed till a luxurious 1030, and then got going very slowly. Today’s goal was to
     refill the wallet, now almost empty of rupees, by any means possible. I won’t go into the
     details, but essentially although there are thousands of the little fellas stashed away in
     Lilette’s Mauritian bank account, it’s proving tricky to get them out. Consequently, we had to
     do some currency mungeing which involved a little serious bank queuing– and until you have
     experienced a queue in a Mauritian bank, you know nothing of queuing. There is usually a polite
     policeman at the air-conditioned end of the queue who will tell you when you are permitted to
     join it. There will usually be one or two people servicing the end of the queue where things
     happen, but no guarantee that they will stay there. There will often be a crazy person who
     doesn’t really know what they are doing in the queue in the first place. But, unlike similar
     institutions in the UK, there is really very little impatience or bad temper. As I may have
     said before, Mauritius is all about waiting.</p>
    <p>Anyway, eventually the wallet feels better, and we proceed to the “Salut les copains” snack
     to make our bellies feel better too, The <hi rend="italic">cari agneau </hi>was OK, but the <hi
     rend="italic">banane flambée</hi> totally failed to ignite. Never mind, we were content to sit
     on the terrasse digesting with the other fat French expats before returning for a brief snooze
     back at the Saladier. In the cool of the evening I went out for a stroll on my own, up the hill
     to the church, then back down to the waterfront. At street corners there are little groups of
     men playing cards by candle light, which looks like it might be fun. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>3 December</head>
    <p>Today is Saturday, the day on which this year’s second <hi rend="italic">Festival Kiltir Ek
     Langaz Kréol Morisien</hi> is coming to Mahébourg. Leaflets and other media no doubt have
     promised a <hi rend="italic">Regat</hi>, as well as a <hi>Salon Kiliner, Evolision Artizanal,
     ek Gran Konser,</hi> expected to be attended by 12 to 15 0000 people. I like the sound of a
     culinary saloon, myself. However, we are slow to get going on account of the day's
     unprecedented heat, and by the time we arrive the regatta is all over. By 4 pm, there's a
     pleasant breeze from the sea and the whole length of the waterfront itself is decked with
     parasols and umbrellas over stalls selling brightly coloured clothing, and jewellery, and
     christmas toys and knick knacks of all kinds. Also a little serious ironmongery. </p>
    <p>The festival proper begins around the statue of the Swami, where barricades and uniformed
     security make sure we take the right route and presumably also deter any lowlife though at this
     time of day the crowd is mostly smartly dressed families, with lots of pretty girls and cute
     babies to distract the eye. The required route takes us past the municipal loos and a
     delightfully shady clump of trees to massive tents holding the salon kiliner, aka lots of
     Indian ladies selling freshly cooked <hi>farata</hi> and <hi>gato pimen</hi>t and <hi>mine
     frit</hi> etc. etc. Not a commercialised product in sight, unless you count the allegedly
     Cornish ice cream vans. A huge dining tent with tables and chairs is already filling up with
     diners who wish to be seated. Pausing only to buy a pair of stuffed farata, we proceed past the
     dining area to join the (as yet) smallish crowd milling around in front of an enormous
     rock-festival scale stage on which the <hi>Gran Konser</hi> is already underway. The MC
     introduces famed réunionnaise speakerine Sandra Mayotte ("she's put on weight" says Nicole
     disapprovingly) and much bouncy kréol music booms forth to general approbation. Alas though, we
     are a bit old and white and self-conscious to stay long. Instead we buy some <hi>vindaye
     poisson</hi> and <hi>achard legume</hi> to go with a ton of <hi>gato piment</hi>, which we
     carry back to the saladier for supper. The concert continues long into the night in any case,
     and we can follow it on the tv <hi>en direk</hi>. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>4 December</head>
    <p>Today being Sunday, I had a quiet morning writing up my adventures and reading Jef's
     <hi>Canard Enchainé</hi>, while Lilette and Nicole gossiped. I went for a walk about 4 pm, up
     the road to Notre Dame des Anges, on this occasion packed with worshippers celebrating (I
     realised as they brought out the coffin) a funeral. The Church has an impressive yellow tower
     and allegedly dates from 1849; its stained glass is anodyne, but its roof is held up by some
     impressive timbers and there is also a rather fine wooden statue of Pere Laval, the so-called
     Apostle of Mauritius. My walk proceeded up route Royale hopping from side to side to take
     advantage of the shade. despite traffic noise, as far as the Museum which is closed of course.
     Google maps indicates that there is a much quieter route home along a narrow residential
     street, which leads me to a corner of Mahebourg I recognise from 2007. The place we stayed on
     that occasion is still there but has been renamed, implausibly, the Chillpill. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>5 December</head>
    <p>We've been here a week, so it's clearly time to do some proper tourism. Jef has done the
     research and proposes that we should take the bus out to Vieux Grand Port where there is a
     proper museum, as well as whatever remains or has been reconstructed of the first European
     buildings in Mauritius, to wit the fort erected by Dutch mariners in the late 17th century,
     when the island was still a tropical paradise covered with ebony groves and dodos. </p>
    <p>The most visible ruins are 18th century: craggy black walls and arches mostly built of basalt
     blocks mixed with coral: very picturesque, but it's very hot and someone is noisily strimming
     the lawns. We retreat to the bungalow containing the museum building proper to contemplate the
     official version of the first settlement here, essentially a pit stop and storage locker for
     the ships of the Dutch East India company en route to the far east. They introduced bananas and
     sugar cane in the 18th century; also rats and deer. Shame about the dodo and the ebony, but
     that's the price of progress.</p>
   </div>

  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
