<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list>
<!--"2022-03-21-19:55",," I started the day at 7:30.   a taxi arrived at 8 much earlier than I had feared and whisked me chattily away to Bristol Airport  arriving at 8:30 a ridiculous time for a flight leaving at 11:50 ... the door to the roof garden was locked I could not face anything like coffee but I got on with some work sorting out eltec ROM and eating a cheese toastie.  I read about somene applying textometrie Dr Who on the plane totally incomprehensible I found myself walking through another endless Airport but this one was Irish so seems less threatening and so to a bus which proceeded slowly along the banks of the liffey to its terminus a rather fine station known as heuston  a beautiful station not too big not too small selling chocolate I could not resist the pub called  the Galway hooker actually a boat not a person anyway I had a nice lunch and got on the train was which was very pleasant if slow and bumpy doing its three hour journey across Ireland ",
-->
  <item>March 21 2022 1150 Flight Bristol to Dublin, infeasibly early due to Ryanair panick. A long
  bus ride into Dublin, but the train ride from there to Galway was nice. Greeted by the statue of
  Wilde, and overnight in the Galway Arms Inn </item>
 <item>22 March No key yet, so used archive room downstairs </item>
 <item> 23 March Get key, move into office, start pondering. </item>
 <item> 24 March Meet Justin for VPP catchup. Move out to Jameson Court apartments at the seaside.
  Until 31st </item>
 <item>1 April Dun Ri Guesthouse in Clifden. </item>
 <item>2 April punished for missing SD’s birthday by food poisoning </item>
 <item>3 April Foyles Hotel makes life much better </item>
 <item>4-9 Apr at no 53 guesthouse, close to campus. Do some work. </item>
 <item>9 apr bus to Dublin 3 hours, waiting at airport also 3 hours. Horrendous. </item>
 <item>11 apr: interviewed </item>
 <item> 2 May L goes to Maryland, and I go to St P, and thence via Paris to Tours. Tried and trusted
  routes both, and all went smoothly for once. </item>
 <item>5th May Tours-Poitiers-Limoges. Overnight at IbisBudget behind station. </item>
 <item>6 May Limoges-Gueret. TAD. </item>
 <item>14 May Gueret-Limoges, taxi (eventually) to airport for 1605 flight to EMA; no sign of speedy
  bus, so have to take slow bus, and taxi (eventually) to B’s concert. Madness. </item>
 <item>17 May Bus to EMA, flight to Limoges, taxi. Glass door incident. Stay overnight at Ibis
  budget again. </item>
 <item>18 May TAD for Two. </item>
 <item>27 May: realise that gout needs loads of drugs so take loads of ibuprofen. </item>
 <item>28 Gout gets better, hoorah </item>
 <item>29 May Loose implant declares self. Very depressed. </item>
</list>
