<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Galway Bloggage - 1</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/> using CETEICEAN</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2022-07-18">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text>
  <body>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/wanderings.png"/>
    <!--  <head>Wanderings to see the Wonders of the West</head>
-->
   </figure>
   <p>In which we discover whether it really is much better to travel hopefully than to arrive. And
    also poke gingerly the academic world to see if it will let me in. All you need to know about my
    adventures as a CLS/INFRA fellow at the National University of Ireland at Galway, since
    rebranded as plain old University of Galway, I am sorry to see. </p>
   <div>
    <head>21 March</head>
    <p> The common wisdom states that to get to Ireland Ryanair is your only man. In which, as so
     many other things, it is sadly mistaken. On my first journey to Galway, back in 2008, I was
     starting from Oxford and therefore naturally travelled by train to Holyhead via Birmingham,
     ferry to Dun Laoghaire, and train from Dublin. On my next such journey, I will explore other
     ferry options, starting from Pembroke Harbour at the other end of Wales. But for this, my first
     expedition as a wandering scholar, I bit the bullet and bought a ticket to Dublin airport.
     Which entailed a taxi at 8 am, arriving at Bristol Airport at 8:30 which is a ridiculous time
     for a flight leaving at 11:50, but Mr Ryanair made me do it. </p>
    <p>The little roof garden offering an oasis of calm in the noisy desert of Bristol Airport was
     shut for no good reason but I got on with some work sorting out some ELTeC-rom texts and eating
     a cheese toastie in one of the many seating areas. On the flight, when it finally transpired, I
     read with mounting somnolescence an incomprehensible article applying textometric techniques to
     the evolution of Dr Who. When next I woke up I found myself walking through another endless
     Airport. This one however was Irish so somehow less threatening. </p>
    <p>I proceeded to a bus which proceeded slowly along the banks of the Liffey to its terminus, a
     rather fine railway station known as Dublin Heuston. Not too big, and not too small, Heuston
     has a chocolate shop and an irresistible pub called the Galway Hooker. "I bet you get jokes
     about that from American tourists" I said to the long-suffering bar person taking my order for
     what proved to be very tasty pie and vegetable lunch. It's actually a boat not a person they
     replied. And so to the train, which was very pleasant if slow and occasionally bumpy doing its
     three hour journey across Ireland. </p>
    <p>From Galway station, it's an easy walk across Eyre Square to the quaint little shopping
     streets which I dimly remembered from 2008; I was also pleased to recognize Oscar and Eduard,
     though this version is a mere replica of <ref
     target="https://www.visitestonia.com/en/sculpture-oscar-wilde-and-eduard-vilde">the Estonian
     original</ref>, and <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/48569044">the two poets never
     actually met</ref>. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/oscarEduard.png"
      width="600px"/>
     <head>An unlikely chat between Oscar Wilde and Estonia's famous writer Eduard
      Wilde<!--; featuring
      now on stock photographs everywhere, but this is one I did--></head>
    </figure>
    <p>Last time I came to Galway, I was accommodated at the TEI's expense and in an entirely
     forgettable hotel called the Harbour Hotel, about which I have indeed forgotten everything
     including its name, (which last I have just now recovered only by trawling back through ancient
     emails) This time I have had to make my own arrangements, and on a limited budget. Which is why
     my journey today finishes at the Galway Arms, a perfectly respectable establishment offering
     reasonably priced rooms, a good pint of Guinness, and congenial company at the bar, I am
     pleased to discover. And so to bed. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>March 22 - 24</head>
    <p>My hosts in Galway have been assiduous in arranging meetings to get me started as a proper
     researcher, (by which I mean, with a key and a security card, an office and a desk of my own),
     but not for today. None the less, after investigating available coffee shops (not bad, but not
     cheap) I set off on the route advised by Google, across Nuns Island and round the cathedral, to
     investigate the NUIG campus. Which is pleasantly sunny this spring morning, lightly sprinkled
     with students and daffodils under the trees and the architecture. There is one classical
     Victorian quad, presumably for ceremonical and administrative use, and much open space
     sprinkled with assorted blocks manifesting brutalist tendencies, but not oppressive. I make my
     way to the James Hardiman Library building, which is guarded by a rather curious statue,
     apparently representing two flying penises in capes and allegedly inspired by a poem of Patrick
     Kavanagh's. I locate the Moore Institute, which is apparently closed, or inaccessible at least.
     I go back down the stairs and snoop around till I find a reading room (in Special Collections)
     which is guarded by a human being rather than a security system. Human beings (in this case a
     friendly librarian) can make exceptions for wandering scholars such as myself, so after a phone
     call or two, I am duly authorised to sit at one of the immense tables in Special Collections,
     whip out my laptop, and get online with Eduroam. Splendid. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/twinSpires.png"
      width="500px"/>
     <head>Actually, it's called "Twin Spires". Nothing to do with penises at all. Well maybe.
     </head>
    </figure>
    <p>Next day I return at 1030 prompt to receive my credentials from Iwona O'Donoguhe, the
     charming Administrator of the Moore Institute. I am sharing an office with one
     person (who doesn't seem to be there much) in the corner of a huge reading
     room on the second floor, reserved for graduates and researchers: there is a comfy chair and a desk and a view over the campus. As an
     academic person I am of course welcome to attend the book launch at 1 pm today. And a meeting
     with David Kelly, the Institute's "DH Manager", is also scheduled should I wish to ask
     questions about whatever became of the VPP project's files, which is why I am here, after all.
     Splendid. </p>
    <p>The book launch turned out to be mildly interesting, since it concerned a book about an 18th
     century actor called Thomas Macklin. The DH Manager likewise, though as suspected no revelation
     of hidden digital treasures ensued. The files they have are the files they expose on the Web,
     and (just like every IT Officer I have ever known) this one is far too busy trying to keep up
     with lunatic University IT policies to do much else. But he did slip me a copy of an SQL
     database they had derived from the VPP data some years ago, which gave me the opportunity to
     revisit and dust off skills which have languished in a very dark and dusty corner of my memory
     for many decades. </p>
   
       <p>My academic host Justin Tonra, like every other academic I have ever known, has a very
       busy timetable, but fits in time to listen to me drone on about Thomas Hailes Lacy, arranges
       a zoom meeting with the elusive Kate Mattacks, formerly research student with the original
       VPP project, and even buys me a pint at the end of the week. <figure>
       <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/justinPint.png"
        width="350px"/>
       </figure></p>
    
    <p> For further details of the academic side of this visit, see <ref
     target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2022-07-TNA_Activity_Report.pdf">the official report
     submitted to the funding body</ref>: the rest of this page focusses almost exclusively on the
     trivia of my day to day existence. Being a free floating research student in a far off land is
     a novel experience, after all. I had to find reliable venues for dinner, lunch, and morning
     coffee, find the optimal routes between my accommodation and the campus, and yes why not
     explore the famed West End of Galway as well as neighbouring tourist attractions so long as I'm
     here.</p>
    <p>Pleasant though it was, I checked out of the Galway Inn on the morning of the 24th, schlepped
     my bag along my new preferred route to campus along the banks of the river Corrib, and at the
     end of the day's hard work studenting, caught the bus out to Salthill, Galway's famed seaside
     resort, where I had reserved myself an actual apartment for the long weekend.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>25-31 March</head>
   
       <p>Salthill has really only one street more or less following the curve of Galway Bay, along
       which are scattered numerous holiday accommodations, pubs, and restaurants. It also boasts a
       couple of beaches, a casino, a fun fair, an antique diving platform from which foolish youths
       can precipitate themselves into Galway Bay, and a stone monument commemorating those who
       tried to escape <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Famine_(Ireland)">the Great
       Hunger</ref> by emigrating to the New World. The monument is one of many across Ireland
       recalling one of the more shameful consequences of British rule in Ireland. It also serves to
       recall the plight of other people reduced to the desperation of nautical emigration: and to
       remind us that there is always someone ready to profit from that desperation. </p>
    <figure>
       <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/coffinShip.png"
        width="340px"/>
       <head>See further <ref
        target="https://www.advertiser.ie/galway/article/40780/the-great-famine-in-galway">this article in a more recent issue of the Galway
        Advertiser</ref></head>
       </figure>
 
    <p>There is also of course a lengthy waterfront promenade for walking along, first in one
     direction, and then in the other, to take in the view and enjoy the sunshine, when there is
     any. Which there was for much of the weekend: I even spotted some bathers and beach loungers.
     Sunday was Mothers Day, or as it seems to be called here "Mammy's Day" so there were lots of
     mothers being taken out for an airing and the decent restaurants were all full. </p>
    <p>Come Monday morning, however, I switched to commuting mode. Most mornings, by the time I had
     got out of bed and eaten my humble breakfast, there was a bus direct to NUIG from just outside
     my luxury apartment, though finding one to make the reverse journey during the evening rush
     hour was less certain. The walk was not so bad, in any case, since it passed by a quite impressive grocery
     shop offering more of a choice for supper than Tesco. And in between, I went to my little office and banged away on my little
     computer, as might be expected. By the end of the month I felt quite justified in taking
     another little extended weekend holiday. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>1 - 9 April</head>

       <p>My internet research suggested that a bus trip to Clifden, allegedly capital city of
       Connemara, might be both amusing and cheap, as indeed it was. I stayed in a little guest
       house round the corner from the former railway station, which last has been converted to a
       Victoriana-themed restaurant/bar. Somewhat unexpectedly I ate something here which disagreed
       with me, and spent much of the next day in bed as a result. But I did eventually manage to go
       for a couple of longish walks all the same, one by the high road and one by the low, both
       featuring satisfyingly boggy scenery and views over the coastline. I did not get as far as
       the bit of bog in which Alcock and Brown crashlanded in 1919, having mistaken a patch of moss
       for some grass. Nor indeed the site of Mr Marconi's wireless telegraphy station. There are
       fine monuments to both in the sleepy centre of Clifden, which I duly observed instead. And
       there is also a very nice old fashioned pub called Foyles Hotel where I stayed for my last
       night in the far West, and whose take on the classic full Irish breakfast (shown below) I
       can whole heartedly recommend. </p> 
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/fullIrish.png"
      width="500px"/>
     <head>A classic full Irish, as served in Connemara</head>
    </figure> 
    <p>Monday rolled round, as Mondays do. I caught the bus back to Galway, and moved into a cheap
     guesthouse near the University for my last five days, which were almost routine by this time.
     Up in the morning, a cup of tea and some porridge, a pleasant walk along the banks of the
     Corrib, maybe pausing for coffee at Mr Ward's pie shop, maybe straight into my monkish cell.
     Fire up the laptop and resume the tap tap tapping. Set goals and get distracted from them.
     Review progress and discuss the way of the world occasionally with Justin over coffee. Turn up
     late for lunch, either at the staff canteen (contracted out to terrible caterers) or at the
     student feeding-troughs in the basement (noisy but filling), or (if feeling rich) at an
     off-campus coffee house. Back to work. And da capo. It's academic life. </p>
    <p>Justin persuaded me that I'd do better to take the express bus direct to Dublin airport, even
     though it took three hours, so I did that very thing. Which was a fairly awful experience,
     though far from being as awful as the ensuing three hour wait for my flight at Dublin airport.
     It's holiday time, and the airport is over run with disgruntled families whose flights have
     been, like mine, delayed by the presence of too many disgruntled families whose etc. Not for
     the first time, I resolve never again to fly from this airport. </p>
    <p>Bristol Airport, on the other hand, seemed wonderfully calm and empty, mostly because I
     wasn't trying to go anywhere except home. Which was easy: I walked out the door and there was a
     bus waiting, which accepted my Old Farts bus pass without demur, unlike the last time I passed
     through here. And so eventually back to Clifton Park Road, and my wonderfully book-lined study,
     in which a day or so later I was interviewed for the delight of CLS Infra. You can see me
     expostulating <ref target="https://youtu.be/03w1BX-jRNk">here</ref>, if you still want to know
     what the purpose of all this was, or was claimed to be. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/fameAtLast.png"/>
     <head>It must be true: I saw it on You Tube</head>
    </figure>
   </div>

 <div>  <p>   <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/wanderings-2.html">[On to Galway Part 2]</ref></p>
  <p>   <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-summary.html">[Back to Summary]</ref></p>
</div>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
