<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../diaryPrint.css" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Grand parenting</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/> </p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-01-14">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>


   <p>Though not particularly polyphiloprogenitive, I have three daughters, who have in due course
    presented me with a total of six grandchildren, to say nothing of a scattering of step children
    as well. For the avoidance of doubt, though, indulge me as I take this opportunity to present
    them to you in their spring 2022 shapes.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/paddylila.png"
     width="600px" height="600px"/>
    <head>Taken on 12 Feb, at their joint birthday party, here are Paddy, born Feb 2009, with his
     dad and Lila, born Jan 2010. They have just blown out the candles on a joint birthday cake.
    </head>
   </figure>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/louisharvey.png"
     width="600px"  height="600px"/>
    <head>Taken on 15 May, here are Louis, born June 2011, and Harvey, born Aug 2016, and their dad.
     They are probably shooting something. </head>
   </figure>
   <!-- <table>
    <row>
     <cell> <figure>
      <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/leon.png"
       width="400px"/>
      </figure></cell>
     <cell> <figure>
      <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/coco.png"
       width="300px"/>
      </figure></cell>
     <cell> <figure>
      <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/daphne.png"
       width="390px"/>
      </figure> </cell>
    </row>
    <row role="label">
     <cell>Taken on 24 April after his birthday party, here is Leon, born 2019 with his mum.
      Definitely time for bed. </cell>
     <cell> <hi>Taken on 11 March, here is Coco, born July 2020 and her mum, just looking cute.
      </hi></cell>
     <cell role="label"> <hi>Also taken on 11 March, here is Daphne, born Aug 2016 , and the pizza
      she made. </hi></cell>
    </row>
   </table>-->

   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/leon.png"
     width="400px"/>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/coco.png"
     width="300px"/>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/daphne.png"
     width="390px"/>
    <head> <table>
     <row role="label">
      <cell>Taken on 24 April after his birthday party, here is Leon, born 2020 with his mum.
       Definitely time for bed. </cell>
      <cell> <hi>Taken on 11 March, here is Coco, born July 2020 and her mum, just looking cute.
       </hi></cell>
      <cell role="label"> <hi>Also taken on 11 March, here is Daphne, born Aug 2016 , and the pizza
       she made. </hi></cell>
     </row>
     </table></head>
   </figure>
   <p>My three daughters and their respective families are quite seriously geographically dispersed,
    which means that we have had to become correspondingly expert in the available public transport routes
    to Nottingham, Maryland (E15), and Stourton (near Shipston on Stour), respectively. Also cheap
    accommodation thereabouts, where there is any (full disclosure: there isn't). </p>
   <p>There are persistent rumours that two-thirds of them plan to move to Bristol soon, but it hasn't
    happened yet. All of which made at least the first part of 2022 quite busy what with birthday
    parties and sundry occasions on which grand-parenting duties (usually baby sitting) must be
    undertaken. Here's a brief checklist: <list>
    <label>January 21-24</label>
    <item>We went to Maryland to look after Coco, Daphne, and Al so that Elizabeth could join her
     sisters for a much-needed sisterly spa weekend. <ref
     target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/structions.png"> Full
     instructions</ref> were provided and a splendid time was had by all.</item>
    <label>Feb 12th</label>
    <item>Mass excursion to Stourton for a joint celebration of Lila's and Paddy's 12th birthdays:
     there was cake and chocolate (see photo above) </item>
    <label>March 11-16</label>
    <item>To Maryland again. Daphne made a pizza (see above), learned how to make <foreign>bol
     renversé</foreign>, and lost a tooth; Coco just looked cute. </item>
    <!--<label>April 14-15</label>
    <item>Lila etc visit</item>-->
    <label>23-24 April</label>
    <item>To Stourton village hall for Leon's 2nd birthday party: there were lots of nibbles and
     balloons and everyone got quite tired. <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/seesaw.png"
      width="800px"/>
     <head>There was also a seesaw </head>
     </figure></item>
    <label>July 10th</label>
    <item> Panos and Rebecca, our upstairs neighbours, organized a splendid joint birthday barbecue,
     for which Belinda played appropriate tunes on her fiddle. Sarah and Belinda then whisked us
     away to the dirty bird and a birthday dinner at Cote. <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/belinda.png"
      width="400px"/>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/dirtyBird.png"
      width="400px"/>
     <head>Belinda (left) and Sarah (right)</head>
     </figure> </item>
    <label>27-30 July</label>
    <item>Coco and Daphne came to stay for a few days, during which there was a grand birthday
     picnic in our back garden, and also an expedition to St Andrew's Park for splashing purposes. <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/picnic.png"
      width="600px"/>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/standrews.png"
      width="450px"/>
     </figure></item>

    <label>21-22 Oct</label>
    <item>We were back in Maryland, baby-sitting again the weekend before the big family outing (see
     next entry). </item>
    <label>24-28 October</label>
    <item> This year we decided to celebrate our 50th wedding anniversary, our golden jubilee, no
     less, by inviting everyone to a four night stay in <ref
     target="https://www.forest-house.co.uk/">a charming country house in the Forest of Dean</ref>,
     formerly the property of an iron master called Mushet. As well as many meals, <ref
     target="https://photos.app.goo.gl/sYRpUvzH7YbA49Fz6">many photos</ref>, and much rushing about
     by Mr and Mrs Shiny, this memorable event featured <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Family/"
     >four talks on family history</ref> by me, one for each of five decades</item>
    <label>3-6 November</label>
    <item>I always seem to be away for Belinda's birthday, so this year I suggested she move it
     back a week. We spent a few days in Arnold and Sherwood, doing exciting things like accompany
     her to the opticians and having lunch. There were also sparklers, which Harvey
     appreciated.</item>
     <figure>
      <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/sparkler.png"/>
     </figure>
    <label>20-31 Dec</label>
    <item>We returned from Mauritius on 19 December. Next day, I noticed that the price of Mauritian
     lychees at Reg the Veg was 1.25 GBP for 100g, as opposed to the top price of 100 MUR a kilo I
     had become accustomed to paying in Curepipe market. Ah well. I dug out the winter woolies, put
     all the short sleeved shirts in the wash, and prepared for a European winter. The various
     necessities making up Xmas lunch were all delivered on time, and Sarah and Kev and company came
     to share a traditional, if slightly reduced, Xmas lunch with us and the Smallwoods, by courtesy
     of whom this photo, to show that some things never change. </item>
    </list></p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/xmasLunch.png"/>
   </figure>
   <p> <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-summary.html">[Back to Summary]</ref> </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
