<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
1<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Blogging</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished draft</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>AMOW</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2022-07-18">First draft started</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
      
   <text>
      <body>
        <div> <head>Wanderings to see the Wonders of the West</head>
         <head>Sunday</head>
         <p>At three PM on Sunday, as the Great British Heatwave started to roll into action, I reluctantly decided that the bus  to Temple Meads was not going to put in an appearance any time soon, and so headed off to the station on foot. It’s downhill all the way, and there is some shade and a light breeze, so I make a reasonably speedy descent to the bottom of Park Street, at which point I remember that this is Harbour Festival Time, so the centre of Bristol is full of partly clothed  families having a good time. Or not. I continue through King Square, ignoring a uniformed person’s request to show that my back pack is innocent of alcohol. I swing on down the right side of the junction opposite Temple Meads, and here I am in good time for the 8 minute journey via  Filton to  Bristol Parkway, which I occupy by sweating profusely and reflecting not for the first time on the regrettable absence of a decent rail network in Bristol. At BPW I detrain and proceed up the stairs and down the stairs and across the overheated car park to a makeshift tent, along with several dozen fellow travellers. A coach loads us up and off we go, across the other  Severn Bridge, and into Newport station, hoorah. The train to Cardiff is only a bit late, and I would be really quite relaxed about that if it were not for alarming intelligence brought to me by the wonders of the internet.</p>
         <p>Yes, dear reader, the 1800 Cardiff train to Pembroke has been cancelled today. As have several others, of course, since one timetable disaster usually involves another. At Cardiff station (am impressive piece of architecture which I would relish in happier circs) the only advice on offer seems to be to get the next train to Swansea, so I join a number of other disconsolate travellers on platform 4, looking in vain for reliable information, even in Welsh.  Should I continue to wait? Should I  overnight in Carnarvon and try again? My knowledge of the Welsh train network expands beyond belief.  Various trains arrive and depart for other destinations, but eventually after an hour or so, the 1855 to Swansea appears and on I get. This is a GWR train just like the ones we know and love, featuring the same robotic voices making the same robotic announcements, though the station names about which the robot lady sound so pleased are of course different.</p>
         <p>Anyway, here we are at Swansea, also a rather fine looking railway station, and I am contemplating the departures board which offers two trains for onward travel in the right direction, either of which would get me to Carmarthen, but neither of which will get me to Pembroke today. At which point FATE in the form of a friendly fellow passenger intervenes. Mr Evans (I am just guessing that was his name) is of the view that GWR is obliged to get us to Pembroke tonight, since that is the ticket we have bought, and thinks this will be arranged if we insist. To my considerable amazement when we put this theory to the test by asking a uniformed person at Swansea station what we can do to get to Pembroke, he adds us to a list of people on his clipboard, and within 5 minutes has organized a fleet of taxis to get us all home. So the last part of my journey was an hour’s bouncing along in a taxi cab at break neck speed, rather than trundling the long rail route. And behold, I arrived in my Pembroke hotel, at almost exactly the same time as I would have done by train. Which was nice. The Post House Hotel failing to offer dinner, the only available source of food was the Coop across the road from which I purchased coleslaw and a pork pie and welsh cakes. And so, exhausted, to a comfortable bed. </p>
         </div><div><head>Monday</head>
         <p>My enjoyment of Pembroke was somewhat darkened by the realisation as I tidied up my packing that I had somehow contrived not to bring a passport. Dark thoughts of calling off the expedition and somehow repeating yesterday’s journey in reverse were entertained only briefly, as even with no breakfast I was pretty sure that Ireland and the UK are still in the Common Travel Area, which means I need produce only an official photo card showing my identity, for which a bus pass  should suffice. Whether Ryanair knows that remains to be seen on the return trip.</p>
         <p>The full Welsh breakfast eventually appeared, a bit late and lacking in sausage, but no matter. I went for a walk along the millpond, as advised by mr Jones (if that was his name) yesterday, and within five minutes Pembroke Castle hove into view. (Entry cost 6 quid). This is bigger than Chepstow, but less fun for me, since it mostly seems to consist of battlements accessible only by means of vertigo-inducing  spiral staircase, though it is also decorated with life size replicas  of celebrated medieval characters. In the middle of the castle but properly visible only by flying over it is an enormous lawn which has been decorated with a map of Wales. There is also a huge tower or keep with satisfyingly gothic pigeons flying about inside it and blue lighting effects. The queue for ice cream in the shop was too long to contemplate by the time I got there so I made my excuses and left. Collecting my bag, I staggered off to the station just in time to catch a (delayed) train to Pembroke Dock,  </p>
         <p>Not to be confused with Pembroke, this is a largely 19th  century construction dating from the time when the Empire maintained a garrison here, as well as dock yards, and flying boats and all sorts of military matters. It’s also very hot,still.  I  slog on with the aid of Google maps, crossing the town centre to get to the Irish Ferry terminal which is the only currently functional part of the naval splendours that once were, though there are plans to redevelop it. It’s a long slog on a hot day, so I am content to sit inside the terminal building  with a cup of coffee waiting to board and not thinking too much about whether or not my bus pass will do the trick. Boarding of a dozen or so foot passengers duly takes place, enlivened slightly by being sniffed at by police dogs, and  security checks carried out by officials without benefit of  any other kind of scanners, hoorah. And my bus pass did the trick!! Oh, said the lady, that’s an unusual one. Is it from London?</p>
         <p>And so to the ferry, which is inexplicably Greek and full of Irish families. I have paid 16 quid extra for the privilege of sitting in a lounge away from the herd, but they are in there anyway, gorging on free cakes and other refreshments. Never mind. Time to ponder family dynamics as manifesting themselves around me. And so across St Georges Channel to the Irish coast, and the exciting moment when we foot passengers were told to rejoin our bus so that we may be unloaded in due course. A fat garda wants to know our nationalities, but other than that there are no further liminal formalities, and I am free to find my way out of Rosslare Europort, which nestles beneath a very large cliff.  On what is still a decidedly warm evening. I trek along the foot path, alongside the massive lorries till we get to the brow of the hill, and there is the blessed saint martin as expected, and thus, in due course, St Martin’s Guest House. Which is run by an elderly gent with a rheumy eye and a gammy leg: I feel instantly at home, especially after discarding my very sweaty shirt. A shower and a nice clifftop walk walk unencumbered by bag or sweaty shirt provedrestorative, as did the Guinness I had before a healthy  chicken salad dinner. And so to bed.</p></div><div>
         <head>Tuesday</head>
         <p>On the morning of the third day, I got up very early indeed, failed to find any breakfast, but did catch the 0910  bus from Rosslare to Waterford, an interesting journey though not on an empty stomach. At Waterford, which is a big place, I took too long to figure out where the train station was (back over the bridge) to get more than a cursory coffee, before boarding train number 1,  the 11 am to Dublin Heuston. I have just realised that any Irish railway station of any significance has a cognomenon commemorating some hero of the Irish Uprising of 1916 shot down by the Brits. Thus Dublin's stations commemorate both Heuston and Connolly (and indeed Pearse), Limerick has Colbert, Cork has Kent, Galway has Ceannte, Sligo has MacDiarmada, while Waterford has Plunkett. Bray station commemorates Daly, Dundalk commemorates Clarke, Kilkenny station is also known as MacDonagh, Dun Laoghaire as Mallin, Tralee as Casement, Wexford as Ohanrahan, and Drogheda is named MacBride. Look them up on Wikipedia if you don’t believe me.</p>
         <p>Irish trains are now all rather smart and clean and made in Japan, but they have no at-seat catering, not even a cup of tea.  Announcements are made in Irish and English though not with quite such monotonous regularity as GWR. It’s holiday time and the train to Dublin is busy with holiday makers. I am anyway too hungry to do any serious work, so I watch the scenery trundle by. Lots of countryside. Lots of cows and sheep. At one point I saw a whole flock (herd?) of black sheep, which was nice. Various implausibly named stations and a few that I didn’t know really existed. After an hour or so, it’s time to change trains, so I get off at Kildare, along with many others, and wait for train number 2, a short hop of 20 minutes  to Portarlington,  where they are rebuilding the station, which is nice, but there is still nothing to eat, and the next train is not due for a good 40 minutes.  However, a helpful person informs me that there is a supermarket five minutes walk away across the sun-drenched car park outside the station,  which I am delighted to find there is indeed So my long delayed breakfast is of a slightly doubtful burger washed down with coconut juice, and an apple, consumed sitting in the sun waiting for the train to Galway…</p>
         <p>Which here it at last is! Train number 3 trundles across yet more scenery and famous places  (including Athlone, which used to feature on Radio dials, but commemorates no-one) to the watery landscape around Galway Bay. Galway is currently enjoying its own version of the Harbourside Festival madness with which this odyssey began, which seems only appropriate. But at least it’s not quite as hot. I reflect on how much worse this journey might have been if I’d had a suitcase to schlep as well as my trusty back pack. I reflect on how well organised Irish trains are. I reflect on the familiarity of my rediscovered route across Galway city to the University environs. But mostly I reflect on how nice it will be to get a proper fish dinner at Hooked, if they have space (which they did, though not till the next day). </p></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
