<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Galway Bloggage - 2</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/> using CETEICEAN</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2022-07-18">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text>
  <body>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/wanderings.png"/>
    <!--  <head>Wanderings to see the Wonders of the West</head>
-->
   </figure>
   <p>In which we discover whether it really is much better to travel hopefully than to arrive. And
    also poke gingerly the academic world to see if it will let me in. All you need to know about my
    adventures as a CLS/INFRA fellow at the National University of Ireland at Galway, since
    rebranded as plain old University of Galway, I am sorry to see. </p>


   <div>
    <head>Sunday 17 July</head>
    <p>At three PM on Sunday, as the Great British Heatwave started to roll into action, I
     reluctantly decided that the bus to Temple Meads was not going to put in an appearance any time
     soon, and so headed off to the station on foot. It’s downhill all the way, and there is some
     shade and a light breeze, so I make a reasonably speedy descent to the bottom of Park Street,
     at which point I remember that this is Harbour Festival Time, so the centre of Bristol is full
     of partly clothed families having a good time. Or not. I continue through King Square, ignoring
     a uniformed person’s request to show that my back pack is innocent of alcohol. I swing on down
     the right side of the junction opposite Temple Meads, and here I am in good time for the 8
     minute journey via Filton to Bristol Parkway, which I occupy by sweating profusely and
     reflecting not for the first time on the regrettable absence of a decent rail network in
     Bristol. At BPW I detrain and proceed up the stairs and down the stairs and across the
     overheated car park to a makeshift tent, along with several dozen fellow travellers. A coach
     loads us up and off we go, across the other Severn Bridge, and into Newport station, hoorah.
     The train to Cardiff is only a bit late, and I would be really quite relaxed about that if it
     were not for alarming intelligence brought to me by the wonders of the internet.</p>
    <p>Yes, dear reader, my next target, the 1800 train from Cardiff to Pembroke, has been cancelled
     today. As have several others, of course, since one timetable disaster usually involves
     another. At Cardiff station (an impressive piece of architecture which I would relish in
     happier circs) the only advice on offer seems to be to get the next train to Swansea, so I join
     a number of other disconsolate travellers on platform 4, looking in vain for reliable
     information, even in Welsh. Should I continue to wait? Should I overnight in Carnarvon and try
     again? My knowledge of the Welsh train network expands as various trains arrive and depart for
     other destinations, but eventually after an hour or so, the 1855 to Swansea appears and on I
     get. This is a GWR train just like the ones we know and love, featuring the same robotic voices
     making the same robotic announcements, though the station names about which the robot lady
     sounds so pleased are of course different, and come in two languages.</p>
    <p>Anyway, here we are at Swansea (aka Abertawe), also a rather fine looking railway station,
     and I am contemplating the departures board which offers two trains for onward travel in the
     right direction, either of which would get me to Carmarthen, but neither of which will get me
     to Pembroke today. At which point FATE in the form of a friendly fellow passenger intervenes.
     Mr Evans (I am just guessing that was his name) is of the view that GWR is obliged to get us to
     Pembroke tonight, since that is the ticket we have bought, and thinks this will be arranged if
     we insist, look you. To my considerable amazement when we put this theory to the test by asking
     a uniformed person at Swansea station what we can do to get to Pembroke, he adds us to a list
     of people on his clipboard, and within 5 minutes has organized a fleet of taxis to get us all
     home. So the last part of my journey was an hour’s bouncing along in a taxi cab at break neck
     speed, rather than trundling the long rail route. And behold, I arrived in my Pembroke hotel,
     at almost exactly the same time as I would have done by train. Which was nice. The Post House
     Hotel failing to offer dinner, the only available source of food was the Coop across the road
     from which I purchased coleslaw and a pork pie and welsh cakes. And so, exhausted, to a
     comfortable bed. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>Monday 18 July</head>
    <p>My enjoyment of Pembroke was somewhat darkened by the realisation as I tidied up my packing
     that I had somehow contrived not to bring a passport. Dark thoughts of calling off the
     expedition and thus repeating yesterday’s journey in reverse were entertained only briefly, as
     even with no breakfast I was pretty sure that Ireland and the UK are still in the Common Travel
     Area, which means I need produce only an official photo card showing my identity, for which a
     bus pass should suffice. Whether Ryanair knows that remains to be seen on the return trip.</p>
    <p>The full Welsh breakfast eventually appeared, a bit late and lacking in sausage, but no
     matter. I went for a walk along the millpond, as advised yesterday by Mr Jones (if that was his
     name), and within five minutes Pembroke Castle hove into view. Entry costs 6 quid presumably
     because this is much bigger than Chepstow castle which I saw last week. On the other hand, it
     is less fun for me, since it mostly seems to consist of battlements accessible only by means of
     vertigo-inducing spiral staircase, implausibly decorated with life size replicas of celebrated
     medieval characters. In the middle of the castle but visible only by flying over it is an
     enormous lawn which has been decorated with a map of Wales. There is also a huge tower or keep
     with satisfyingly gothic pigeons flying about inside it and blue lighting effects. The queue
     for ice cream in the shop was too long to contemplate by the time I got there so I made my
     excuses and left. Collecting my bag, I staggered off to the station just in time to catch a
     (delayed) train to Pembroke Dock, </p>
    <p>Not to be confused with Pembroke, this is a largely 19th century construction dating from the
     time when the Empire maintained a garrison here, as well as dock yards, and flying boats and
     all sorts of military matters. It’s very hot but with the aid of Google maps, I plot a course
     across the town centre to the Irish Ferry terminal which is the only currently functional part
     of the naval splendours that once were, though there are plans to redevelop it. It’s a long
     slog on a hot day, so I am content to sit inside the terminal building with a cup of coffee
     waiting to board and not thinking too much about whether or not my bus pass will do the trick.
     Boarding of a dozen or so foot passengers duly takes place, enlivened slightly by being sniffed
     at by police dogs, and security checks carried out by officials without benefit of any other
     kind of scanners, hoorah. And my bus pass did the trick!! Oh, said the lady, that’s an unusual
     one. Is it from London?</p>
    <p>And so to the ferry, which is inexplicably Greek and full of Irish families. I have paid 16
     quid extra for the privilege of sitting in a lounge away from the herd, but they are in there
     anyway, gorging on free cakes and other refreshments. Never mind. An opportunity to ponder the
     dynamics of family relationships, as manifesting themselves around me. And so across St Georges
     Channel to the Irish coast, and the exciting moment when we foot passengers were told to rejoin
     our bus so that we may be unloaded in due course. A fat garda wants to know our nationalities,
     but other than that there are no further liminal formalities, and I am free to find my way out
     of Rosslare Europort, which nestles beneath a very large cliff. On what is still a decidedly
     warm evening. I trek along the foot path, alongside the massive lorries till we get to the brow
     of the hill, and there is the blessed saint martin as expected, and thus, in due course, St
     Martin’s Guest House. Which is run by an elderly gent with a rheumy eye and a gammy leg: I feel
     instantly at home, especially after discarding my very sweaty shirt. A shower and a nice
     clifftop walk walk unencumbered by bag or sweaty shirt proved restorative, as did the Guinness
     I had before a healthy chicken salad dinner. And so to bed.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>Tuesday 19 July</head>
    <p>On the morning of the third day, I got up very early indeed, failed to find any breakfast,
     but did catch the 0910 bus from Rosslare to Waterford, an interesting journey though less so on
     an empty stomach. At Waterford I took too long to work out where the train station was (back
     over the bridge) to get more than a cursory coffee, before boarding train number 1, the 11 am
     to Dublin Heuston. I have just realised that any Irish railway station of any significance has
     a cognomenon commemorating some hero of the Irish Uprising of 1916 shot down by the Brits. Thus
     Dublin's stations commemorate both Heuston and Connolly (and indeed Pearse), Limerick has
     Colbert, Cork has Kent, Galway has Ceannte, Sligo has MacDiarmada, while Waterford rejoices in
     Plunkett. Bray station commemorates Daly, Dundalk commemorates Clarke, Kilkenny station is also
     known as MacDonagh, Dun Laoghaire as Mallin, Tralee as Casement, Wexford as Ohanrahan, and
     Drogheda is named MacBride. Look them up on Wikipedia if you don’t believe me.</p>
    <p>Irish trains are now all rather smart and clean and made in Japan, but they have no at-seat
     catering, not even a cup of tea. Announcements are made in Irish and English though not with
     quite such monotonous regularity as on GWR. It’s holiday time and the train to Dublin is busy
     with holiday makers. I am anyway too hungry to do any serious work, so I watch the scenery
     trundle by. Lots of countryside. Lots of cows and sheep. At one point I saw a whole flock
     (herd?) of black sheep, which was nice. Various implausibly named stations and a few that I
     didn’t know really existed. After an hour or so, it’s time to change trains, so I get off at
     Kildare, along with many others, and wait for train number 2, a short hop of 20 minutes to
     Portarlington, where they are rebuilding the station, which is nice, but there is still nothing
     to eat, and my next train is not due for a good 40 minutes. However, a helpful person informs
     me that there is a supermarket five minutes walk away across the sun-drenched car park outside
     the station, which I am delighted to find there is indeed. So my long delayed breakfast is of a
     slightly doubtful burger washed down with coconut juice, and an apple, consumed sitting in the
     sun waiting for the train to Galway. </p>
    <p>Which here it at last is! Train number 3 trundles across yet more scenery and famous places
     (including Athlone, which used to feature on Radio dials but commemorates no-one, and Kilkenny
     which is nothing to do with South Park) to the watery landscape around Galway Bay. Galway is
     currently enjoying its own version of the Harbourside Festival madness with which this odyssey
     began, which seems only appropriate. But at least it’s not quite as hot. I reflect on how much
     worse this journey might have been if I’d had a suitcase to schlep as well as my trusty back
     pack. I reflect on how well organised Irish trains are. I reflect on the familiarity of my
     rediscovered route across Galway city to the University environs. But mostly I reflect on how
     nice it will be to get a proper fish dinner at Hooked, if they have space (which they did,
     though not till the next day). </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>20 - 23 July</head>
    <p>The plan was to spend the rest of the week and maybe the weekend tying up at least a few of
     the many Lacy loose ends, but events continued to conspire against this. Firstly it was the
     first week of everyone in Galway going on holiday. On the one hand, this meant that my usual
     haunts in the library were pleasantly quiet, populated only by a scattering of graduate
     students long past despairing of ever meeting their deadlines, but that other parts of the
     campus was being over-run with graduation ceremonies, proud parents etc. On the other hand, the
     week in prospect coincided with general public rejoicing, as Galway geared up for an
     international arts festival, the Galway Races, and the Irish national football championships,
     inter alia: all of which made it difficult to find a table in a restaurant or a quiet corner in
     a bar at any reasonable time of day or night. But the main obstacle to concentrating on the job
     in the hand was of course the Passport Problem. </p>
    <p>My plan had been to take a Ryanair flight direct from Knock to Bristol. Would Ryanair be as
     accomodating as Irish Ferries when it came to identifying myself? Sadly no. Their website
     states unequivocally that only a passport would do, and mine was in a drawer in Bristol. Some
     frantic googling and late night Whatsapping ensued, as a consequence of which Lilette took the
     passport with her to Nottingham, Belinda printed out the required documentation, and Mr UPS
     promised he would collect it from her for delivery to me in my student lodging in Galway within
     a couple of days. In the event however only the first part of this promise was kept. I won't
     detail the frustrating and occasionally self-contradictory explanations provided by the UPS
     officials I spoke to at various unknown locations in cyberspace, but the consensus seemed to be
     that since I had failed to provide the right accompanying documentation, my package was still
     locked away in the UK, at Nottingham airport it transpired eventually. To her eternal credit,
     Belinda went and shouted on my behalf at an actual UPS person until they agreed to relinquish
     their grasp on the package and get it delivered to me in Bristol, which is where I was by the
     time this whole torrid drama had played itself out. And how, dear reader, did I manage to get
     back into the UK without a passport? By using a different airline, of course. Hats off to Aer
     Lingus, which allowed me to board a flight from Shannon to London without fuss.</p>
    <p>Despite this, I did manage to complete a fairly coherent and mostly true report on my stint
     as a CLS Fellow (final version <ref
     target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Papers/2022-GalwayReport.pdf"
     >here</ref>). That status (and an intro from Justin Tonra) gave me the opportunity to engage in
     a pleasant and instructive discussion with Professor David O'Shaughnessy before leaving. And I
     also enjoyed what I believe is known as the craic in one of the many Galway pubs offering
     musical evening entertainment.</p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/craic.png"
      width="600px"/>
     <head>It's a serious business</head>
    </figure>
    <p>And so to my revised journey home, which involved nothing more complicated than a long
     distance bus from Galway to Shannon, a lengthy wait there, an uneventful flight to Heathrow
     (the best kind), and a tedious two hour bus ride from there to Bristol. I was so pleased to get
     back and not be on a bus any more that I walked all the way home from the bus station. </p>
   </div>
   <div>  <p>   <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/wanderings-1.html">[Back to Galway Part 1]</ref></p>
    <p>   <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-summary.html">[Back to Summary]</ref></p>
   </div>   
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
