<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Blogging</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2022-07-18">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text>
  <body>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/wanderings.png"/>
    <!--  <head>Wanderings to see the Wonders of the West</head>
-->
   </figure>
   <p>In which we discover whether it really is much better to travel hopefully than to arrive. And
    also poke gingerly the academic world to see if it will let me in. All you need to know about my
    adventures as a CLS/INFRA fellow at the National University of Ireland at Galway, since
    rebranded as plain old University of Galway, I am sorry to see. </p>
   <div>
    <head>21 March</head>
    <p> The common wisdom states that to get to Ireland Ryanair is your only man. In which, as so
     many other things, it is sadly mistaken. On my first journey to Galway, back in 2008, I was
     starting from Oxford and therefore naturally travelled by train to Holyhead via Birmingham,
     ferry to Dun Laoghaire, and train from Dublin. On my next such journey, I will explore other
     ferry options, starting from Pembroke Harbour at the other end of Wales. But for this, my first
     expedition as a wandering scholar, I bit the bullet and bought a ticket to Dublin airport.
     Which entailed a taxi at 8 am, arriving at Bristol Airport at 8:30 which is a ridiculous time
     for a flight leaving at 11:50, but Mr Ryanair made me do it. </p>
    <p>The little roof garden offering an oasis of calm in the noisy desert of Bristol Airport was
     shut for no good reason but I got on with some work sorting out some ELTeC-rom texts and eating
     a cheese toastie in one of the many seating areas. On the flight, when it finally transpired, I
     read with mounting somnolescence an incomprehensible article applying textometric techniques to
     the evolution of Dr Who. When next I woke up I found myself walking through another endless
     Airport. This one however was Irish so somehow less threatening. </p>
    <p>I proceeded to a bus which proceeded slowly along the banks of the Liffey to its terminus, a
     rather fine railway station known as Dublin Heuston. Not too big, and not too small, Heuston
     has a chocolate shop and an irresistible pub called the Galway Hooker. "I bet you get jokes
     about that from American tourists" I said to the long-suffering bar person taking my order for
     what proved to be very tasty pie and vegetable lunch. It's actually a boat not a person they
     replied. And so to the train, which was very pleasant if slow and occasionally bumpy doing its
     three hour journey across Ireland. </p>
    <p>From Galway station, it's an easy walk across Eyre Square to the quaint little shopping
     streets which I dimly remembered from 2008; I was also pleased to recognize Oscar and Eduard,
     though this version is a mere replica of <ref
     target="https://www.visitestonia.com/en/sculpture-oscar-wilde-and-eduard-vilde">the Estonian
     original</ref>, and <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/48569044">the two poets never
     actually met</ref>. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url=""/>
     <head>An unlikely chat between Oscar Wilde and Estonia's famous writer Eduard Wilde; featuring
      now on stock photographs everywhere, but this is one I did</head>
    </figure>
    <p>Last time I came to Galway, I was accommodated at the TEI's expense and in an entirely
     forgettable hotel called the Harbour Hotel, about which I have indeed forgotten everything
     including its name, (which last I have just now recovered only by trawling back through ancient
     emails) This time I have had to make my own arrangements, and on a limited budget. Which is why
     my journey today finishes at the Galway Arms, a perfectly respectable establishment offering
     reasonably priced rooms, a good pint of Guinness, and congenial company at the bar, I am
     pleased to discover. And so to bed. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>March 22 - 24</head>
    <p>My hosts in Galway have been assiduous in arranging meetings to get me started as a proper
     researcher, (by which I mean, with a key and a security card, an office and a desk of my own),
     but not for today. None the less, after investigating available coffee shops (not bad, but not
     cheap) I set off on the route advised by Google, across Nuns Island and round the cathedral, to
     investigate the NUIG campus. Which is pleasantly sunny this spring morning, lightly sprinkled
     with students and daffodils under the trees and the architecture. There is one classical
     Victorian quad, presumably for ceremonical and administrative use, and much open space
     sprinkled with assorted blocks manifesting brutalist tendencies, but not oppressive. I make my
     way to the James Hardiman Library building, which is guarded by a rather curious statue,
     apparently representing three flying penises in capes. I locate the Moore Institute, which is
     apparently closed, or inaccessible at least. I go back down the stairs and snoop around till I
     find a reading room (in Special Collections) which is guarded by a human being rather than a
     security system. Human beings (in this case a friendly librarian) can make exceptions for
     wandering scholars such as myself, so after a phone call or two, I am duly authorised to sit at
     one of the immense desks in Special Collections, whip out my laptop, and get online with
     Eduroam. Splendid. </p>

    <p>Next day I return at 1030 prompt to receive my credentials from Iwona O'Donoguhe, the
     charming Administrator of the Moore Institute Administrator. I am sharing an office with one
     person (who doesn't seem to be there much) in the corner of a huge research student reading
     room on the second floor: there is a comfy chair and a desk and a view over the campus. As an
     academic person I am of course welcome to attend the book launch at 1 pm today. And a meeting
     with David Kelly, the Institute's "DH Manager", is also scheduled should I wish to ask
     questions about whatever became of the VPP project's files, which is why I am here, after all.
     Splendid. </p>
    <p>The book launch turned out to be mildly interesting, since it concerned a book about an 18th
     century actor called Thomas Macklin. The DH Manager likewise, though as suspected no revelation
     of hidden digital treasures ensued. The files they have are the files they expose on the Web,
     and (just like every IT Officer I have ever known) this one is far too busy trying to keep up
     with lunatic University IT policies to do much else. But he did slip me a copy of an SQL
     database they had derived from the VPP data some years ago, which gave me the opportunity to
     revisit and dust off skills which have languished in a very dark and dusty corner of my memory
     for many decades. </p>
    <p>My academic host Justin Tonra, like every other academic I have ever known, has a very busy
     timetable, but fits in time to listen to me drone on about Thomas Hailes Lacy, arranges a zoom
     meeting with the elusive Kate Mattacks, formerly research student with the original VPP
     project, and even buys me a pint at the end of the week. For further details of the academic
     side of this visit, see <ref
     target="https://lb42.github.io/Lacy/2022-07-TNA_Activity_Report.pdf">the official report
     submitted to the funding body</ref>: the rest of this report focusses almost exclusively on the
     trivia of my day to day existence. Being a free floating research student in a far off land is
     a novel experience, after all. I had to find reliable venues for dinner, lunch, and morning
     coffee, find the optimal routes between my accomodation and the campus, and yes why not explore
     the famed West End of Galway as well as neighbouring tourist attractions so long as I'm here. </p>
    <p>Pleasant though it was, I checked out of the Galway Inn on the morning of the 24th, schlepped
     my bag along my new preferred route to campus along the banks of the river Corrib, and at the
     end of the day's hard work studenting, caught the bus out to Salthill, Galways famed seaside
     resort, where I had reserved myself an actual apartment for the long weekend.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>25-31 March</head>
    <p>Salthill has really only one street more or less following the curve of Galway Bay, along
     which are scattered numerous holiday accomodations, pubs, and restaurants. It also boasts a
     couple of beaches, a casino, a fun fair, an antique diving platform from which foolish youths
     can precipitate themselves into Galway Bay, and a stone monument commemorating those who tried
     to escape <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Famine_(Ireland)">the Great
     Hunger</ref> by sailing for the New World from here. As this 1849 press cutting shows <figure>
     <graphic url="coffinShip.jpg"/>
     <head>Clipping from the <ref
      target="https://www.advertiser.ie/galway/article/40780/the-great-famine-in-galway">Galway
      Advertiser</ref></head>
     </figure>, then as now emigration by boat was not the easiest of options. </p>
    <p>There is also of course a lengthy promenade for walking along, first in one direction, and
     then in the other, to take in the view and enjoy the sunshine, when there is any. Which there
     was for much of the weekend. Sunday was Mothers Day, or as it seems to be called here "Mammy's
     Day" so there were lots of mothers being taken out for an airing and the decent restaurants
     were all full. </p>
    <p>Come Monday morning, however, I switched to commuting mode. Most mornings, by the time I had
     got out of bed and eaten my humble breakfast, there was a bus direct to NUIG from just outside
     my luxury apartment, though finding one to make the reverse journey during the evening rush
     hour was less certain. The walk was not so bad, taking in a couple of quite impressive grocery
     shops as it did. And in between, I went to my little office and banged away on my little
     computer, as might be expected. By the end of the month I felt quite justified in taking
     another little extended weekend holiday. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>1 - 9 April</head>
    <p>My internet research suggested that a bus trip to the Clifden, allegedley capital city of Connemara,  might be both amusing and cheap, as indeed it was. I stayed in a little guest house round the corner from
    the former railway station, now a bar where I ate something ill-advised and spent much of the day in bed as a result. But I eventually managed to go for a long walk all the same, and enjoyed some boggy scenery
    and views over the coastline, but did not get as far as the bit of bog in which Alcock and Brown crashlanded in 1919, having mistaken a patch of moss for some grass. Nor indeed the site of Mr Marconi's wireless 
    telegraphy station. There are fine monuments to both in the sleepy centre of Clifden, which I duly noted instead. And there is also a very nice old fashioned pub called Foyles Hotel where I stayed for my last night in the far West.
    </p><p>Monday rolled round, as Mondays do, and I caught the bus back to Galway, and moved into a cheap guesthouse near the University for my last five days, which were almost routine by this time. 
   </p>
    <list>
     <item> 24 March Meet Justin for VPP catchup; zoom with Kate. Move out to Jameson Court
      apartments at the seaside. Until 31st </item>
     <item>1 April Dun Ri Guesthouse in Clifden. </item>
     <item>2 April punished for missing SD’s birthday by food poisoning </item>
     <item>3 April Foyles Hotel makes life much better </item>
     <item>4-9 Apr at no 53 guesthouse, close to campus. Do some work. </item>
     <item>9 apr bus to Dublin 3 hours, waiting at airport also 3 hours. Horrendous. </item>
     <item>11 apr: interviewed </item>
    </list>
   </div>



   <div>
    <head>Sunday 17 July</head>
    <p>At three PM on Sunday, as the Great British Heatwave started to roll into action, I
     reluctantly decided that the bus to Temple Meads was not going to put in an appearance any time
     soon, and so headed off to the station on foot. It’s downhill all the way, and there is some
     shade and a light breeze, so I make a reasonably speedy descent to the bottom of Park Street,
     at which point I remember that this is Harbour Festival Time, so the centre of Bristol is full
     of partly clothed families having a good time. Or not. I continue through King Square, ignoring
     a uniformed person’s request to show that my back pack is innocent of alcohol. I swing on down
     the right side of the junction opposite Temple Meads, and here I am in good time for the 8
     minute journey via Filton to Bristol Parkway, which I occupy by sweating profusely and
     reflecting not for the first time on the regrettable absence of a decent rail network in
     Bristol. At BPW I detrain and proceed up the stairs and down the stairs and across the
     overheated car park to a makeshift tent, along with several dozen fellow travellers. A coach
     loads us up and off we go, across the other Severn Bridge, and into Newport station, hoorah.
     The train to Cardiff is only a bit late, and I would be really quite relaxed about that if it
     were not for alarming intelligence brought to me by the wonders of the internet.</p>
    <p>Yes, dear reader, my next target, the 1800 Cardiff train to Pembroke, has been cancelled
     today. As have several others, of course, since one timetable disaster usually involves
     another. At Cardiff station (an impressive piece of architecture which I would relish in
     happier circs) the only advice on offer seems to be to get the next train to Swansea, so I join
     a number of other disconsolate travellers on platform 4, looking in vain for reliable
     information, even in Welsh. Should I continue to wait? Should I overnight in Carnarvon and try
     again? My knowledge of the Welsh train network expands as various trains arrive and depart for
     other destinations, but eventually after an hour or so, the 1855 to Swansea appears and on I
     get. This is a GWR train just like the ones we know and love, featuring the same robotic voices
     making the same robotic announcements, though the station names about which the robot lady
     sounds so pleased are of course different, and multiform.</p>
    <p>Anyway, here we are at Swansea (aka Abertawe), also a rather fine looking railway station,
     and I am contemplating the departures board which offers two trains for onward travel in the
     right direction, either of which would get me to Carmarthen, but neither of which will get me
     to Pembroke today. At which point FATE in the form of a friendly fellow passenger intervenes.
     Mr Evans (I am just guessing that was his name) is of the view that GWR is obliged to get us to
     Pembroke tonight, since that is the ticket we have bought, and thinks this will be arranged if
     we insist. To my considerable amazement when we put this theory to the test by asking a
     uniformed person at Swansea station what we can do to get to Pembroke, he adds us to a list of
     people on his clipboard, and within 5 minutes has organized a fleet of taxis to get us all
     home. So the last part of my journey was an hour’s bouncing along in a taxi cab at break neck
     speed, rather than trundling the long rail route. And behold, I arrived in my Pembroke hotel,
     at almost exactly the same time as I would have done by train. Which was nice. The Post House
     Hotel failing to offer dinner, the only available source of food was the Coop across the road
     from which I purchased coleslaw and a pork pie and welsh cakes. And so, exhausted, to a
     comfortable bed. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>Monday 18 July</head>
    <p>My enjoyment of Pembroke was somewhat darkened by the realisation as I tidied up my packing
     that I had somehow contrived not to bring a passport. Dark thoughts of calling off the
     expedition and somehow repeating yesterday’s journey in reverse were entertained only briefly,
     as even with no breakfast I was pretty sure that Ireland and the UK are still in the Common
     Travel Area, which means I need produce only an official photo card showing my identity, for
     which a bus pass should suffice. Whether Ryanair knows that remains to be seen on the return
     trip.</p>
    <p>The full Welsh breakfast eventually appeared, a bit late and lacking in sausage, but no
     matter. I went for a walk along the millpond, as advised by Mr Jones (if that was his name)
     yesterday, and within five minutes Pembroke Castle hove into view. Entry costs 6 quid
     presumably because this is much bigger than Chepstow castle which I saw last week. On the other
     hand, it is less fun for me, since it mostly seems to consist of battlements accessible only by
     means of vertigo-inducing spiral staircase, implausibly decorated with life size replicas of
     celebrated medieval characters. In the middle of the castle but visible only by flying over it
     is an enormous lawn which has been decorated with a map of Wales. There is also a huge tower or
     keep with satisfyingly gothic pigeons flying about inside it and blue lighting effects. The
     queue for ice cream in the shop was too long to contemplate by the time I got there so I made
     my excuses and left. Collecting my bag, I staggered off to the station just in time to catch a
     (delayed) train to Pembroke Dock, </p>
    <p>Not to be confused with Pembroke, this is a largely 19th century construction dating from the
     time when the Empire maintained a garrison here, as well as dock yards, and flying boats and
     all sorts of military matters. It’s very hot but with the aid of Google maps, I plot a course
     across the town centre to the Irish Ferry terminal which is the only currently functional part
     of the naval splendours that once were, though there are plans to redevelop it. It’s a long
     slog on a hot day, so I am content to sit inside the terminal building with a cup of coffee
     waiting to board and not thinking too much about whether or not my bus pass will do the trick.
     Boarding of a dozen or so foot passengers duly takes place, enlivened slightly by being sniffed
     at by police dogs, and security checks carried out by officials without benefit of any other
     kind of scanners, hoorah. And my bus pass did the trick!! Oh, said the lady, that’s an unusual
     one. Is it from London?</p>
    <p>And so to the ferry, which is inexplicably Greek and full of Irish families. I have paid 16
     quid extra for the privilege of sitting in a lounge away from the herd, but they are in there
     anyway, gorging on free cakes and other refreshments. Never mind. Time to ponder family
     dynamics as manifesting themselves around me. And so across St Georges Channel to the Irish
     coast, and the exciting moment when we foot passengers were told to rejoin our bus so that we
     may be unloaded in due course. A fat garda wants to know our nationalities, but other than that
     there are no further liminal formalities, and I am free to find my way out of Rosslare
     Europort, which nestles beneath a very large cliff. On what is still a decidedly warm evening.
     I trek along the foot path, alongside the massive lorries till we get to the brow of the hill,
     and there is the blessed saint martin as expected, and thus, in due course, St Martin’s Guest
     House. Which is run by an elderly gent with a rheumy eye and a gammy leg: I feel instantly at
     home, especially after discarding my very sweaty shirt. A shower and a nice clifftop walk walk
     unencumbered by bag or sweaty shirt proved restorative, as did the Guinness I had before a
     healthy chicken salad dinner. And so to bed.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>Tuesday 19 July</head>
    <p>On the morning of the third day, I got up very early indeed, failed to find any breakfast,
     but did catch the 0910 bus from Rosslare to Waterford, an interesting journey though less so on
     an empty stomach. At Waterford I took too long to figure out where the train station was (back
     over the bridge) to get more than a cursory coffee, before boarding train number 1, the 11 am
     to Dublin Heuston. I have just realised that any Irish railway station of any significance has
     a cognomenon commemorating some hero of the Irish Uprising of 1916 shot down by the Brits. Thus
     Dublin's stations commemorate both Heuston and Connolly (and indeed Pearse), Limerick has
     Colbert, Cork has Kent, Galway has Ceannte, Sligo has MacDiarmada, while Waterford has
     Plunkett. Bray station commemorates Daly, Dundalk commemorates Clarke, Kilkenny station is also
     known as MacDonagh, Dun Laoghaire as Mallin, Tralee as Casement, Wexford as Ohanrahan, and
     Drogheda is named MacBride. Look them up on Wikipedia if you don’t believe me.</p>
    <p>Irish trains are now all rather smart and clean and made in Japan, but they have no at-seat
     catering, not even a cup of tea. Announcements are made in Irish and English though not with
     quite such monotonous regularity as GWR. It’s holiday time and the train to Dublin is busy with
     holiday makers. I am anyway too hungry to do any serious work, so I watch the scenery trundle
     by. Lots of countryside. Lots of cows and sheep. At one point I saw a whole flock (herd?) of
     black sheep, which was nice. Various implausibly named stations and a few that I didn’t know
     really existed. After an hour or so, it’s time to change trains, so I get off at Kildare, along
     with many others, and wait for train number 2, a short hop of 20 minutes to Portarlington,
     where they are rebuilding the station, which is nice, but there is still nothing to eat, and
     the next train is not due for a good 40 minutes. However, a helpful person informs me that
     there is a supermarket five minutes walk away across the sun-drenched car park outside the
     station, which I am delighted to find there is indeed. So my long delayed breakfast is of a
     slightly doubtful burger washed down with coconut juice, and an apple, consumed sitting in the
     sun waiting for the train to Galway. </p>
    <p>Which here it at last is! Train number 3 trundles across yet more scenery and famous places
     (including Athlone, which used to feature on Radio dials but commemorates no-one, and Kilkenny
     which is nothing to do with South Park) to the watery landscape around Galway Bay. Galway is
     currently enjoying its own version of the Harbourside Festival madness with which this odyssey
     began, which seems only appropriate. But at least it’s not quite as hot. I reflect on how much
     worse this journey might have been if I’d had a suitcase to schlep as well as my trusty back
     pack. I reflect on how well organised Irish trains are. I reflect on the familiarity of my
     rediscovered route across Galway city to the University environs. But mostly I reflect on how
     nice it will be to get a proper fish dinner at Hooked, if they have space (which they did,
     though not till the next day). </p>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>20 - 23 July</head>
    <p>The plan was to spend the rest of the week and maybe the weekend tying up at least a few of
     the many Lacy loose ends, but events continued to conspire against this. Firstly it was the
     first week of everyone in Galway going on holiday. On the one hand, this meant that my usual
     haunts in the library were pleasantly quiet, populated only by a scattering of graduate
     students long past despairing of ever meeting their deadlines, except when the campus was being
     over-run with graduation ceremonies, proud parents etc. On the other hand, the week in prospect
     coincided with general public rejoicing, as Galway geared up for an international arts
     festival, the Galway Races, and the Irish national football championships, inter alia: all of
     which made it difficult to find a table in a restaurant or a quiet corner in a bar at any
     reasonable time of day or night. But the main obstacle to concentrating on the job in the hand
     was of course the Passport Problem. </p>
    <p>My plan had been to take a Ryanair flight direct from Knock to Bristol. Would Ryanair be as
     accomodating as Irish Ferries when it came to identifying myself? Sadly no. Their website
     states unequivocally that only a passport would do, and mine was in a drawer in Bristol. Some
     frantic googling and late night Whatsapping ensued, as a consequence of which Lilette took the
     passport with her to Nottingham, Belinda printed out the required documentation, and Mr UPS
     promised he would collect it from her for delivery to me in my student lodging in Galway within
     a couple of days. In the event however only the first part of this promise was kept. I won't
     detail the frustrating and occasionally self-contradictory explanations provided by the UPS
     officials I spoke to at various unknown locations in cyberspace, but the consensus seemed to be
     that since I had failed to provide the right accompanying documentation, my package was still
     locked away in the UK, at Nottingham airport it transpired eventually. To her eternal credit,
     Belinda went and shouted on my behalf at an actual UPS person until they agreed to relinquish
     their grasp on the package and get it delivered to me in Bristol, which is where I was by the
     time this whole torrid drama had played itself out. And how, dear reader, did I manage to get
     back into the UK without a passport? By using a different airline, of course. Hats off to Aer
     Lingus, which allowed me to board a flight from Shannon to London without fuss.</p>
    <p>Despire this, I did manage to complete a fairly coherent report on my stint as a CLS Fellow
     (final version <ref
     target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Papers/2022-GalwayReport.pdf"
     >here</ref>). That status (and an intro from Justin Tonra) gave me the opportunity to engage in
     a pleasant and instructive discussion with Professor David OShaughnessy before leaving. And I
     also enjoyed what I believe is known as the craik in one of the many Galway pubs offering
     musical evening entertainment.</p>
    <p>And so to my revised journey home, which involved nothing more complicated than a long
     distance bus from Galway to Shannon, a lengthy wait there, an uneventful flight to Heathrow
     (the best kind), and a tedious two hour bus ride from there to Bristol. I was so pleased to get
     back and not be on a bus any more that I walked all the way home from the bus station. </p>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
