<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>21 Days in Mauritius</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-02-02">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/mauritianMap.png"/>
    <head>Mauritian end of my time line</head>
   </figure>
   <p>Those unfortunates unacquainted with the geography of Mauritius, an island in the Indian
    ocean, may find the above map helpful. We spent most of this trip in the bottom right hand
    corner, more specifically in the quiet old town of Mahébourg, named for Mahé de la Bourdonnais
    (1699-1753), a product of the age of reason who liked towns to be laid out on a grid pattern. We
    did not on this occasion bother with the top left hand corner, which is where the government and
    the tourist hotels and beaches hang out. In the middle, and considerably further from sea level,
    is the urban sprawl of Curepipe where many Mauritians, including Lilette's family, live and
    work, even though it rains most of the time.
    <!-- https://www.mauritiuslyyours.com/post/did-mark-twain-really-say-this-about-mauritius--></p>
   <p>On this visit, I kept a handwritten diary, from which I have polished up the following choice
    extracts. </p>
   <div type="div3" rend="P11">
    <head>27 November</head>
    <p>This date, formerly known as Oblivion Monday, fell this year on a Sunday. An auspicious day,
     then, to get up infeasibly early and catch a pre-ordered taxi, with enough spare time to get
     half way there and then go back to recover at least some of the essential items we’d forgotten
     to pack. And so to Bristol Bus and Coach Station, unrecognisable since the sixties when last I
     frequented it. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="suitcases.png" width="300px"/>
     <head>Miss Suitcase 2022 arrives at Bristol Bus and Coach Station</head>
    </figure>
    <p>A pre-booked and very bored shuttle bus shuttles us to Heathrow Airport through the gloomy
     morning weather. Two hours along the motorway, enlivened only by eating a banana and reading
     the LRB. Heathrow Airport is recognisably much the same as when I used to do the transatlantic
     commute from here. From the central bus station, now somewhat reduced in facilities, we collect
     trolleys and descend to the bowels of what is now re-branded as the Elizabeth line. Tickets to
     Terminal 4 are free but automation requires that you have one. The tunnels are brightly lit,
     but still too big and vaguely threatening in the way that the approach to Airportland should
     be.</p>
    <p> We trundle our trolleys out of the lift, and yes, here it is: Airportland. Home of benign
     repetitious public announcements and dreary repetitious music, populated by a different world
     of nationalities all on their best behaviour, cowed into consumerist submission by a steady
     drizzle of shops filled with things you can’t afford and don’t need, and of which you are in
     any case unworthy, as the new underclass of serving staff populating them strongly suspects.
     Ever wondered what it must have felt like to be Leonard Bast shopping up West? Never mind, it’s
     time for lunch. </p>
    <p>T4 is still basically a long corridor of unappealing boutiques once you have been processed
     through the security checks (on this occasion less awful than Eurostar, and much better than
     Stansted). We walk resolutely to Carluccio’s in the far corner where the muzak is almost
     painfully loud, but the food is tolerable. And so, eventually, to boarding time, getting into
     my airplane socks, and stowing myself away in my limited piece of personal space where I am to
     be confined for the next eleven hours. Let us pass in silence over the dull food and duller
     discomfort of a day-long journey confined to cattle class, noting only that it could have been
     worse. Possibly. What do you expect for £780?</p>
    <p>The whole process of landing, de-planing, rediscovering luggage, being processed by
     immigration, panicking at not immediately finding the taxi which is supposed to meet us, tracking him down by phone, 
     all takes an hour or more, but passes for the most part in some sort of daze. A big sigh of
     relief and a gradual relaxation as we realise that, yes, we have made it, and here is
     Mahébourg, nestling unmistakeably in the lap of a sleeping lion. What’s more, it’s Monday and
     the sun is shining and … isn’t this the road to the market place ? Do I recognise this
     restaurant from years ago? Is it too late to get a <foreign>bol renversé</foreign>? Apparently not. What did you
     say the date was?</p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>28 November </head>
    <p>We are staying at the Auberge le Saladier on rue de la Chaux, a charming b&amp;b I found on
     le Booking. We have a large airy room on the ground floor, with comfortable bedding, functional
     plumbing, and a rather noisy fan. Our hosts are charming, chatty, and very patient. There is an
     outside terrace where we can sit and take breakfast in the fresh air, watching the other guests
     coming and going. There is fresh fruit salad, dreadful coffee, and delicious <hi>pain
     maison</hi> for breakfast, whenever we feel like having it. Supermarkets, the market, and the
     seaside promenade are within 5 minutes walk and the buses to Curepipe stop just round the
     corner. Also just round the corner is a rather fine flamboyant as a landmark.  Really all rather satisfactory. 
     <figure>
      <graphic url="flamboyant.png" width="300px"/>
      <head>Landmark flamboyant tree on the corner of La Chaux street</head>
     </figure>
     
     The first day passes in slow motion as we recover from
     the journey, readjusting and rediscovering the tempo of Mauritian life, in which (I realise)
     hanging about waiting for something to happen is core to most experiences. The nearest
     supermarket has everything, including expensive French jam, and curious Indian convenience
     foods. And drinking water, which is currently in short supply at Le Saladier, it seems.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3" rend="P12">
    <head>29 November</head>
    <p>We are not here simply to eat expensive French jam, nor indeed simply to bask in the
     sunshine. We are here also on a family visit and grand Toussaint reunion. Which means getting
     up early-ish and catching the express bus to Curepipe, so called because it takes advantage of
     a couple of bits of motorway in between the long suburban crawl through the noisy but
     picturesque streets of Rose Belle. Like her sister Nicole, Lilette has a Mauritian id card
     which entitles her to free bus travel, but I have to fork out some rupees to the bus conductor
     when he passes by.</p>
    <p>The Jan Palach bus station at Curepipe is unchanged from the last time I was here, if a
     little dingier, though its front end has been transformed by the arrival of a spanking new tram
     terminal high above our heads. The marketplace is still there and just as colourful and noisy
     as a tropical market place should be. The posh shopping arcade for the upwardly mobile is also
     still there, serving proper coffee and nice cakes, which we indulge in before Jef and Nicole
     appear, and we all then go in search of the local bus out to Les Casernes, and the first of
     several visits to the house where Lilette’s mum used to live, now occupied by her brother Alain
     alone, in the garden of which her other surviving brother Roger has built his own house. Lots
     of waiting and some domestic drama ensued (we had arrived too early, and Olive was not well)
     but family affairs are like that. For lunch, we went for a walk down the road and caught some
     delicious fresh <hi rend="italic">farata</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">snack</hi> which has
     recently opened just down the street. And we eventually got back to Mahébourg, just before
     nightfall. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3" rend="P13">
    <head>30 November</head>
    <p>A repeat of yesterday’s expedition to Curepipe, but this time we are expected. Roger has
     arranged a copious lunch for us, though we are of course late because Alain also wants to talk
     to us in his house. I am delighted to renew my acquaintance with Phoenix beer and <hi
     rend="italic">mine frit</hi> accompanied by lots of salad and washed down with very strong
     espresso. We take the bus all the way to the Mahébourg bus station on our return, which gives
     an opportunity to stroll through the market, mostly closed by now, and along the waterfront.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3" rend="P14">
    <head>1 December</head>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/blueBay.png"
      width="800px"/>
     <head>"What a groove! a tropical paradise!"</head>
    </figure>
    <p>Today we did not go to Curepipe. Instead we took the bus to Blue Bay, or would have, had a
     taxi not appeared first. Blue Bay still closely approximates to a tropical paradise. Jef and I
     splash about in the water a bit; Nicole and Lilette natter and gossip about the creole families
     all around us. A dodgy geezer with a mobile gets soundly cussed by a young heavy who, probably
     justly, suspects him of secretly taking snaps of his bikini-clad companion. No violence, but
     lots of shouting, so we walk off in search of lunch. It’s further away than I remember it, but
     the Blue Bamboo is still in business and still does a respectable lunch. Jef and I have <hi
     rend="italic">cari cerf</hi>; Nicole has a disgusting veggie pizza; Lilette has <hi
     rend="italic">cari poisson</hi>. Of course our finances won’t permit such extravagance every
     day, but for once in a while... And then, in due course, the bus back to the market where we
     bought fruit for dinner. This could become a routine.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>2 December</head>
    <p>We stayed in bed till a luxurious 1030, and then got going very slowly. Today’s goal was to
     refill the wallet, now almost empty of rupees, by any means possible. I won’t go into the
     details, but essentially although there are thousands of the little fellas stashed away in
     Lilette’s Mauritian bank account, it’s proving tricky to get them out. Consequently, we had to
     do some currency mungeing which involved a little serious bank queuing– and until you have
     experienced a queue in a Mauritian bank, you know nothing of queuing. There is usually a polite
     policeman at the air-conditioned end of the queue who will tell you when you are permitted to
     join it. There will usually be one or two people servicing the end of the queue where things
     happen, but no guarantee that they will stay there. There will often be a crazy person who
     doesn’t really know what they are doing in the queue in the first place. But, unlike similar
     institutions in the UK, there is really very little impatience or bad temper. As I may have
     said before, Mauritius is all about waiting.</p>
    <p>Anyway, eventually the wallet feels better, and we proceed to the “Salut les copains” snack
     to make our bellies feel better too, The <hi rend="italic">cari agneau </hi>was OK, but the <hi
     rend="italic">banane flambée</hi> totally failed to ignite. Never mind, we were content to sit
     on the terrasse digesting with the other fat French expats before returning for a brief snooze
     back at the Saladier. In the cool of the evening I went out for a stroll on my own, up the hill
     to the church, then back down to the waterfront. At street corners there are little groups of
     men playing cards by candle light, which looks like it might be fun. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>3 December</head>
    <p>Today is Saturday, the day on which this year’s second <hi rend="italic">Festival Kiltir Ek
     Langaz Kréol Morisien</hi> is coming to Mahébourg. Leaflets and other media no doubt have
     promised a <hi rend="italic">Regat</hi>, as well as a <hi>Salon Kiliner, Evolision Artizanal,
     ek Gran Konser,</hi> expected to be attended by 12 to 15 0000 people. I like the sound of a
     culinary saloon, myself. However, we are slow to get going on account of the day's
     unprecedented heat, and by the time we arrive the regatta is all over. By 4 pm, there's a
     pleasant breeze from the sea and the whole length of the waterfront itself is decked with
     parasols and umbrellas over stalls selling brightly coloured clothing, and jewellery, and
     christmas toys and knick knacks of all kinds. Also a little serious ironmongery. </p>
    <p>The festival proper begins around the statue of the Swami, where barricades and uniformed
     security make sure we take the right route and presumably also deter any lowlife though at this
     time of day the crowd is mostly smartly dressed families, with lots of pretty girls and cute
     babies to distract the eye. The required route takes us past the municipal loos and a
     delightfully shady clump of trees to massive tents holding the <hi>salon kiliner</hi>, aka lots
     of Indian ladies selling freshly cooked <hi>farata</hi> and <hi>gato pimen</hi> and <hi>mine
     frit</hi> etc. etc. Not a commercialised product in sight, unless you count the allegedly
     Cornish ice cream vans. A huge dining tent with tables and chairs is already filling up with
     diners who wish to be seated. Pausing only to buy a pair of stuffed <hi>farata</hi>, we proceed
     past the dining area to join the (as yet) smallish crowd milling around in front of an enormous
     rock-festival scale stage on which the <hi>Gran Konser</hi> is already underway. The MC
     introduces famed speakerine Sandra Mayotte ("she's put on weight" says Nicole disapprovingly)
     and much bouncy kréol music booms forth to general approbation. Alas though, we are a bit old
     and white and self-conscious to stay long. Instead we buy some <hi>vindaye poisson</hi> and
     <hi>achard legume</hi> to go with a ton of <hi>gato pimen</hi>, which we carry back to the
     saladier for supper. The concert continues long into the night in any case, and we can follow
     it on the tv <hi>en direk</hi>. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>4 December</head>
    <p>Today being Sunday, I had a quiet morning writing up my adventures and reading Jef's
     <hi>Canard Enchainé</hi>, while Lilette and Nicole gossiped. I went for a walk about 4 pm, up
     the road to Notre Dame des Anges, on this occasion packed with worshippers celebrating (I
     realised as they brought out the coffin) a funeral. The Church has an impressive yellow tower
     and allegedly dates from 1849; its stained glass is anodyne, but its roof is held up by some
     impressive timbers with carved angels on them and there is also a rather fine wooden statue of Pere Laval, the so-called
     Apostle of Mauritius. My walk proceeded up route Royale hopping from side to side to take
     advantage of the shade. despite traffic noise, as far as the Museum which is closed of course.
     Google maps indicates that there is a much quieter route home along a narrow residential
     street, which leads me to a corner of Mahébourg I recognise from 2007. The place we stayed on
     that occasion is still there but has been renamed, implausibly, the Chillpill. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>5 December</head>
    <p>We've been here a week, so it's clearly time to do some proper tourism. Jef has done the
     research and proposes that we should take the bus out to Vieux Grand Port where there is a
     proper museum, as well as whatever remains or has been reconstructed of the first European
     buildings in Mauritius, to wit the fort erected by Dutch mariners in the late 17th century,
     when the island was still a tropical paradise covered with ebony groves and dodos. </p>
    <p>The most visible ruins are 18th century: craggy black walls and arches mostly built of basalt
     blocks mixed with coral: very picturesque, but it's very hot and someone is noisily strimming
     the lawns. We retreat to the bungalow containing the museum building proper to contemplate the
     official version of the first settlement here, essentially a pit stop and storage locker for
     the ships of the Dutch East India company en route to and from the far east. They introduced
     bananas and sugar cane and slaves to work it in the 18th century; also rats and deer. Shame
     about the dodo and the ebony, but that's the price of progress.</p>
    <p>We get onto a very crowded bus back towards Mahébourg, but then off it again at the turn off
     for Ferney, since the plan is to have lunch at the <ref
     target="https://www.ferney.mu/ferney-falaise-rouge/">Ferney Falaise Rouge</ref>, which is a
     posh restaurant perched on top of some red cliffs overlooking the bay. We have to walk along a
     palm-lined track across a cane field to get there but it's worth the effort. Proper lunch is
     provided in European-style luxury, and, as we are early enough to have avoided the rush of
     motorized tourists, the usual waiting passes very comfortably sitting under a palm tree with a
     cool drink. I had <hi>cochon marron roti</hi> with mash, since you ask, and for dessert an
     unexpectedly copious panna cotta with sour berries which was delicious. After which, walking
     back to the main road to get the bus was quite hard work, but we managed it somehow. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>6 December</head>
    <p>An early start for Jef and Nicole, who are going to do something mysterious in Curepipe
     again. And also a slightly less early one for us, as Lilette has thought of a new way of
     getting access to her thousands of rupees. So off we go to the nearest branch of the MCI Bank,
     and join the queue outside for the queue inside, under control of polite but firm policeman, as
     aforesaid. It only takes 40 minutes to progress from the outside queue to the interior (air
     conditioned) queue, at which point I leave Lilette to her fate and go for a coffee at Le
     Basilic. Another half hour later, she reappears laden with rupees, and ready for lunch, which
     we take in an aged Chinese restaurant near the market: it was called Le dragon de chine when I
     was last here in 2007, and presumably still is, though the signage has disappeared and the
     verandah seems to have shrunk. But it still serves possibly the best <hi>bol renversé</hi> in
     Mahébourg, for a mere 150 rupees. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/bolrenverse.png"
      width="800px"/>
     <head>Arguably the best bol renversé in  Mahébourg</head>
    </figure>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>7 December</head>
    <p>An essential part of any visit to Mauritius is the traditional island tour, which unrolls
     more or less as follows. First, catch your taxi man. This was arranged for us by our hosts at
     Le Saladier. Next decide which direction you wish to go in, i.e. clockwise or anti-clockwise
     round the island. Finally prepare a list of interesting points you wish to visit and hope your
     taxi man knows where they are. Hope that the weather will be kind, but don't hold your breath.
     On this occasion, the skies opened as soon as we set off, which meant that our first few
     beach-visits were wind-swept and mostly cursory, which is a pity as these were fine beaches. We
     made a tentative stop at the Saint Aubin estate to visit the old distillery, but the entrance
     fee discouraged us. Eventually, the rain stopped, and the sun came out long enough for us to
     appreciate the views at Gris Gris beach, where there is no reef so the rocks are satisfactorily
     battered by torrential waves, direct from the Indian Ocean. Which is why it is called <hi>La
     roche qui pleure</hi>. Just up the road to Souillac from here there once lived that rarest of
     birds, a Mauritian poet. His name was Robert Edward Hart (1891-1954) and they have turned his
     house (which has splendidly romantic views over the raging ocean) into a museum. You can see
     his type writer and his violin as well as his desk, and lots of remnants of his poetic career.
     It's a rather fine building too, made of coral and local stones, and seems to have been
     renovated since I last visited it. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/typeWriter.png"
      width="800px"/>
     <head>Robert Edward Hart's typewriter</head>
    </figure>
    
    <p>For our lunch stop we went to La Batelage at the port of Souillac. This used to be a very
     posh restaurant looking over an estuary which was once an important landing point for shipping
     from Port Louis. The 18th century warehouse with its fine 19th century fittings is still there,
     but the quality of service in the restaurant has declined considerably. Much Mauritian waiting
     and some tasty fish (capitaine) later, we resumed our day out with a visit to a new attraction:
     the Parc de la Vallee des Couleurs. This is an example of what the eco-tourist industry can do
     with a large expanse of land unsuitable for agriculture: it is all carefully constructed foot
     paths going up and down and round about, flirting with some well channelled rocky streams.
     There are curious four wheel bikes to hire and ziplines for thrills, and there are
     multicoloured sands to gawp at, if you like that kind of thing. The view over the park and down
     to the coast about 10 km away is pretty impressive though, even when it starts raining again.
     But it's an exhausting business being a tourist, and I think I may have dozed off as we zoomed
     back along the Southern coast road, via Chemin Grenier and Surinam. Or did we really stop and
     watch at the spot where there are always people hanging on the wire fence to see the airplanes
     at SSR Airport land and take off and trundle about? </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>8 December</head>
    <p>My manuscript diary and my memory both agree that this was a day of inactivity until at 5 pm
     prompt Yves Tonta turns up in his motor and drives us all to his very smart new house in Beau
     Vallon, an area which I remember as being largely under construction. Now there are lots of
     smart new houses here in what is effectively an up-market residential suburb of Mahébourg, but
     the simple grid system of the old town has been abandoned in favour of other more exotic
     patternings: or so it seems as Yves twists and turns his Toyota through the dark. The inside of
     his home is also very decorative, with two distinct verandahs adjoining each other and both
     securely gated. Security seems to be rather important. Anyway, we sit as invited round a round
     table and are served beer and gajak in the form of dainty tuna sandwiches and some kind of
     chicken roll, served by the third Mrs Yves, who is apparently an ex ballerina of South African
     origins, judging from her accent, though she has lived in Mauritius for years. Much domestic
     chatting ensued, none of which seemed to require or engage any contribution from me. Instead,
     it was largely enlivened by photos of loverly grandchildren and old acquaintances on Yves'
     tablet. And at the end of the evening Mauritian waiting on a grand scale before we are offered
     a lift home. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>9 December</head>
    <p>By the time I turn out for the usual breakfast, Jef and Nicole have long since disappeared on
     the earliest possible bus to Kirpip. The day is appropriately commemorated by a birthday card
     from Lilette and a beep from the only one of my facebook friends not currently asleep in Europe
     (tx Chris). And then we set off across town for another raid on Lilette's horde of rupees at
     the MCB. The queue is very much shorter than last time and they have put up a splendid
     christmas tree so I leave Lilette to it, and nip round the corner to get my hair cut at the
     little salon de coiffure I noticed three days ago. Much refreshed and comparatively dapper as
     well as rich, we do a little desultory shopping at the market and then proceed to birthday
     lunch at Les Copains D'abord, the posh resto on the sea front we have been saving up for this
     occasion. The veg tempura is a bit soggy, but the fish in coconut sauce does not disappoint. My
     phone starts pinging as Europe wakes up: my daughters get online and Facebook prods my social
     media contacts into action, which is all rather nice. We go for yet another stroll along the
     Waterfront, enjoying the breeze, despite lowering gray skies and a temperature of 27. There's
     no-one much about this afternoon: a half-hearted beggar; two or three tourist couples like us;
     a fisherman who tells us he can't take his boat out because the sea is too rough, or he'd be
     delighted to offer us his services. Lilette politely tells him to go away in kreol, but she is
     only a woman, so he takes no notice till I perform the International Fuck Off gesture. Down by
     the obelisk at the end of the waterfront a small group of slightly drunk ne'er-do-wells are
     hanging out; a couple of ambulatory Mauritian policemen stroll past and look at them severely.
     Their mere presence is enough. The obelisk, by the way, commemorates the Battle of Grand Port,
     apparently the only naval battle of the Napoleonic era in which Johnny Frenchman
     comprehensively defeated the marauding Brits, largely because the British commander either
     lacked or ignored local intelligence about the rocks in the bay, and consequently ran his ships
     aground well within range of French pot shots. (<ref
     target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Grand_Port">The Wikipedia article</ref> is
     comprehensive and more readable than the novel about it by Patrick O'Brian) </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>10 December</head>
    <p>Copain or not, something in yesterday's lunch definitely upset my digestion, so I spent my
     birthday evening and most of this morning lying in bed taking occasional sips of water and
     feeling sorry for myself. Everyone else had the good sense to go away and, at Nicole's
     suggestion, lunch at the local KFC. I do manage to get to the supermarket around 4 pm, where I
     buy more water, yoghurt, and dahi, all of which my digestive system seems to be willing to
     accept. In the rest of the evening, I watch with mounting incredulity a surge of "likes" on my
     Facebook birthday posting, as the greetings pile in from people whose name I mostly recognise,
     but of whom I have seen nothing for many years. Is this what my social life has been reduced
     to, and how it's going to be henceforth ? Not too sure I like the sound of that, but it's still
     nice to be pinged so frequently and so warmly.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>11 December</head>
    <p>Oh look, it's Sunday again, so not much happening in Mahébourg. But my belly feels much
     better and I am ready to risk a refreshing shaved-ice-and-sugary-fruits confection from a
     street vendor, with no ill effects, though everyone else looks a bit doubtful. They then
     suggest more or less insistently that we should go to KFC for lunch again, after a lengthy
     browse of Mahébourg's two or three tourist schmutter shops. As far as I am concerned, KFC was
     just as awful as you might suppose (I had a veggie patty with chips), but my companions and
     everyone else in the place seemed very happy to be there, so what do I know. Lots of young
     people being cool, lots of families with small kids out for a Sunday treat. Lots of cardboard
     packaging and not much decent food. Grrr. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>12 December</head>
    <p>The plan today is to make an expedition to Flic en Flac, a seaside resort on the opposite
     side of the island. This means getting up infeasibly early (i.e. about 0700) to get the 0830
     bus to Curepipe, transferring there to the wonderful new tram at 0935, a luxurious tram ride to
     Quatre Bornes (arr. 1011), and then another traditional Mauritian bus out to Flic en Flac via
     Bambous, arriving about 1120. The bus to Curepipe we know well, though I think this was the
     first time I had taken it during the rush hour. It's empty when we get on it, but fills up
     rapidly and is standing room only by the time it's half way through Rose Belle. The new <ref
     target="https://mauritiusmetroexpress.mu/">Metro Express tram</ref> on the other hand is just
     wonderful. Curepipe Central station is reached by lift or escalator, since it is about 40
     metres above the chaotic traffic around the old bus station. Helpful staff on the platform
     explain how to get tickets: as at T4, automation means you must have a pass of some sort even
     if you don't have to pay for it (this applies to the ladies of course). Smart new trams saunter
     into the station silently every ten minutes, and then out again down a gentle slope before
     proceeding towards Rose Hill, following more or less the route of the old railway. The bus from
     Quatre Bornes to Flic en Flac, on the other hand, is much the same as it was back in 2006 when
     I last took it, i.e. bouncy and old skool, and in no particular hurry. </p>
    <figure><graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/tram.png" width="40%"/>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/bus.png" width="40%"/>
    <head>Boarding a tram (L)  vs boarding a bus (R)</head></figure>
    <p>Flic en Flac, when we get there, has not changed a great deal either. It still has a long
     beautiful beach, accessible to everyone, with white crunchy sands (maybe a little too much
     coral in it for barefoot walking though). It is still fringed with lots of filaotrees to sit
     underneath <hi>en famille</hi>, and plenty of families so doing. There are still lots of little
     vans selling street food, and also a chap with a pile of fresh coconuts and a mighty scimitar
     to serve them with. And most of the shops and restaurants I vaguely recall are still there too,
     except for the ones that have disappeared or been upgraded. This includes the <hi>Canne a
     Sucres</hi>, where Lilette's friend Claude-May is still in business and delighted to see us
     again after, gosh, 20 years. We visit other relatives, take a light late lunch at the nearest
     Thai restaurant, and a bit of a splash in the sea (Jef is more sensibly prepared for this than
     I am), before regretfully repeating the three steps of the journey here in reverse. Since we
     left Flic-en-Flac at 15h30, we necessarily left Curepipe in the rush hour, on a less than
     luxurious and very over-crowded bus, whose back door swung open alarmingly at every other bump.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>13 December</head>
    <p>Another trip to Curepipe today, but less frantic. Nicole and Jef go to the bank, and we
     decide to walk to rue Henri Robert rather than take the bus, which is pleasant. The Eglise
     protestant de St Clement has gained a new roof and some tasteful wooden shutters since I last
     saw it. At Alain's house, I accept a beer and settle down to the usual sort of waiting. The
     plan for the day is family focussed. First we all pile into Alain's car and zoom back to the
     Curepipe marketplace to buy some flowers, then back to the house to pick up a metal implement
     and some cleaning materials. For today we are going to do some graveyard maintenance as well as
     pay our respects at the Bigarade cemetery. Marie France's grave doesn't have a headstone as yet and
     Lilette's mum has no memorial as yet, but has been interred with her parents who do. Alain
     scrubs the inscription up to more or less legibility, and we plant flowers on both before
     returning (eventually) to Roger's house for an enormous meal. </p>
    <figure><graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/grave.png" width="40%"/></figure><p>There are <foreign>gato pimen</foreign>, delicious
     bread, farata, rice, <foreign>rougaille poisson</foreign> and <foreign>bredes</foreign>, nice cakes, and a massive salad. More than
     anyone can eat indeed, even with the wine that Jef has provided. It takes a while to get everyone to
     the table, but eventually the sadness that permeates the house does dissipate a little. </p>
    <p>As we are definitely too stuffed to move, Alain gives us a lift back to Curepipe bus station.
     We just catch a bus that is about to leave, packed to the gunnels with commuters, but we are
     getting quite used to that, and now expert in sharing a seat meant for three as the bus bounds
     and leaps like a wild animal down the motorway home. </p>
   </div>

   <div type="div3">
    <head>14 December</head>
    <p>A very quiet day in which Lilette does a little desultory banking, and then goes to the
     hairdresser. There is a snack next door to the hair salon where we eat quite plausible mine
     frite before returning for a lazy afternoon doing nothing much. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>15 December</head>
    <p>Time for another taxi-hosted expedition, this time in an anti-clockwise direction. The
     tax iman this time is less experienced and doesn't entirely stick to the proposed route, so we
     don't get to walk in the Bois des Amourettes. But we did see a debarcadere (landing stage) and
     some ancient cannon as well as taking exploratory strolls along several pleasant beaches along
     the North Eastern coast, facing Ile aux Cerfs. This last is now a major tourist venue, but the
     beaches are public and accessible, at Palmar and Belle mar and even Bras d'eau, though large
     portions of many of them have been appropriated by hotel developments. There is also a much
     improved coastal cycle path to admire, though as we are in a taxi we don't actually get to use
     it, nor any of the beaches. We spend some time in an allegedly discounted cashmere shop full of
     classy cashmere and over priced tourist goods, where Nicole bought herself a birthday present,
     and Lilette some insanely expensive postcards. And then we went to a little place called La
     Pelouse in Trou d'eau douce ("Fresh Water Hole" really doesn't sound as nice) for lunch.
     Freshly grilled capitaine in a creole sauce, followed by fresh pineapple, followed by a very
     sleepy ride home. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>16 December</head>
    <p>Jef and Nicole have disappeared on their own adventure by the time I have had my breakfast
     and Lilette has appeared after doing her morning exercises. She suggests we lunch "Chez Edwige"
     as recommended by Yves a few days ago, which turns out to be a pleasantly unpretentious and
     entirely correct restaurant. We perch on a shady balcony overlooking the road to Blue Bay and
     choose from a small menu: <hi>carri poulet</hi> for me and (implausibly) spaghetti bolognese
     for Lilette, both of which were very satisfactory. And after an impeccably served <hi>banane
     flambee</hi> to share, we stagger home, a bit hot for lack of shade, but replete. </p>
    <p>Today is the beginning of the Hare Krishna Waterfront Festival, which (I think) celebrates
     the birth of Krsna with any amount of hoo hah down on the waterfront. By the time we get down
     to it, there is much expectant chanting and singing in the big tent, with associated speeches
     in Kreol and French and English. It might be a village fete or a wedding. There are crowds of
     pretty girls and old ladies all wearing their best saris; there is a band of musicians with a
     charming singer sitting in the middle of the tent; there are fat men in white robes officiating
     mysteriously; there are kids rushing around who will daub your forehead with paint if you let
     them. Outside the tent there are (of course) stalls selling colourful clothing, objects of
     devotion, and delicious vegetarian snacks. This is a three day festival with a narrative of its
     own, of which we are of course entirely ignorant, but I liked it very much. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>17 December</head>
    <p>After breakfast, I went for a short walk, but returned fairly soon, considering that if ten
     minutes walking gives me a shirt as sweaty as this, either the shirt or the climate needs to be
     changed. The latter possibility is only a few days away, alas, and Lilette and Nicole are
     already thinking about packing. But for today, another mass expedition to Curepipe is planned,
     even though it's Saturday and Curepipe is full of Christmas shoppers. Nicole (whose birthday it
     is) wants to eat at Kasafe, a specific restaurant owned by a friend of a friend and located on
     Sir Virgile Naz street, wherever that might be. Obligingly, Mr Google and I successfully plot a
     route through Curepipe's extensive urban sprawl, both there and back. The lunch turns out to be
     Chinese and quite tasty. Then we walk back to the centre of town to pick up pre-ordered cakes
     from the bakery, and some lychees from the market before catching the bus out to Forest Side
     once more. And at Rogers we wait, of course, for Roger who is out shopping, before eventually
     progressing into birthday party mode when he returns. There is cake, there is wine, there is tea.
     Roger has brought birthday presents for both his sisters: a portable electric fan each. Alain has brought a mountain of family photos for us all
     to look at, which is interesting: I take copies of some of them. The party mood is spoiled only
     at the last moment when I got my little finger caught in the car door as Nicole was closing it.
     No serious damage, except to Nicole's mood, as we all bounced along in the bus back home. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>18 December</head>
    <p>I went for another early morning saunter round the market and found a bargain price toy dodo
     for Lilette. For lunch we all went to a nearby restauranmt already full of Christmas parties
     and balloons, which was a mistake: our food took an hour to appear, and was not particularly
     good when it did. Daube de cerf, too tough. A brief siesta ensued, and then I checked us in for
     our flights home. </p>
    <p>Down at the seafront the Hare Krishna party is reaching a climax, with the arrival of various
     dignatories on board a boat pulled along by a couple of splendid fake swans. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/krishna.png"
      width="600px"/>
     <head>Krishna's boat arrives</head>
    </figure>
    <p>I gawped at this, and at the subsequent procession of said dignatories carrying brightly
     coloured wooden representations of Krishna as Jagannatha through the crowd. The party was
     clearly going to go on all night, and I was quite sorry to leave it for our walk home along the
     sea front. Jef and Nicole are leaving tomorrow morning at dawn, so we said our farewells as the
     night fell. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>19 December</head>
    <p>We have an extra day's grace since our flight back to London is not due to leave till shortly
     before midnight tonight. We start by going for a walk to the National History Museum, down the
     rue Royale. This is in a beautiful 18th century mansion, le chateau Gheude, itself much in need
     of conservation. Inside, as well as a lot of creaky floor boards and two grand but slightly
     wonky staircases there are photos and paintings describing the history of the island, largely
     but not entirely from the European perspective. There is lots about the Dutch settlers, and
     also about the Battle of Grand Port (see above), as well as some disturbing paraphernalia of
     slavery. Portraits of notable blighters such as Robert Surcouf, the pirate, are complemented by
     information about notable Mauritians long since forgotten like <ref
     target="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfred_Richard">the painter Alfred Richard</ref>
     (1824-1880), and by a hall full of photographs of modern political figures. And you can see
     Mahe de Labourdonnais' four poster bed, and a model of the Governor's personal railway
     carriage: the carriage itself is outside slowly decomposing in a shed behind the house. </p>
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/carriage.png"
      width="600px"/>
     <head>The Governor's Railway Carriage: in need of some TLC</head>
    </figure>  
    <p>We then went in search of lunch, though with little success. The first place Mr Google
     suggested was shut, the second was too noisy and already full of busy lunchers; the third
     (Karay Mario) would have been perfect but had no space for us. So we took the bus back into
     town and found a deserted snack willing to provide us with a modest bol renverse and some fish
     szechuan style. Better than nothing. </p>
    <p>Back at the Saladier, Yunnus has obtained a large pile of freshly made faratas for us to
     smuggle home. My challenge is to find some appropriate wrapping for them, which I do eventually
     in the Chinese supermarket (of course). Then we do the rest of the packing, and (eventually)
     set off for the airport. I change into long trousers for the first time since we got here,
     leaving the room keys in the pocket of my shorts which are then packed away with other
     unsavoury garments at the bottom of my suitcase. Whoops. I am alerted to this by a phone call
     from the long suffering Yunnus, and can thus unpack, extract, and return the keys as soon as we
     get to the airport. </p>
   </div>
   <div type="div3">
    <head>20 December</head>
    <p>What more is there to say about a tedious 12 hour flight (it's uphill going back, so takes an
     hour longer)? Nothing, obviously. We arrived at the Heathrow Central Bus station an hour after
     the bus I had tickets for left, railed pointlessly against the inadequacies of privatised bus
     systems, and bought some more tickets on the next available bus, which being a different
     company, naturally deposited us somewhere completely different when we arrived in Bristol. But
     there is a posh hotel here, and posh hotels can usually be persuaded to provide you with useful
     services like a cup of coffee and a taxi, provided you ask nicely and look respectable. And so
     indeed the receptionist of the Hampton Hotel did, and here we are back in our little
     over-heated house in Clifton, and ready to have a snooze. Later we will get ready for Xmas, but
     for now it's time for bed, even though the clock says it's not even midday yet. </p>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
