<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Blogging</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-01-04">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <head>2022: another year</head>
   <figure><graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/timeline.png"/><head>European end of my timeline</head></figure>
   <p>What's left to say about the year 2022? I survived it, as did most of those near and dear to
    me. Despite coming close several times, the UK's current apology for a government did not
    entirely collapse. I spent most of the year running away, as this blog attests.</p>
   <list>
    <item>In January and February, I seem to have done a lot of running about between dentists and doctors. I also paid my Covid dues and stayed in bed for a few days. And tried my best to contribute something sensible to the  <ref target="2022-07-blog.xml">CLS WG3 project</ref> on counting "verbs of inner life". </item>
    <item>In March I went to Galway, to test my brief (but very enjoyable) reincarnation as an
     itinerant scholar, as holder of a prestigious CLS INFRA fellowship </item>
    <item>In May I went, as usual, to Tours to teach TEI "niveau 2", and then to La Vergne where
     I stayed till July, with the exception of a brief side trip to Nottingham to enjoy a Belinda concert</item>
    <item>In June I went to Lyon to teach a summer school: it was hot </item>
    <item>In July I had another brief visit to Galway to wrap up my fellowship alas</item>
    <item>In August I escaped to La Vergne again </item>
    <item>In mid-September, I came back to the UK perforce, to attend the annual TEI conference in Newcastle</item>
    <item>At the end of October, we celebrated (a bit early) our golden wedding anniversary with an extraordinary family holiday in the Forest of Dean</item>
    <item>In November I managed to fit in another week in La Vergne, a three day teaching spell in
     Tours, and a day long meeting in Paris, before joining Lilette for a three week break in
     Mauritius, not before time. </item>
   </list>
   <p>It's all in my Google Location History, in glorious detail, but I don't know how to share that.</p>
   <figure><graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/mauritianMap.png"/><head>Mauritian end of my timeline</head></figure></body>
 </text>
</TEI>
