<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>2022: another year</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ref>http://lb42.github.io/Diary/</ref></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-01-14">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <head/>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/timeline.png"
     width="500px"/>
    <head>European end of my timeline</head>
   </figure>
   <p>What's left to say about the year 2022? I survived it, as did most of those near and dear to
    me. Despite coming close several times, the UK's current apology for a government did not
    entirely collapse. As this blog attests, I spent much of the year trying to avoid this by travelling,  when not engaged by
    <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/grandparenting.html"> grandparental </ref> or gardening duties. </p>
   <list>
    <item>In January and February, I seem to have done a lot of running about between dentists and
     doctors. I also paid my Covid dues and stayed in bed for a few days. And tried my best to
     contribute something sensible to the <ref target="https://foxglove.hypotheses.org/669">CLS WG3
     project on counting "verbs of inner life".</ref> </item>
    <item>In March <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/wanderings-1.html">I went to Galway for
     three weeks</ref>, nervously clutching a prestigious CLS INFRA fellowship to test my brief (but
     very enjoyable) reincarnation as an itinerant scholar. </item>
    <item>In May I went, as usual, to Tours to teach TEI "niveau 2", and then to La Vergne where I
     stayed most of the summer, with the exception of a brief side trip to Nottingham to enjoy a
     Belinda concert and collect Lilette. </item>
    <item>In June Lilette returned to Bristol and I went to Lyon to teach at an ENS summer school:
     it was very hot and the journey home was somewhat stressful</item>
    <item>In July I took <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/wanderings-2.html">another brief
     visit to Galway</ref> to wrap up my fellowship alas</item>
    <item>In August I escaped to La Vergne again </item>
    <item>In mid-September, I came back to the UK perforce, to attend (and address) the annual TEI
     conference, this year hosted by the University of Newcastle </item>
    <item>At the end of October, we celebrated (a bit early) our golden wedding anniversary with an
     extraordinary family holiday in the Forest of Dean</item>
    <item>In November I managed to fit in another week in La Vergne, three days teaching TEI niveau
     1 in Tours, and a day long meeting in Paris, before joining Lilette for a three week break in
     Mauritius, not before time. </item>
   </list>
   <p>The minute details of where and when are all logged in my Google Location History, but I don't
    know how to share that, other than by the occasional screen shot. But there are links to more
    detailed reportage of various kinds in the above list.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/mauritianMap.png"/>
    <head>Mauritian end of my timeline</head>
   </figure>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
