<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bloggage: 2022-06-25</title>
            <author/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2022-06-25T10:50:05.108236083</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished blog entry</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Written by OpenOffice</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2022-06-25T12:02:26.796029793</date>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Getting home  (Lyon-Paris-London-Bristol, 24 June 2022)</head>
         <p>The rail system of the future has arrived already in France. So long as you book well in advance and (here’s the rub) make sure you use the train booked, getting from Lyon to Paris is a mere 35 euro in first class and with Italian comfort too. If on the other hand you are an idiot anglais, and somehow convince yourself that your train is leaving at 1255 rather than 1155, and therefore spend an extra 20 minutes debating with the lovely lady at reception whether it’s worth taking a taxi to the Gare de Lyon Part Dieu in the rain, before deciding to  take  the bus,  so that  you arrive just as the rain stops and both your train and the one following it have already departed  – then  you will just have to fight with a ticket machine to get a place on the next available INOUI or OUIGO (either of which is a pretty silly name for a train: what was wrong with TGV?) for hmm 59 euro in second class. On the plus side, I discover that a French ticket machine will actually scan the code on my Old Fart Discount Card and fill in all the required details for itself, and also that said machine will only sell you a seat on the train if it still has seats available.  And so I proceed in reasonable comfort from Lyon to Paris, though the sandwich from “Le Bar”  was really quite nasty, and I spent much of the journey idly speculating what I would do if I missed the Eurostar I was booked on: pay another 250 quid to be sure of making London before the strike proper began? Or pay another 200 quid only, and risk having to camp out in London for a day or two? Sigh. </p><p>From the Gare de Lyon to the Gare du Nord is only about 15 minutes, if you get the RER D, but make that 25 if you don't have a ticket, and if the RER D happens to be on strike so you have to take the RER A, and change to RER B, as indeed I did. Did I mention that the Gare de Lyon and environs were really quite hot and sticky at this time? Anyway, here I am at the Gare du Nord, trying to check in for the 1613 eurostar and, praise the lord, it’s only 1545. So I have to get through the crowd at the stupid passport machine, which deigns to let me pass on the 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>  attempt, and now hoorah, another 2 hours of air conditioned calm as I whizz regretfully through France and under the sea to a whole new world of pain, which is St Pancras underground station at 1730 the day before a rail strike, and indeed Paddington ditto at 1750. </p><p>In sharp contrast with the French one, the British ticket machine sneers at my pitiful attempts to remember my ticket reservation number refusing  to give me a ticket, even after three goes in three different machines.  I go and protest to a real person in the Paddington ticket office, who is helpful but can only point out that I have somehow booked the same journey (Paddington to Bristol) twice, though why this should mean I can’t have even one ticket remains obscure. Being an obliging sort of chap he gives me two  sets of tickets for the same train, due to leave at 1902, which gives me time to go and buy a restorative pasty while I wait.  Just as well, since shortly afterward,  when I begin to wonder why the 1902 has not yet appeared on the departure board,  I learn from another GWR person that it has  been cancelled anyway. The consequence of which is that I perforce made common cause with two trainloads of would be travellers to Bristol on the same train, at least half of whom didn’t have reservations either, so it was standing-room only all the way to Didcot, and there was a lot of very polite “I think that’s my seat” musical chairs going on, though no music. Oh, except for the moment when I panicked because I could not find my phone (it got separated from me along with my baggage during the rush to find space on the train) and so made it play a loud and annoying tune, using  Mr Google’s wonderful “find my phone” service. See, technology can also be really helpful sometimes. Sometimes.</p>
<p>After Didcot, the bodycount per square centimetre dropped down to a reasonable number and I regained my equanimity, though Temple Meads was still pretty crowded. Crazy people going to Glastonbury, all of them already high on drugs according to my  taxidriver.</p>      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
