<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>La vie creusoise</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-01-19">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>Every now and then, someone asks me to explain what we get up to when we disappear to our
    house in France, usually with an overtone of puzzlement, if not downright bewilderment. What's
    the attraction of a somewhat battered house with no central heating in the middle of nowhere,
    hard to get to or from by public transport, and with nothing much to do in the immediate
    vicinity? It seems a good pretext to review what we actually did do there during 2022, as
    typical a year as any. </p>
   <p>My usual excuse for slipping away to La Vergne is that someone has paid me to go to France
    anyway, so I might as well stay on for a while. In 2022, this wheeze worked three times, twice
    because I was invited to help teach TEI Workshops at the CESR in Tours ("Advanced" in May,
    "Beginners" in November), and once in June because I was invited to teach all about ODDs at an
    encoding summer school organized by the ENS de Lyon. There is of course a non-neglible
    opportunity cost attached to such invitations: I have to wrestle with the CNRS or other
    administration to actually get my reimbursement, but I am getting wily in the ways of e.g. a
    horrendous piece of software called "Chorus Pro", and the money always turns up eventually. </p>
   <p>As regards getting there, I think I now know as much as anyone about how to travel by train
    between London, Tours, Paris, and La Vergne. As with Amazon logistics, the tricky part is in the
    "last mile", but this year we persuaded someone else to take on the (paid) role of providing a
    personal taxi service to and from the (not very near) nearest station at La Souterraine. And
    there is always <ref
    target="https://www.agglo-grandgueret.fr/les-navettes-du-grand-gueret-en-transport-la-demande"
    >the TAD</ref>, of course, if suitable planning has been made. </p>
   <p>For example, my first expedition to La Vergne this year involved the following steps: <list
    rend="numbered">
    <item>GWR train Bristol to London Paddington; tube to St Pancras; Eurostar from St Pancras to
     Paris Nord (dep 1331, arr 1647) </item>
    <item>Metro to Paris Montparnasse; Montparnasse to Tours (dep 1756, arr. 1915)</item>
    <item>Check in at Le Grand Hotel, my favourite, conveniently located a few minutes stroll from
     La Chope, where tradition requires that an initial dinner with my teaching colleagues be held. </item>
    <item>Work for a few days, and then get a couple of slow trains from Tours to Limoges (via
     Poitiers, rather than Paris, for a change)</item>
    <item>An evening in Limoges, staying at the cheap Ibis hotel near the station, imposes itself,
     since there is no useful train to Gueret until next morning (there is one, but then I would
     have to spend the evening in Gueret)</item>
    <item>Take the 0910 from Limoges, which potters pleasantly across the departement, stopping here
     and there, and arriving at 1010. Which gives me time to do a little shopping before catching
     the (previously reserved) TAD to La Vergne. </item>
    </list></p>
   <p>For the next eight days, I pottered around in splendid rural isolation. On Saturday I took the
    TAD to and from Gueret market, where I stocked up on fresh meat and veg, and also bought some
    tomato plants to plant in my potager, once I had released it from its plastic over-winter
    covers. I cleaned the house a bit. I ate well. I used up my stock of firewood in the evenings
    when necessary and watched French telly. I went for a walk round the lake a couple of times and
    said hello to the neighbours. I claimed to be getting the house prepared for Lilette. </p>
   <p> <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-summary.html">[Back to Summary]</ref> </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
