<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>La vie française - 2</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-01-27">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p rend="italic">Every now and then, someone asks me to explain what we get up to when we disappear to our
    house in France, usually with an overtone of puzzlement, if not downright bewilderment. What's
    the attraction of a somewhat battered house with no central heating in the middle of nowhere,
    hard to get to or from by public transport, and with nothing much to do in the immediate
    vicinity?  </p>

   <p>In August there's no need for explanation. Everyone, but everyone, heads for the countryside
    in August. And the people who live in the country? They head to the seaside, of course. <ref
    target="https://medium.com/@louBurnard/in-which-we-go-to-the-seaside-or-what-i-did-in-my-holidays-cf530bc0605a"
    >We did that</ref> a few years ago, but this year we were very happy to just stay put in La
    Vergne. The weather was kind to us, and there were important amusements to attend. </p>
   <p>Since we were starting from Bristol, we took the overland route by train which is reasonably
    speedy, but requires an overnight stay either in London or in Paris, since (as aforesaid) there
    is no useful train from Paris to La Souterraine after 0930. There used to be an early afternoon
    one, but it is no more. Yes, there are flights from Bristol to Paris, and no I do not want to
    take them: you are then faced with the problem of getting from Orly to Austerlitz, which is a
    horrible RER journey even when the metro is not on strike. Instead we have a pleasant evening at
    one of the Korean restaurants on the boulevard Saint Jacques, a good nights sleep in another
    forgettable Paris hotel (L'Orphée), and get up at a reasonable time of day. Lucy comes to meet
    us at La Souterraine as promised and allows us to make a whistle stop tour of the local Lidl as
    well. And here we are back home in La Vergne, which is still bearing traces of the rapid house
    cleaning I gave it back in May, all ready to resume doing nothing in particular for a few weeks.
    Has anything changed in our absence? Not visibly, unless you count weeds of which we have
    plenty, or tomatoes, which are much improved. The grass is parched, so I don't know where they
    are getting their refreshment from. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/canards.png"
     width="800px"/>
    <head>Salut les canards</head>
   </figure>
   <p>The ducks down at the shady end of the lake are in fine fettle when we go out for an evening
    stroll; the fish are occasionally to be seen leaping, and swooping birds may be observed to
    graze on hovering insects. It's a nice lake, frequented by occasional clumps of serious minded
    fishermen, some with battered vans groaning beneath the weight of their extensive fishing
    equipment, others who just came along for the ride. We grunt greetings to make them acknowledge
    our presence, which usually works. There is a nice view of the wooded hill beneath which the
    houses of La Vergne nestle and two pleasant walks into Bussière, one following the track of an
    old railway, the other following the crest of a hill. Et in arcadia ego.</p>
   <p>Cousin Dave supplied me with a well-secured plastic tub of sourdough starter the last time I
    saw him, which I transported at the bottom of my baggage (another advantage of travelling by
    train). This enabled me to bake some really quite plausible bread as a change from the baguettes
    delivered by the local itinerant boulangère. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/loaves.png"
     width="400px"/>
    <head>Today's loaves are made with French flour and Australian rye starter</head>
   </figure>
   <p>The 28th August is Saint Symphorien's day, patron saint of the commune of Bussière-Dunoise.
    Consequently, the end of the month is marked by a three day festival, of which the highlights
    included a procession of tractors pulling floral floats, lots of reasonably well behaved children, a Baby Schtroumpf roundabout and someone selling barbe a papa,  
    competing marching bands, and much general jollity. If your French is up to it, the local
    paper gave it <ref
    target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/laMontagne.png">a good
    write up</ref>, and here are a few photos in any case. </p>
   <figure>
    <!--<graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/tractor.png"
     width="350px"/>-->
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/dancingGirls.png"
     width="600px"/>
    <head>Les Majorettes de Saint Montrond, specially hired for the occasion</head>
   </figure>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/greenBand.png"
     width="600px"/>
    <head>Local band</head>
   </figure>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/banda.png"
     width="600px"/>
    <head>L'entente musicale</head>
   </figure>
   
   <p>At the end of our stay we finally found a suitable weekend to go out for lunch with Evelyne,
    our local TAD conductrice, and a few of her favourite clients, as had been being proposed since
    the spring. The venue was a place called Toulx-Sainte-Croix, or more exactly Les Pierres
    Jaumatres, a hill on top of which there are some aesthetically remarkable large boulders and a
    very fine view, plus a huge chalet restaurant. The stones are apparently technically known as a
    chaos, and are the result of natural erosion, though that didn't stop various 19th century
    archaeologists claiming they were made by the druids. <ref
    target="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierres_Jaum%C3%A2tres">Georges Sand knew better</ref>, it
    says on this wiki page. My photos are <ref target="https://photos.app.goo.gl/he9JxiE6i4iRtoHS7">
    here</ref>. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/walnuts.png"
     width="350px"/>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/raspberry.png"
     width="350px"/>

   </figure>
   <p>September time in previous years has been marked by masses of walnuts, but this year the
    harvest was frankly pathetic. Not enough rain or rain at the wrong time or just the cussedness
    of things, I dunno. The last raspberry of the season was also unimpressive, but there my
    expectations were much lower. Clearly a systematic pruning of everything is needed. </p>
   <p> <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-summary.html">[Back to Summary]</ref> </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
