<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>La vie française - 1</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-01-27">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <p>Every now and then, someone asks me to explain what we get up to when we disappear to our
    house in France, usually with an overtone of puzzlement, if not downright bewilderment. What's
    the attraction of a somewhat battered house with no central heating in the middle of nowhere,
    hard to get to or from by public transport, and with nothing much to do in the immediate
    vicinity? It seems a good pretext to review what we actually did do there during 2022, as
    typical a year as any. </p>
   <p>My usual excuse for slipping away to La Vergne is that someone has paid me to go to France
    anyway, so I might as well stay on for a while. In 2022, this wheeze worked three times, twice
    because I was invited to help teach TEI Workshops at the CESR in Tours ("Advanced" in May,
    "Beginners" in November), and once in June because I was invited to teach at an encoding summer
    school organized by researchers in Lyon. There is of course a non-neglible opportunity cost
    attached to such invitations: at Tours, for example, I have to wrestle with the CNRS
    administration (more precisely, a horrendous piece of software called "Chorus Pro") to actually
    get my reimbursement. By now though I am getting quite wily in its ways and the money always
    turns up eventually. </p>
   <p>As regards getting there, I think I now know as much as anyone about how to travel by train
    between London, Tours, Paris, and La Vergne. As with Amazon logistics, the tricky part is in the
    "last mile", but this year we persuaded someone else to take on the (paid) role of providing a
    personal taxi service to and from the (not very near) nearest station at La Souterraine. And
    there is always <ref
    target="https://www.agglo-grandgueret.fr/les-navettes-du-grand-gueret-en-transport-la-demande"
    >the TAD</ref>, of course, if suitable planning has been made. </p>
   <p>For example, my first expedition to La Vergne this year involved the following steps: <list
    rend="numbered">
    <item>GWR train Bristol to London Paddington; tube to St Pancras; Eurostar from St Pancras to
     Paris Nord </item>
    <item>Metro to Paris Montparnasse; Montparnasse to Tours </item>
    <item>Check in at Le Grand Hotel, my favourite, conveniently located a few minutes stroll from
     La Chope, where tradition requires that an initial dinner with my teaching colleagues be held. </item>
    <item>Work for a few days, and then get a couple of slow trains from Tours to Limoges (via
     Poitiers rather than Paris, for a change)</item>
    <item>An evening in Limoges, staying at the cheap Ibis hotel near the station imposes itself,
     since there is no useful train to Gueret until next morning (there is one, but then I would
     have to spend the evening in Gueret)</item>
    <item>Take the 0910 from Limoges, which trundles pleasantly across the département, stopping here
     and there, and arriving at 1010. Which gives me time to do a little shopping before catching
     the (previously reserved) midday TAD to La Vergne. </item>
    </list></p>
   <p>For the next eight days, I pottered around in splendid rural isolation. On Saturday I took the
    TAD to Gueret market, where I stocked up on fresh meat and veg, and also bought some tomato
    plants to plant in my potager, once I had released it from its plastic over-winter covers. I
    cleaned the house a bit. I ate well. I used up my stock of firewood in the evenings when
    necessary and watched French telly. I went for a walk round the lake a couple of times and said
    hello to the neighbours. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/daffodils.png"
     width="400px"/>
    <head>I think these are <hi>jonquilles sauvages</hi></head>
   </figure>
   <p>My major spring time endeavour was to get the tomatoes planted out. I am also very fond of
    tomatoes, especially freshly picked. The climate and the soil in my potager seems to suit them
    very well, which is fortunate since I am a fair-weather gardener at best.</p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/tomatoes-1.png"
     width="300px"/>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/tomatoes-2.png"
     width="300px"/>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/tomatoes-3.png"
     width="300px"/>
    <head><table>
     <row>
      <cell role="label">This year, as usual, I bought ten seedlings and planted them out as soon as
       I could, at the start of May.</cell>
      <cell role="label">In June as they grew I spent a lot of time constructing sticks and string
       for them to grow up (in French these are known as "tuteurs").</cell>
      <cell role="label">And even though this year I wasn't there to water them adequately in July,
       by mid-August there were loads of them, some huge and meaty, some fat and sweet. </cell>
     </row>
     </table></head>
   </figure>
   <p>At the end of my solitary week, I took a weekend jaunt off to Nottingham, partly to see
    Belinda performing with the Mat Davis orchestra, but mainly to collect Lilette and bring her
    back to France. This involved some careful timetabling, but was accomplished entirely by TAD,
    train, and (I regret to say) Ryanair, which provides an occasional flight between Limoges and
    East Midlands Airport. My itinerary was not entirely smooth, but succeeded in its primary
    objectives: I did actually get to the concert before it finished, and I did bring Lilette back
    safe to France. (I even made a series of whatsapp videos recording my progress, yet to be
    edited) The outward leg , on 14 May, went perfectly (TAD to Gueret, train to Limoges, taxi to
    the Limoges Airport, flight to EMA) but although I arrived at EMA in good time for the fast bus
    into Nottingham, this simply did not materialize, so I had to take the slow one. But I did
    arrive in Hucknell in time to hear the encored version of the Star Wars March. The return leg,
    three days later, also went very smoothly until I got into an argument with a glass door at
    Limoges airport, knocking one of my teeth out of shape. You can see why a chap might prefer to
    stay peacefully in France. </p>
   <p>There ensued four weeks of peace and quiet for both of us. An occasional spot of gardening,
    quite a lot of eating, regular strolls round the lake, occasional sorties to Guéret or Bussière,
    and so on. This year, the lake has gained a flock of wild ducks, complete with stern notices
    advising us neither to eat nor to feed them, whose melodious singing greets the dusk every day
    (and probably the dawn too, but I am asleep then). With considerable help from Lucy and John, we
    tamed a bit of the back garden by weeding a bit and trimming some hedges. I tracked down an
    emergency dentist in Gueret, who took X-rays of my wobbly implant and confirmed my suspicion
    that this would necessitate another trip to Oxford (which it did). I spent far too much time
    working out how to make the recycled laser printer I bought last year work, and just about
    enough getting ready for my next teaching gig: the first instalment of something called <ref
     target="https://ethap.sciencesconf.org/">Ecole Thématique : Analyser et Publier des corpus
    encodés en XML</ref>, to be held in June in Lyon. </p>
   <p>Making haste very slowly, we packed the house up, and took the TAD to Gueret on the morning of
    17 June. They were setting up (or taking down) the funfair, so place Bonnyaud was littered with
    plastic elephants in cages rather than spring flowers and tomato plants. And eventually we took
    the 1240 slow train to Paris, changing at St Sulpice Lauriere and Vierzon, arriving early
    evening in good time for an excellent Mauritian dinner at Le Dodo, and also for a good nights
    sleep at another forgettable Parisian hotel near Poissoniere. Next morning, after a stroll
    around the Parc Montholon, I guided Lilette back to the Gare du Nord, and waved her off on the
    1613 eurostar back to London before myself heading off in search of a slow train to a place I
    have never visited before called Tournus, chosen more or less at random because it's on the way
    to Lyon, seems to have some nice old buildings, and is probably not too busy. I should mention
    that this is the time of year when Paris (as they say) sizzles, or starts to, so I have no
    desire to stay there for the weekend before teaching begins in Lyon. So I schlep my bag across
    to the Gare de Bercy, clamber aboard the 1533 to Tournus and off we go.</p>
   <p>In Tournus, I enjoy the luxury of the Terminus Hotel Restaurant, which offers fresh fried fish
    allegedly caught by the patron this morning, and a decent enough chablis to wash it down, as
    well as a very comfortable night's sleep. Next morning, I dutifully stroll down the main drag of
    Tournus, which takes me past numerous shops to a large cobblestone square, in which lurks the
    celebrated Abbaye de Saint Philibert, renowned for its mediaeval mosaics. Around it there are,
    as expected, a lot of nice old buildings, and also a lot of restaurants and bars and hotels for
    the benefit of those wishing to inspect same. I make my way through some windy mediaeval streets
    to the banks of the river Saone, a bridge across which presumably gave Tournus its primary
    raison d'etre, and reflect that it is really getting a touch warm for a fat elderly tourist like
    myself to engage in extensive perambulation before heading back to the station and the next
    train to Lyon. </p>
   <p>I emerge from the bedlam of Lyon Part Dieu into the unforgiving afternoon sun around 3 p.m. to
    discover that the station forecourt is no longer what it was, and now bears an uncanny
    resemblance to one I left in Stratford East London several weeks ago. Yes, Mr Westfield has
    moved in on the languishing commercial properties which partially conceal the tower of the Lyon
    Library. Bizarre. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/westfield.png"
     width="600px"/>
    <head>Westfield sur saone</head>
   </figure>
   <p>This week I will be staying in an "apart'hotel" strategically placed midway between the
    training school's two sites (the MSH in rue Berthelot and the ENS campus behind Ave Jean
    Jaures), in the middle of a district of Lyon which has been transitioning from industrial to
    urban for the last couple of decades, again a bit like Stratford. Former factories are
    re-imagined as up-market drinking halls, or knocked flat, providing space for less lovely high
    rise developments, providing accommodation, for students, and for hopeful new enterprises as
    well as the predictably faceless office blocks. The street layout remains unchanged of course,
    so there are several long straight lines along which the traffic and the wind are equally
    unrelenting, but at least the high rises provide some shade, and there are still occasional
    little back streets and squares to be relished. I have been coming here on and off for years,
    and I rather like the way it works. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/graffiti.png"
     width="600px"/>
    <head>The graffiti are also remarkable</head>
   </figure>
   <p>There are a couple of rather posh pizza joints behind the block containing my hotel, but by
    now it is too late for lunch, and too early for dinner, so they are both shut, and I am forced
    to sit around waiting for refreshment. <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/stoutpizza.png"
     width="600px"/>
    <head> It was worth waiting for though.</head>
    </figure></p>
   <p>The next week sees me commuting either north or south from my apart'hotel, getting to know
    which side of the street is going to be shady, and where it's worth stopping for a coffee, or to
    replenish my small larder of snacks. A light lunch and a fine dinner are, of course, provided
    with true lyonnaise hospitality, so the snacks are strictly superfluous and it's too hot to eat
    much anyway. The teaching room at the MSH was on the top floor (I recognised it from 2010) with
    somewhat spasmodic air conditioning, but we all survived, and it was a pleasure to work with
    Alexey, Maud, Benedicte, Serge and company again. <!--<figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/alexeyetal.png"/>
    <head>Alexey, Maud, and Benedicte sorting out a participant</head>
    </figure> -->My role was to provide a gentle introduction to Xpath and XSLT which could
    function as a gateway drug for the sessions on txm, XQuery, and BaseX as applied to TEI
    documents. Also, I am still hoping to learn how to do something useful with BaseX, which seemed
    a good excuse to stick around for the whole week. But then the skies opened and it poured with
    rain so I started <ref target="https://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-06-25-blog.html">returning
    (with difficulty) to Bristol</ref>. </p>

   <p> <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/vieFrancaise-2.html">[On to La vie française 2
    ]</ref> </p>

   <p> <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-summary.html">[Back to Summary]</ref> </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
