<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>La vie française - 3</title>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published at <ptr target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary"/> </p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>AMOW</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2023-02-01">First draft started</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/geese.png"
     width="700px"/>
    <head>Geese or cranes or something equally noisy flying in formation over La Vergne en route to
     wherever it is these birds go for the winter</head>
   </figure>
   <p>As aforesaid, and whatever the season, there's no easy way of getting to La Vergne by train
    without an overnight stay somewhere. For my third and last escape to France starting 8th
    November this year, I took the simplest route, starting from Oxford not for old times sake but
    on account of a dental appointment. Here's how it went: <list>
    <item>Oxford to London; London to Paris, arriving 2217 pm</item>
     <item>Overnight at the Orphée hotel (which is getting far too much of my money) opposite the
     Gare d'Austerlitz (which is <hi>still</hi> being renovated) </item>
    <item>Get up in time for the 0930 train to La Souterraine. </item>
    <item>Get a ride home with Lucy via Lidl to get some provisions. </item>
    </list></p>
   <p>The weather was sunny, but quite chilly in the evening. Fortunately, Johan whatever his other
    failings as a factotum did manage to source a stash of logs before my arrival, so I had toasty
    warm evenings in front of the stove. I mostly spent the days gardening, shopping, eating, or
    banging away on the computer, either preparing for next week's teaching, or following up on some
    ELTeC business. Naturally, I also took the TAD to Gueret market at the weekend, from which I
    managed to take this rather nice picture of one of the few public artworks in the commune. <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/vedrines.png"
     width="400px">
     <head>This concrete stèle memorializing the forced landing here in 1911 of French flying ace
      <!--ref target="https://www.airmemorialcreusois.fr/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/VEDRINES-_bio_.pdf"
      -->Jules Védrines<!--/ref--> is just visible from the road out of Bussière Dunoise. The man who made
      it used to live in La Vergne. </head>
    </graphic>
    </figure></p>
   <p>I was aided considerably in my gardening by Jon, as a result of whose efforts the overgrown
    glycine and the ancient rose bushes in front of the house were severely abbreviated and the
    larch interfering with the rhododendrons entirely removed. For my part, I talked very severely
    to the overgrown white rose behind the house. We shall see the effects of all this next spring,
    no doubt. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/whiterose.png"
     width="500px"/>
    <head>Can these dried twigs live?</head>
   </figure>
   <p>Before leaving I did manage to meet the new proprietor of the village shop, a charming lady
    called Ocean, and compliment her on the modifications she is making. Then Lucy drove me back to
    La Souterraine, where I caught the train to Vierzon, where I caught another train to Tours, as
    usual. It's time to initiate a new generation into using TEI for the encoding of <hi>le patrimoine
    écrit</hi>. As happens every year, I consider proposing major changes to the organization of the
    course, and then realise it's just fine as it is. This time I have booked into a little
    self-catering flat rather than the Grand Hotel just for a change, but the TEI teaching takes
    place in the same familiar way, in the same familiar place with the same colleagues, and the
    same pleasant lunches and dinners punctuating three days of training sessions. </p>
   <figure>
    <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/students.png"
     width="600px"/>
    <head>Students hard at work</head>
   </figure>
   <p> After which, I need a little rest before proceeding to my next formal engagement. This takes
    the form of a day of tourism, investigating some parts of Tours I have not yet visited:
    specifically the Jardin des Prébendes d'Oé, where there is a nice park, and also several curious
    buildings. The next day, still in tourist mode, I pack up my little flat, and take the train to Le Mans, and thence to this extraordinary building: 
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/cathedral.png"
      width="600px"/>
     <head>Recognise this, anyone?</head>
    </figure></p>
   <p>It seems unnecessary to explain why one might want to visit the cathedral at Chartres. I have
    done my internet research, so I know what I have to look out for, and by gum, there it is. I am
    suitably impressed. They may have covered it over with chairs, but <ref
    target="http://www.studiesincomparativereligion.com/public/articles/The_Mystery_of_the_Great_Labyrinth-Chartres_Cathedral-by_John_James.aspx"
    >the great labyrinth</ref> is still there on the floor and I am glad to have seen it. As of
    course I am to have gawped at the statues on the front door and the statues along the Choir
    Screen and the lovely stained glass and even the tastefully yellowish walls which seem to have
    caused some controversy. I did not descend to the crypt though, so I am unable to confirm or
    deny the presence there of a black madonna who is actually white. </p>
   <p>I spent an amusing morning in a coffee bar on the way to the station monitoring responses to
    my tweet which invited people to guess the location of the photo of the cathedral I had just
    tweeted, and then, caught the Ouigo to Paris. </p>
   <p>In Paris, I am attending the annual meeting of the Labex "Passes dans le Present", on the
    scientific committee of which I have the honour to serve. The meeting is all day tomorrow on the
    Paris Nanterre campus, but for some reason they have booked me into yet another apart'hotel on
    the edge of the Cite des Arts and Sciences at La Villette, i.e. on the other side of Paris. No
    matter, the metro is not on strike, and the Parc de la Villette is a splendid place to walk
    around in. I am particularly taken by the jewish supermarkets which are currently stuffed to the
    gills with imported nonsense for Chanukah. </p>
   <p>After the business part of the Labex meeting, we move to a larger seminar room for a public
    mini conference, where everyone is invited to put on a mask. The masks provided are, however,
    animal faces intended for children, which makes them a little small for most of the
    participants, several of them therefore preferring to sport them as if they were fancy hats. I
    am not sure who thought this would be a wizard wheeze. My chum Philippe who chaired the last
    session looks rather imposing in his though.
    <figure>
     <graphic url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lb42/Works/master/Diary/media/philippe.png"
      width="600px"/>
     <head>Compulsory masks at Nanterre University</head>
    </figure></p>
   
   <p>And so finally, back to the Gare du Nord for my last Eurostar of the year, cd back to London, back
    to Bristol, and then... </p>
   <p> <ref target="http://lb42.github.io/Diary/2022-summary.html">[Back to Summary]</ref> </p>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
