<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Reason not the knees (Jan - Aug, 2008)</title>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Self-published (WordPress)</publisher>
<idno type="URL">https://louburnard.wordpress.com/2008/01/04/how-i-spent-the-festive-season/</idno>
<date when="2008-01-04">2008-01-04</date>
<availability>
<p>Originally published on WordPress.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Converted from WordPress WXR export.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="post">
<head>How I spent the festive season</head>
<p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/nilbymouth.jpg"/>
</figure>So what happened was this: Thursday before Xmas, I started my shopping  by buying Lilette a  present, and then had a coffee and sandwich in Cafe  Nero on the High to celebrate. As I was walking out, I almost collided  with someone else walking in, havered around a bit on the steps, lost my  footing, and landed on the pavement, with my left leg twisted into a  non-sustainable position. I then found I couldn't get up, and went  through an increasingly surreal sequence of events, being rushed off to  A&amp;E at the JR in an ambulance. What larks. A sequence of people came and  looked at me, and prodded me. and then  wheeled me off to another room  to wait for expert opinion which, in the event didnt come. So that  evening, eventually, I was wrapped up tight in bandages and sent home.  The next day I checked into the aptly named "trauma unit" for more  inspection by the experts. Who decided they weren't quite sure whether  or not I needed an operation until I'd been scanned by ultrasound so  they gave me a rather fancy metal and velcro splint affair to wear and  told me to come back the next day. Which I duly did, (at 0845 in the  morning, gulp: fortunately Belinda was visiting and willing to ferry  me). The Ultrasound man, when he finally appeared the next morning, on  the basis of several screens of what looked to me like meaningless  static said  <hi rend="bold">
<hi>*</hi>he<hi>*</hi>
</hi> couldn't see any serious damage. But the Real  Clinician, a no-nonsense avuncular character, said that was nonsense,  and stuck his fist into my knee producing  an alarmingly large hole to  prove the point. Your quadriceps is ruptured, he said firmly, and we  have to repair it. Go home now and we will call you in after Xmas. So I  went home, still sporting my rather fine splint, and had a rather  subdued but still very nice family Xmas and boxing day, pottering about  on my crutches and not having to do any washing up. On the afternoon of  the 27th they called me into the JR so off I went with a change of  underwear and shirt, and a nice book to read. I will not drone on about  hospital life on this occasion, since I think there's rather more I  would like to say about it than anyone probably wants to know, but just  remark that it's not unlike sitting around airports waiting for planes  which are always being cancelled for unexplained reasons, having to go  through equally inexplicable arcane procedures, and generally feeling  completely powerless within an enormously complex system, probably  intended for your long term benefit but  which you're not completely  sure about.  I was labelled on both wrists, drawn on with a pen to show  which leg was to be sliced up and pronounced nil by mouth. The next day  (28th) I sat around in this state until lunchtime, when they decided  they wouldn't be able to get round to me that day, so rescinded the "nil  by mouth" bit, which meant I got to eat some cauliflower cheese and  another evening's hospital entertainment.</p><p>
The next day, being 1 Jan,  they said I could go home, which was a great relief, even though there  are too many stairs in my house and the heating is erratic -- but there  is only one dotty old cripple here and it's me. So yes I am at home now  and for the foreseeable future. I have to wear this enormous purple cast  for the next 
<hi rend="bold">
<hi>*</hi>six weeks<hi>*</hi>
</hi> apparently, and do some strange exercises that  will eventually make it possible to flex my knee again. I don't know  when I'm going to be in the office again, but I am hoping I'll be able  to give my BNC workshop on the 15th, though probably from a wheelchair  assuming I can lay my hands on one by then. (No,  all of this was not  carefully planned so that I could assess  OUCS current provisions for  wheelchair access!) I'll know more after my follow-up appt at the  traumatic  clinic on the 10th.Finally, on the 29th, I was  trundled off, knocked out, sliced up, repaired, and trundled back, at  some time between 11 and 15h. Then I had two days in recovery, which was  an emotional see-saw from deepest gloom at having to depend on harassed  nursing orderlies for help with the most minor personal ablutions to  elation at the point that the nice physio lady showed me I could  actually walk if I just tried it a bit harder. New Years Eve I was given  a new dressing for my wound ("very nicely healed -- no ooze at all" -- I  haven't looked) and offered a choice of colours for the plaster cast.  The last time I saw a plaster cast it was actually made of plaster of  paris and it was white, but that was circa 1959, and nowadays you can  have it any one of a number of bright colours and it is made of  fibreglass: amazing. I chose royal purple. 
</p>
</div>
<!--<div type="comments">
<head>Comments</head>
<div type="comment">
<dateline>
<date when="2008-01-05">2008-01-05</date>
</dateline>
<byline>
<ref target="http://people.uleth.ca/~daniel.odonnell/">Dan</ref>
</byline>
<div>I suppose the purple cast is a positive.

Get well soon!</div>
</div>
<div type="comment">
<dateline>
<date when="2008-01-05">2008-01-05</date>
</dateline>
<byline>
<ref target="http://www.oss-watch.ac.uk/">Stuart Yeates</ref>
</byline>
<div>Hi Lou

At least you're not missing out on any weather worth having.

cheers
stuart</div>
</div>
<div type="comment">
<dateline>
<date when="2008-01-05">2008-01-05</date>
</dateline>
<byline>PeetM</byline>
<div>You poor thing Lou!

Thanks for sharing your story - looking forward to seeing purple plaster-cast soon!

I wonder what 'options' there are on the theme of 'nil by mouth' - I mean, why not just 'nil' ... unless they suspect one might consume something in some other interesting way!</div>
</div>
<div type="comment">
<dateline>
<date when="2008-01-05">2008-01-05</date>
</dateline>
<byline>David Barnard</byline>
<div>On other occasions and in other hospitals I have met folks named "Nil by Mouth" - and always thought it unfortunate that the names of both parents were not given ("Nil by Mouth out of Accident") - but never observed anyone so clearly ENJOYING the experience as your photograph indicates that you were doing.

Seriously, I hope that the recovery time passes quickly and that you mend well.</div>
</div>
<div type="comment">
<dateline>
<date when="2008-01-07">2008-01-07</date>
</dateline>
<byline>JamesC</byline>
<div>I'm assuming 'Nil by mouth' means that it is fine for you to have enteral feeding, i.e. a 'drip'.

Get well soon Lou, I'm sure OUCS will fall apart without you here.  The building is already complaining by not having the heat on.

-James</div>
</div>
<div type="comment">
<dateline>
<date when="2008-01-08">2008-01-08</date>
</dateline>
<byline>mikef</byline>
<div>better get well soon...

else post more blog entries to amuse.

mike</div>
</div>
</div>-->

<div type="post">
<head>The Purple Legged Routine</head>
<p>It's the tenth day since I was sent home in my purple cast, and time for an update. I have found a place in Burnard Towers where I can sit relatively comfortably, and here I am doing it.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/01/purpleleg.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/purpleleg.jpg"/>
</figure>
</p><p>      

For most of the past week, my time has been pretty evenly divided amongst the following activities:
<list type="ordered">
<item>sitting here reading the paper or tapping on my laptop.</item>
<item>getting out of (or into) bed, washing, being washed, having breakfast etc. The morning routine we have now established takes about two hours.</item>
<item>err, that's it. No third thing.</item>
</list></p><p>
Yesterday was however exceptional, for the following reasons:-
<list type="unordered">
<item>A doctor at the Trauma clinic pronounced himself satisfied with my progress and told me to get on with exercising my newly stitched muscle. A physio lady at the same place explained some rather implausible ways of doing so. I spent nearly four hours waiting for these insights (they said they were having "one of those days"), but did get some nice new bandages to replace the increasingly smelly old sock protecting my leg from its purple carapace</item>
<item>I arranged to take delivery of a real wheelchair, on loan for a week. This turned out to be a really useful way of enabling me to sit down at the dinner table with the rest of the family at last.</item>
<item>Guy and Daniella arrived on a visit, and the countdown to the wedding tomorrow began in earnest. Guy brought the five assorted miniature bottles of balsamic vinegar you can see in the picture above for sharing amongst daughters as they arrive.</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>
<div type="post">
<head>Wheelchair Wanderings</head>
<p>When you're mostly immobile, moving out of the house for some event gets major importance attached to it. And since I'm in no position to get out of the house for anything other than majorly important events anyway, this week has been noteworthy for the majorness of its major events, which were three in number.
</p><p>
On Saturday the sun shone and my sister got married at Oxford Registry office. This was also my first ever experience of life from a hired wheel chair: probably more exciting for those doing the pushing than those receiving it.  However, it was a lovely ceremony, with poetry and girls blubbing at the right moment (see further <ref target="http://picasaweb.google.com/lou.burnard/PamsWedding">photos </ref>) In the evening there was a splendid party in the St Margarets Road Institute made   unrecognisable with lights and decorations and two heart-shaped bathmats. The food and drink were copious and several people made speeches. though mine was probably the silliest. After the happy pair  I think my lovely daughters were the stars of the occasion: Derek, Sarah and Belinda sang jazzy standards with violin, and were then joined by Elizabeth for a well rehearsed selection of Tata's favourite   sixties anthems,  culminating in a <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-xSt63HOptw">classic performance of "Chapel of Love"</ref> complete with veils and confetti. The journey home (propelled along a wet and windy Kingston Road by Guy) was a bit scarey though.
</p><p>
On Tuesday my wheelchair and I put in an appearance at OUCS, so that I could do my bit for the <ref target="http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk/workshop/">BNC/Xaira workshop</ref>, along with Guy and Ylva. As far as I can judge (and  I couldnt get downstairs to mingle with the punters during coffee breaks) this went reasonably well. I also managed to say hello to a few work colleagues before returning to Burnard Towers to collapse again.
</p><p>
On Thursday, I made it all the way up to JR to meet a physio lady who listened sympathetically to my complaints about not being able to sleep comfortably but confirmed my suspicion that there was Nothing To Be Done about them. Ah well, we are in this for the long haul.</p>
</div>
<div type="post">
<head>Blow up the shrinking world</head>
<p>Routines set in before you know it. The world shrinks down, or the routine puffs up, till that's all you know about. This week I realised I was getting seriously bored with mine. Each day starts with some aspirin, a banana, a cup of tea, extensive ablutions, and eventually breakfast. I sit on the same sofa and process the same email till dinnertime. This is good, but not good.  Two high spots of this week bucked that shrinking trend:
<list type="unordered">
<item>I hobbled up the road to Manos on Wednesday and sat in the sun drinking coffee and reading the paper. I bought some freshly forced rhubarb.</item>
<item>Elizabeth and I took a taxi for my physio appointment  at the JR on Thursday. Suzy introduced me to a fiendish electronically controlled device which inexorably flexed my knee for me, progressively increasing the amount of flexion from my entrypoint of about 30 degrees, to an unbelievable 47 degrees, at which point I wimped out.</item>
</list></p><p>
I did some work for OUCS, no really. Mostly about European funding bids and such like, but also at last including some real work on the enrich project, and not before. This filled the day satisfactorily, but didn't make me feel the world was getting any bigger.
</p><p>
At the weekend, we were blessed with visitors: Belinda and her Trinidadian chum Phyllis; Alex and Elizabeth. There was a lot of drinking and jollity and I resolved that extensive hobbling might just be the only thing to stop me from going stir crazy. Certainly I felt all the better for <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1z3">today's excursion</ref>: all 0.62 km of it round the block and up to the railway bridge. Just wish the pavements were a bit flatter</p>
</div>

<div type="post">
<head>Getting a grip</head>
<p>This week I've resolved to make a conscious effort to go walkies every day. In a desperate attempt to make this self-evidently useful activity mildly interesting I'm also planning to record my daily routes using one of those new-fangled interweb-based google-map-pedometer thingies. Click on one of the route links below to see what I mean...

</p><p>
<table>
<row>
<cell role="label">Day</cell>
<cell role="label">Route</cell>
<cell role="label">Length (km)</cell>
<cell role="label">Comments</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Sunday</cell>
<cell>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1zf">A peek at Port Meadow</ref>
</cell>
<cell>0.82</cell>
<cell>The sun shone and the world looked fine</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Monday</cell>
<cell>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1z8">All the way to Banbury Rd</ref>
</cell>
<cell>1.43</cell>
<cell>Missed the van but posted some letters anyway. Cold.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Tuesday</cell>
<cell>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1z9">Walton Street</ref>
</cell>
<cell>1.29</cell>
<cell>Refilled wallet. Bought paper for printer. Coffee at Jericho Cafe, shopping 			from Gluttons.</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Wednesday</cell>
<cell>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1ze">Aristotle Lane</ref>
</cell>
<cell>1.34</cell>
<cell>Sunny again. Bought paper and soup at Bunters. The Anchor wasn't open yet, but the canal was walkable.</cell>
</row>
</table></p><p>
At today’s physio appointment, I managed to reach 53 degrees of flexion before wimping out. Still some way to go. On the other hand, I have now got my slug working, and am currently enjoying <ref target="http://arts.guardian.co.uk/filmandmusic/story/0,,2081602,00.html">les Orientales </ref>via the miracle of NFS.</p>
</div>
<div type="post">
<head>Walkies</head>
<p>This week, the daily walk has become a bit of an obsession, if an obsession is something you can only have a bit of.  I am increasingly well-informed on the parlous state of the pavements around here, and can bore for Europe on those (not a few) whose camber is less than optimal.
</p><p>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1zl">Thursday's walk </ref>(1.22 km) was wet and windy, so much so at the start that I almost gave up on it. But the wind was behind me down Plantation Road, and the rain eased off eventually. I bought milk and painkillers and newspaper in Belsyre court, and  looked thoughtfully at a bus on Woodstock Road, which I might maybe take one tomorrow. Back at Manos, I had coffee and cake and read the newspaper until the rain stopped.
<table>
<row>
<cell>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/img_0448.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/02/img_0448.jpg--></graphic><head>Mad person walking into the wind across Port Meadow</head>
</figure>
</cell>
<cell>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1z3">Fridays walk </ref>(1.95 km) was beautifully sunny again, and the Meadow was easy underfoot. Just a pity that the wind was blowing quite so fiercely and in quite such a wrong direction. The path over the bridge and down to Aristotle Lane was a touch muddy, but the Anchor was open, so we had coffee.</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p><p><ref target="http://routebuilder.org/1zx"> Saturdays walk </ref>(1.89 km) was cold and I didn't stop for refreshment anywhere on it. I just proceeded in a straight line down North Parade to buy a newspaper, up Banbury Road, and back via Farndon Road. This was walking for its own sake.</p><p>

<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/200">Sundays walk </ref>(1.59 km) was a more leisurely dash to St Margarets Road for Jean's birthday party, where I sat in a corner, was brought various nice things to eat, drank two glasses of champagne,  and recounted my heroic recovery to anyone who'd listen. I strolled back along the canal to make up the numbers.</p>
</div>
<div type="post">
<head>Normality looms</head>
<p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/ad13th.jpg"><!--http://www.marmaland.com/images/ad13th.jpg--></graphic>
</figure></p><p>On Monday we made marmalade. This is an important annual event in my house, not to be avoided. Lilette bought 2 kilos of oranges at the weekend, but we didn't have time to do anything with them until Sunday evening, when I boiled them up. On Monday morning, despite the lure of the outside sunshine, I dutifully sat down in the kitchen and chopped them up: a slow and messy process but quite relaxing when accompanied by the sound of the Quartet. As all marmalade afficionados know, the rest of the process has a certain inevitability about it: you need to find enough jars, hopefully with appropriate tops,  remember to get some jam pot covers, wash them, bake them dry, boil up the orange soup again, try to extract some more pectin from the pips and pulp, find the right amount of sugar, ensure that it is dissolved before it starts boiling, and eventually start testing for the elusive wrinkle, which in my case this year appeared about the same time as the jam started to darken alarmingly.  Then there's just the logistical problem of getting it out of the pan and into the jars without too much spillage, sealing and labelling the jars, and clearing the sticky decks. A little tiring when you're hopping around the kitchen in a purple carapace, but worth the effort, even it did mean <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/204">Monday's walk</ref> (1.09 km) was short and delayed more than somewhat. I lunched at Meltz on a panini and coffee and risked a walk through Jericho and over the canal bridge, returning more than a little pooped.
</p><p>
Tuesday I decided  to keep up the momentum with <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/207">the longest walk yet  </ref>(2.38 km) This involved some more pottering about through Jericho and a<figure>
<graphic url="media/25.jpg"><!--http://www.oxfordrestaurantguide.co.uk/images/restaurants/big/25.jpg--></graphic>
</figure> pause for refreshment in Cafe Rouge. Being in that part of town around noon meant naturally enough that lots of people I would normally expect to exchange no more than a grunt or a glance with, stopped, looked uncertainly at my accompanying sticks, and needed to be informed about my dramatic progress, Exciting though this touch of reality was, it pales into insignificance compared with the excitement of catching a bus: I waited five minutes for a 30 second ride (and I suppose I have to reduce my total kilometrage for this walk by 0.5), but it was worth it if only for the experience of being offered a seat.</p>
</div>
<div type="post">
<head>Got to admit it's getting better</head>

<p>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/20a">Wednesday's walk </ref>(2.30 km) was an enjoyable stroll across a very sunny Port Meadow to Burgess Field and back, taking in the chance to greet a few muddy horses en route, and observe a twitcher, twitching at the possible presence of some large wading birds miles away across the large puddle which covers most of that part of the meadow at this time of year. <figure>
<graphic url="media/slug-logo.png"><!--http://slug.org.au/slug-logo.png--></graphic>
</figure>Envigorated by this bucolic splendour, I spent most of the rest of the day tapping away on my laptop on ENRICH-related matters, mostly. OK, I also got both NFS and samba working on the slug, and played back music from it on Elizabeth's mac, once.</p><p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/painted%20pebble.jpg"><!--http://www.shetland-heritage.co.uk/amenitytrust/archaeology/painted%20pebble.jpg--></graphic>
</figure>Thursday morning saw a more major achievement: in the closing minutes of my weekly physio appointment with the electronic rack, I did actually achieve the target <hi rend="bold">60 degrees of flexion</hi>. Whereupon, as they do, Suzie remarked that the goalposts were now moving on, of course, but still and all. Back home, Mr Mutton called to say he might be able to start replacing our moribund central heating next week for a paltry four digit sum, and Elizabeth made me a tasty lunch which I just managed to finish before  the first of the new-dispensation TEI council conference calls began....  And before it got too dark, I also managed to complete  <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/20e">a respectably long walk </ref>(1.78 km). So I mark this day with a satisfactory pebble, listening to a copy of Sgt Pepper I had forgotten was lurking on Benson's hard disk.
</p> </div>

<div type="post">
<head>Long distance hobbling</head>
<p>The ante is hereby upped. My minimum walk length henceforth should exceed 2 km. though I can see it is going to be hard to keep the walks interesting as well. On Friday, I made it <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/2k">all the way to Mick's cafe</ref>, (2.76 km) via Roger Dudman Way, which is a  nice new  route to the Botley road alongside the railway, taking in such delights as Cripley meadow allotments, Castle Mill House, and Turbo Ted's Nursery. I wish I had taken a photo inside, since Mick himself was lunching under his own likeness in the mural which covers all of one wall of his cafe, but I didn't; here's <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sledgecallier/416939675/">one of the outside</ref> taken by someone else instead. Friday was also remarkable as being the first time I have ventured back to OUCS since the BNC Workshop. This was also the first time I have seen the inside of my office this year (I looked in to see whether janus, my desktop, is really as dead as it seems to be: it is)</p><p>

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/02/croci.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/croci.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/02/croci.thumbnail.jpg--></graphic><head>crocuses</head>
</figure>
</p><p>
<ref target="http://routebuilder.org/20p">To the Parks,</ref> (2.84 km)  to the Parks! it's Saturday afternoon and  everyone is out jogging, walking their dogs, children, or elderly relatives, making them (well maybe not the dogs) admire  the spring flowers -- daffodils, snowdrops, crocuses are everywhere -- and every now and again groups of people start howling in support of some muddy game involving a leather ball.  I sat on a bench and contemplated the follies of youth, before stumbling home via the Lady Margaret Gate, and North Parade, where I had coffee <ref target="http://www.dailyinfo.co.uk/reviews/venue/303/Chez%2BGaston/">chez Gaston</ref>, now apparently run by Serbians.
</p><p>
But today I managed only <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/20s">a paltry 2.57 km</ref> wandering around the wonders that Berkeley Homes hath wrought on what used to be Lucy's spoil heap. I suppose blocks of  <ref target="http://www.flickr.com/photos/61686932@N00/1495091731/">faux Victoriana </ref>and blocks of faux Regency fit together just as well as the real things,  and actually the houses do look quite pleasant on a quiet sunny afternoon, even though there is a feeling of having strayed into an architectural model.</p>
</div>

<div type="post">
<head>Week 6: the beginning of the end</head>
<p>The sixth week of their (partial) incarceration in a purple fibreglass casket  and my leg is getting restless, if not indeed overambitious. Also, the sun is still shining brightly, and the real world is beckoning. So, on Monday, I devote the morning to catching up on email, and take <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/214">a very circuitous route</ref> to the Co-op in Walton Street after lunch... but the real big news of this day was not  the arrival of a new Dyson, but a call from Kylie from A1.
</p><p>
And sure enough, implausibly early on Tuesday, Mr Mutton is here to introduce us to Bob the builder and Justin the heating engineer and a pile of new radiators and copper piping, the installation of which is clearly going to wreak havoc for the rest of the week. so off I hobble, this time   <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/219">to the post </ref> (2.28 km), a pounding of familiar streets with an interesting and lengthy interlude: sitting in Cafe Rouge talking business with Sue Fenley for an hour or so, before returning home to discuss bathrooms with Ron.
</p><p>
Wednesday, more heating engineers appear, and start methodically ripping out the old central heating. Fortunately, it is still sunny, so  after lunch I go  for <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/21a">a familiar walk,</ref> across Port Meadow and back. A horse takes more than decent interest in my shoulder bag, which is a little disconcerting.
</p><p>
And so to Valentines Day, today, the long awaited date of my review at the Traumatic Clinic. Suzie's machine gets me up to a maximum flexion of 68 degrees before it, which it transpires is not really good enough. The Consultant when I finally see him at first suggests maybe I should keep the cast on till I have reached the magic 90 degrees. I demur. He gives in and hands me over to a nice nurse, who instructs me in the mysteries of the Universal Knee Brace which she then installs on my leg. 
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/02/bionicleg.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/bionicleg.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/02/bionicleg.thumbnail.jpg--></graphic><head>A bionic leg</head>
</figure>This gadget allows me to flex my knee up to 90 degrees AND NO MORE, but this is very different from the cast which didn't allow me to flex at all. Which makes me feel a little wobbly and confused ... but still relieved to be free of my purple carapace at last. I retreat to Burnard Towers and focus on the serious problem of getting some (electrical) heating up and running.</p>
</div>

<div type="post">
<head>Is this normalcy?</head>
<p>It's Monday, and I went <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/21p">to the office</ref>. Just like that. I sat in my chair and bent my knee a bit, and poked at a computer or two, and people popped their heads round the door and welcomed me back. It was all very reassuring. OK, I admit, one big motivation to get out of Burnard Towers is the fact that it's<hi rend="italic"> really really </hi>cold with no central heating at all, not to mention the fact that Bob and Co are still thumping up and down stairs and taking up floorboards. Whereas my office is nice and warm, even though janus has apparently gone away to be rebrained, so that currently the desktop computing facilities available to me at the Towers are rather better than those at <ref target="http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/about/">OUCS</ref> (Geek alert: this weekend I successfully installed linux drivers for the Canon Pixma ip4500 I bought before Christmas and <hi rend="italic">
<hi rend="bold">it all just worked!</hi>
</hi>; I also eventually transformed an ancient audio tape into a CD, which was more problematic). I made phone calls,read mail, and generally behaved in a managerial manner. Easy peasy.
</p><p> <figure>
<graphic url="media/eandal.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/02/eandal.thumbnail.jpg--></graphic><head>Elizabeth and Al</head><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/02/eandal.jpg-->
</figure>
In other             
news this weekend, Elizabeth, Al, Pam, Lilette, and I   went to<ref target="http://www.dailyinfo.co.uk/reviews/venue/533/The%2BAnchor%2BInn/"> the Anchor</ref> on Saturday night to over eat in celebration of Elizabeth's 24th birthday (and my newfound ability to sit at table like a mensch). I had devilled kidneys, followed by <hi rend="italic">bavette de boeuf </hi>and chips, followed by rhubarb fool, the whole washed down by a respectable South African pinot, since you ask. On Sunday, Rob and Sylvie, and Owen and Dylan came to tea and we got through an indecent amount of chocolate biscuits and scones and clotted cream. Necessary because of the cold, of course. All of which means that I really didn't do as much walking as I should have, despite the sunshine and my flexible bionic leg.</p>
</div>

<div type="post">
<head>A week of firsts</head>
<p>This week I have mostly been doing things for the first time since last year. Monday, I went to the office and stayed there all day, for the first time. Tuesday, I went to the dentist, the first time I've walked as far south as Beaumont Street. Wednesday, I worked on ENRICH all day (OK, that wasn't a first). Thursday, I made up for Wednesday by having two firsts: a real business meeting (with ISO), and going on a bus up to the JR for my physio. A bus! there and back!
</p><p>
You may correctly deduce that life is getting back to normal. It is a strange kind of normality, still without heating, and still without the ability to get into the shower unaided, but hey, I get up and breakfast, and I walk into the office and send emails hither and yon. I hobble around in my National Health cheapo Don Jon leg brace, sometimes with and sometimes without sticks. I scorn the wheelchair. I exercise. I look forward with some nervousness to to the day (6th March, Suzy says) when I can  discard the brace and join the ranks of the Unaided Hobblers. I also look forward to the day (10 March) when I make my first trip abroad -- to Nancy and then Lyon; buying tickets for that was today's first.</p>
</div>

<div type="post">
<head>Getting by with a gammy leg</head>
<p>Here's what I managed to do on my expedition to France this week...
</p><p>
When I arrived at Nancy Gare about 6 pm, I was pleasantly surprised  to be met by Bertrand Gaiffe, who bundled me into a taxi and sent me off to the <ref target="http://www.hoteldeguise.com">Hotel de Guise</ref>. Which offered me a first-floor room, which was OK since the staircase in  question is highly scenic, featuring nice marble statuary, and well -worn but very small steps. The room rejoiced in a very creaky floorboards and a walk-in shower, hoorah.</p>
<p>Half an hour later, Alex Boulton turned up with his wife and a colleague called Jeanne-Marie Debaisieux: I managed (somehow) to get into the front of his immense motor, and off we drove to the Gentilhommiere, one of the best in the little restaurant ghetto which is rue Marechaux, and which also provides the good advice you see in this photo. <!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/nancy.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/nancy.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/nancy.thumbnail.jpg--></graphic><head>Good advice in a restaurant</head>
</figure></p><p>
My steak was a little too well done, but we had a very enjoyable evening, deprecating the deplorable absence of oral corpora in France (on which Jeanne-Marie has forthright views),  and the general cussedness of French academic life.</p><p>
Next day, Tuesday, I had a shower, which was nice.<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/cnrtl1.jpg-->
Bertrand then
returned and whisked me off in his motor to <ref target="http://www.atilf.fr">ATILF</ref>, which was much as I remember it  from 2003, except that in the front hall there is now a poster proclaiming to the world that it hosts the Centre nationale de ressources textuelles et lexicales  (<ref target="http://www.cnrtl.fr">CNRTL</ref>) and that this  is strictly a TEI establishment (or soon will be).
</p><figure>
<graphic url="media/cnrtl1.jpg"/>
<head>A posterful of good intentions</head></figure> <p>
We had a useful morning discussing TEI politics, and speculating idly about what we should do in the context of the <ref target="http://www.tge-adonis.fr">Adonis</ref> TEI Expertise project. Then we walked (very slowly) up the hill to lunch, where I enjoyed my first  <ref target="http://www.tartiflette.net/">tartiflette</ref> of the year: a deliciously rich baked confection of potato, cream, cheese, and ham served with just the right amount of crunchy salad and a decent cote du rhone. After lunch we walked even more slowly back down the hill, and were then joined by two ladies from <ref target="http://www.inist.fr">INIST</ref> for further discussion about the proposed ADONIS project. They suggested we might use it to reanimate the TEI-FR list, which seems to have been largely moribund since 2006. Various speculative plans were confected, and Bertrand wrote them up. Then the talk turned to local matters (notably a plateforme for dissemination of oral corpora which Etienne Petitjean had apparently started but not finished).
</p><p>
Bertrand then walked me and my suitcase down the hill to the gare (employing a secret and  previously unknown to me <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/23z">route)</ref> again, in good time for the 1810 train Corail train to Lyon, which <ref target="http://routebuilder.org/240">railway route </ref>has the extraordinary characteristic of linking one major city in France to another  <hi rend="bold">without</hi> going via Paris. On the other hand it   takes a bit more than four hours and didn't seem to have a buffet car, which was annoying. I passed the time by doing some more TALC reviews, but mostly by reading <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marina_Lewycka">Marina Lewycka'</ref>s new novel <hi rend="italic">Two  Caravans</hi>, which I can warmly recommend, though I have my doubts about the talking dog.
</p><p>
I arrived at Lyon Part Dieu about 1030 pm, so everything was shut (obviously); humped my suitcase down to the metro, and made it to Debourg just in time to persuade the late night kebab house on the corner to sell me something that might be considered dinner. The security guards at <ref target="http://www.ens-lsh.fr">ENS-LSH</ref> had clearly been alerted to my arrival since when I presented myself to request the key for my room in the Hotel des Invites, I was told that I had a special ground floor room, and even personally escorted to it,a degree of service which I have never seen before. I ate some of my kebab, drank a lot of water, and went to sleep.

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/ens-lsh.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/ens-lsh.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/ens-lsh.thumbnail.jpg--></graphic><head>ens-lsh.jpg</head>
</figure></p><p>
Wednesday morning I experimented with a different shower: also nice. I walked down the road to the little bakers for my petit dej without my leg irons, which was also nice. Then I put my leg irons on properly, and set off to the <ref target="http://jadt2008.ens-lsh.fr">JADT 2008 conference</ref>, arriving in time to make a dramatic entrance in the middle of the ENS director's opening remarks, for which he will no doubt not forgive me.
</p><p>
As well as being the first time in a long time that I've been out of the country, this was also the first time in a long time that I've been to a proper academic conference: I won't try to summarize everything I heard (all the proceedings are online, and were also handed out in printed form), but I can say that I chaired one session, asked a (very small) number of intelligent questions at others, had my mind blown by one or two papers, and managed to stay awake through several others. I heard about some new cool text analysis software; I struggled to follow some very ingenious mathematical modelling; I saw a large number of diagrams that looked like this one.<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/3axes.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/3axes.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/3axes.thumbnail.jpg--></graphic><head>3axes.jpg</head>
</figure>

</p><p>
How pleasant to be at a conference which I had not organized, and where I had nothing to do but listen (I was down to do a Xaira workshop, but hardly anyone turned up so I cut it very short). I renewed acquaintance with numerous textometricians and French corpus linguists, and met some new ones. I was impressed by a plenary from Francois Rastier, less so by one from Jean-Michel Salaun. One evening, there was a screening of a video made a few years ago, in which some of the founding fathers of the current generation of textometricians, i.e. the <hi rend="italic">equipe St Cloud</hi> lead by Maurice Tournier and Pierre Lafon, reminisce about <ref target="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/1/1/45">their work </ref>in the seventies analysing the political broadsheets and tracts from <hi rend="italic">les evenements </hi>
<ref target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mai_68">May 68.</ref>. Alas, the archive of papers visible in the video seems to have vanished as ineluctably as the data (on punch cards) derived from it. Another evening offered a boat trip, but I regretfully declined that in favour of a quiet evening eating, yes,  tartiflette at the student resto round the corner. Friday evening, with the conference finally  wound down, I was able to go out for a quiet dinner with Serge Heiden, and seek his views on the ADONIS TEI project.
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/waiter1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/waiter1.jpg"><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/03/waiter1.thumbnail.jpg--></graphic><head>waiter</head>
</figure></p><p>All of this intellectual activity was rewarded on Saturday morning when I caught the 1000 train to Paris, in good time to meet Guy for lunch at <ref target="www.le-train-bleu.com">Le Train Bleu</ref>: a truly memorable feast in truly memorable surroundings. We had the 48 euro menu, at the heart of which was a gigot d'agneau served from an early 20th century carving table by a waiter with early 20th century flair. There are not many places like this restaurant left in the  world, and very few of them are in such good working order: they are to be cherished. See further my flickr pages.  After lunch, I checked into a hotel near Gare du Nord, and we then went to inspect Guy's flat in rue Alexandre Dumas, a bijou residence at the top of six terrifying flights of highly polished wooden stairs, with a wonky banister somewhere around flight number four. But the lunch made it all worth while...</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
