<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/deplacement-vers-la-vergne-3-8807d28c5353-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Deplacement vers La Vergne, #3</title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Downloaded from https://medium.com/@louBurnard/deplacement-vers-la-vergne-3-8807d28c5353 and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>

<div>
<head>Déplacement vers La Vergne, #3</head>
<p>Can you get from Grenoble to La Vergne by train? Just about, is the short
answer, but you can’t do it in one day. Or not when I tried anyway. Here’s how
it went…</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*gjrzjd1CfvX7bGNhWxjNvw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>This of course is the view from my usual hotel in Grenoble. It’s late
December so there’s an Xmas market in full swing. </head>
</figure>
<p>On 17 December 2014, the morning after <ref target="http://foxglove.hypotheses.org/498">my small
contribution to the political history of Digital Humanities (en France)</ref>, I
said goodbye to the Hotel Europe in sunny downtown Grenoble and set off for la
gare, backpack on my back….</p>
<p>The first train of many is the 1022 departure TER 17616, over the hills and
far away to Lyon PartDieu. I have done the journey before, but in the opposite
direction, so I am anticipating lots of splendid mountain scenery and delightful
prospects as the the train totters up to Le Tour du Pin and down again on the
other side. On this occasion however, the weather is not favourable. Rain sets
in and continues for the rest of the two hour journey.</p>
<p>At Lyon I just have time to pop into the Tall Voyagers Saloon for a drink and
a pee, before catching the next train, TER 86610 to Roanne, wherever that is,
via all sorts of implausibly named stations (see display)</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*h2VFk0YaR-03ePNthb_t4A.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>After “Tarare” comes “Amplepuis”</head>
</figure>
<p> The rain sets in with a vengeance, and the landscape becomes increasingly
soggy, thwarting my natural desire to document the details of the picturesque
countryside I am trundling through.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*2UGsZPTsrNTeBYTrZRkC5w.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>By the time we get to Roanne (13h30) I am seriously in need of lunch, and it
is still far too wet. But what is this I spy, just opposite the station?</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*DmDipX40rs5DJzD4CJtOYA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Photo from <ref
target="http://www.troisgros.fr/le_central/central_cafe.html"
>http://www.troisgros.fr/le_central/central_cafe.html</ref></head>
</figure>
<p> It’s a proper French eating establishment, the (slightly) cheaper kid
brother of a very posh eaterie known as the Troisgros, (“three fatties” ?) for
which Roanne is apparently renowned, though not hitherto by me. I enter and
throw my unworthy self on the mercy of the charming serveuse. <hi rend="italic"
>Une place pour dejeuner, sans reservation</hi>? We will see what the chef says.
Fortunately, the chef is willing, presumably since he still has some of the set
lunch left and the clientele is already well into dessert. The <hi rend="italic"
>formule sur la pouce</hi> turns out to be a tasty vegetable tart, followed by
what I suspect of being beef tongue, lightly poached and served with a piquant
sauce, quite a gastronomic treat compared with what one normally finds in the
cafe opposite the station. Thus fortified, I consider rainy Roanne, which seems
to have little to recommend it, except maybe the distant prospect of one day
being linked by TGV to somewhere else (it seems)</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*GisaZHKSfdalaJ9Zc9zCbw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Would it change your life to be 90 minutes from Paris? Well, depends on
the weather I’d say.</head>
</figure>
<p> There’s an enormous block of offices next door to the station, at the end of
which I find two fat policemen contemplating a traffic junction and a very large
puddle. Back to the station, where I sit on the deserted platform I, trying to
avoid the rain and waiting for the 15h48 stopping train <hi rend="italic"
>to</hi> Clermont-Ferrand, TER 75736</p>
<p>This chugs through the drizzle, stopping here and there, finally reaching my
destination, Riom Chatel Guyon, with five minutes to spare before the TER 73058,
coming <hi rend="italic">from</hi> Clermont-Ferrand arrives. (Take a look on
this map: you’ll realise that this is one of those very rare occasions where the
French railway system actually seems to have been planned to make transversal
journeys feasible)</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*qpYXZQRLFCD5NamdGFrojw.png" rend="img" mimeType="image/png"/>
</figure>
<p> This, my last train of the day, leaves on time at 1702, as the night starts
to fall. It’s a Bombardier. It’s warm. It’s dry. Excellent.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Nzi3x9dg_AosMbYXHq95aQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> And so via various implausibly named towns and villages (Pontmort, Aubiat,
Aigueperse, Gannat, St Bonnet de Rochefort, and Commentry) we chunter across the
Auvergne, cautiously skirting the massif central. <ref
target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commentry">Commentry</ref> was once, it
appears, a coal mining town, and also has the distinction of being the first
commune to elect a socialist mayor (in 1883) but today it just looks wet.
Finally, at 1830 I arrive at the charming railway junction town of Montluçon,
ready for a quick dinner and bed. The latter is provided by the <ref
target="http://www.lefaisan03.com/">Hotel Le Faisan</ref>, which I chose on the
grounds that it seemed to be neither as impossibly luxurious as one of its
neighbours nor as blandly corporate as the other; the former by a surprisingly
pink establishment called Le Scott Resto just across the road from the hotel, of
which I will say nothing. Given the robust nature of <ref
target="http://www.tripadvisor.co.uk/Restaurant_Review-g196521-d3209506-Reviews-The_Scott_Resto-Montlucon_Allier_Auvergne.html"
>its owner’s responses to some critical reviews on TripAdvisor</ref>, you may
attribute this to sheer cowardice on my part if you wish.</p>
<p>The next morning I am up early to do some sightseeing and the rain seems to
have stopped. First up, the splendid memorial outside the station, commemorating
the gallant resistance of the good citizens of Montluçon when during the
Occupation some of them were forced to work the coal fields for the Boches.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1_CVqeNBJ0M9fBxZZFZG-kPw.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>See further <ref
target="http://www.afmd-allier.com/PBCPPlayer.asp?ID=1412769"
>http://www.afmd-allier.com/PBCPPlayer.asp?ID=1412769</ref> and <ref
target="http://www.vanderkrogt.net/statues/object.php?webpage=ST&amp;record=frau009"
>http://www.vanderkrogt.net/statues/object.php?webpage=ST&amp;record=frau009</ref></head>
</figure>
<p> Next, it’s a pleasant enough stroll down the broad Avenue Marx-Dormoy, which
in normal times is dominated by this statue of <ref
target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marx_Dormoy">the great man</ref> behind the
1920s war memorial. Today however, it is dominated by a rather tacky Christmas
funfair, which somewhat encroaches on his space.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*2mz2VWUaq8rW6So2IXWNTw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Statue commemorating Marx-Dormoy apparently just getting out of bed:
there’s a better picture <ref
target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marx_Dormoy#mediaviewer/File:Montlu%C3%A7on_monument_Marx_Dormoy_1.jpg"
>her</ref>e</head>
</figure>
<p> The Avenue joins up with the central shopping street, down which I wander in
search of toiletries and a nice view of the Modern Bar.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*AAPOHKdX74Jq6aawobIwgA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>rue des Serrures, Montlucon</head>
</figure>
<p> But the main architectural presence is of course the <ref
target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ch%C3%A2teau_des_ducs_de_Bourbon_%C3%A0_Montlu%C3%A7on"
>Château des ducs de Bourbon à Montluçon</ref>, which sits on top of the hill
around which this and all the other streets cluster in approved medieval
fashion.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*gutI4cOkS9Z8XUxRhNJRTw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>The Chateau itself</head>
</figure>
<p> All around the chateau, there are splendid viewpoints over the said streets,
some of them with helpful if outdated indicator boards to show where various
establishments used to be, back in the day:</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*T3HyCOrfko1Cw1HHz7tuNg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head><hi rend="bold">Syndicat d’Initiative</hi>s is a phrase you don’t hear
much these days</head>
</figure>
<p> Down below there are indeed narrow twisty little medieval streets full of
picturesque half timbered houses, ancient monuments etc.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*QJmEx80jzZTePaL5rieX-g.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
<head>rue des cinq-pierres</head>
</figure>
<p> Definitely worth a revisit when the weather has improved. For the moment,
however, it’s time to head back to the station for the final train of the trip,
the very last (almost) part of my journey, which is the 11h34 TER 68703 to Gueret, a one
hour journey via Huriel, Lavaufranche, Gouzon, Parsac, and Busseau-sur-Creuse
etc. On the map it’s a very wiggly train line, and in the flesh (as it were)
probably highly scenic. I say “probably” because the one-carriage train itself
turned about to be so dirty after yesterday’s rain that I could scarcely see
through the window of my notionally first class compartment.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*QzftU5DcaJ8ghzdcm09LxA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>TER 68703 waiting to depart from Montlucon. In need of a good wash.</head>
</figure>
<p>No matter. I arrived in Gueret unscathed, where Wim and Anke met me, loaded
me into their car and drove me to Dun Le Palestel for our appointment with
Maitre de Lisle.  After which final transaction, I am now the proud owner of No. 3 La Vergne. Wim and Anke, unimpressed, drop me at the Intermarche supermarket and drive off into their own life. And so, the last leg of my journey to La Vergne was perforce accomplished by an over priced taxi. </p><p>Postscript: and that is how I came to spend my first night
in La Vergne, brrr brr, on Dec 18, 2014. The following day, I got a lift to La Souterraine with Duane, and took the train to Limoges, where I had another day to wait before catching an aeroplane to Southampton, and thus back to Oxford. But that's another story. </p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
