<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Source: https://medium.com/@louBurnard/an-expedition-to-the-grand-duchy-of-lithuania-2-6ffbee8d5fdc-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>An expedition to the Grand Duchy of Lithuania </title>
<author/>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<p/>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Originally published at https://medium.com/@louBurnard/an-expedition-to-the-grand-duchy-of-lithuania-2-6ffbee8d5fdc  and https://medium.com/@louBurnard/an-expedition-to-the-grand-duchy-of-lithuania-3-626e7212a85d ; combined and translated from HTML to TEI</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<body>


<head>An Expedition into the Grand Duchy of Lithuania </head>

<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/mapofnortherneurope.png-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/mapofnortherneurope.png" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/mapofnortherneurope.png?w=700--></graphic>
<head>A map of Northern Europe</head>
</figure>
<p> Click on the above map and consider. As you can see the most direct route
from London to Vilnius by train would take you through Brussells and Warsaw and
then either across Belarus or by snaking a little further North directly into
Lithuania. Sadly however, though it has been promised for some time now, there
is currently no direct rail link, and travel via Belarus remains complicated.
There is however a third way, not so well advertised, by means of the daily
ferryboat across the Baltic from Kiel to Klaipeda (not marked on my map, but
it's Lithuania's only seaport): which proves to be very agreeable if you are not
in a hurry and the weather is good.</p>
<div>
<head>Day 1 (20 July 2014)</head>
<p> We left Oxford around lunchtime on Sunday, and made the entirely familiar,
not to say boring, train journey to Brussells, arriving in good time to enjoy an
entirely unexpected fun fair located directly outside the cheap hotel I'd
randomly selected from the dozens around Bruxelles-midi. <!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_170303_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140720_170303_v1.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_170303_v1.jpg?w=700--></graphic>
<head>Here's the rather dramatic view from the 6th floor. </head>
</figure>
</p>
<p> The fun fair is behind the row of caravans. Glancing down there, the first
thing we saw was a strange amusement which seemed to consist of placing children
into inflated floating  pods: <!--https://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_170108_v1.jpg-->
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140720_170108_v1.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_170108_v1.jpg?w=700--></graphic>
<p>A strange amusement</p>
</figure>
</p>
<p> Otherwise, Belgian funfairs seem to be strong on deep fried food, (I rather
enjoyed my beignets de framboises – real live raspberries wrapped in dough and
deep-fried but Lilette was unimpressed). There were scarey roller coasters and
pop music as per St Giles Fair, but also child-friendly real live pony rides,
archery contests, ancient machines for trying your strength or measuring your
passion, and similar atavistic delights. <figure>
<graphic url="media/20140720_182550.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_182550.jpg?w=700--></graphic><head>Almost
anything you want, covered in batter, deep fried, and sprinkled with
sugar</head>
</figure>
</p>
<p>

<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140720_173852.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_173852.jpg?w=700--></graphic>
<head>Real Ponies!</head>
</figure>
</p>
<p>

<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140720_174911_v1.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_174911_v1.jpg?w=700--></graphic>
<head>Test your Passion Machine. We don't need one, thank you.</head>
</figure>
</p>
<p>

<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140720_181949_v1.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_181949_v1.jpg?w=700--></graphic>
<head>Really scarey rides for people with strong somachs and a serious death
wish</head>
</figure>
</p>
<p>

<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140720_181525.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140720_181525.jpg?w=700--></graphic>
<head>If you can't talk nicely...</head>
<figDesc> Be nice, or go away</figDesc>
</figure>
</p>
<p> Afterwards we strayed into a street full of Moroccan restaurants, just as
dusk came and they began to open up for the benefit of those observing Ramadam,
and even us too. And so to bed on the 6th floor: a good start to the
holiday.</p>
</div><div>
<head>Day 2 (21 July 2014)</head>

<p><figure>
<graphic url="media/20140721_114541_v1.jpg" width="700px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140721_114541_v1.jpg?w=700--></graphic>
<head>Sausage Break at Frankfurt hauptbahnhof: entirely appropriate.</head>
</figure></p>
<p> After an entirely unmemorable breakfast, we headed back to Midi station,
fighting our way through hundreds of other holiday makers, backpackers,
screaming children, etc. to catch the 1030 ICE train into and across Germany.
Which was, of course, just like every other ICE train I've ever caught, i.e.
(depending on one's mood and how late it's running) restful, sybaritic, or
really rather boring. It got less crowded after Koln, and even less so by the
time we got to Frankfurt, where we were able to enjoy a protracted sausage break
waiting for ICE 74, the train that goes all the way from Zurich to Kiel, and
which was running about 30 minutes late. I wish I had something interesting to
say about these magnificent white trains that just zoom across Europe, quietly
announcing their speed and the stations they pass through on monitors at the end
of each carriage. Sitting in the <hi rend="italic">gros raum</hi> comfy chairs,
with wifi and regular offers of drinkable coffee and refreshments (I recommend
the <hi rend="italic">eintopf</hi>) in real white china from impeccably
turned-out wait persons, as the countryside hurtles past the window it's easy to
get blasé about them. Which one should not, as they are a splendid achievement. 

<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140721_120425.jpg" width="700px"/>
<!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140721_120425.jpg?w=700-->
<head>ICE 37 arrives at Frankfurt only 28 minutes late, en route from Zurich to
Kiel</head>
</figure></p>
<p> And so to Kiel, the main port of Schleswig-Holstein as any fule kno. Our
hotel, the accurately named “Basic Hotel” is just a few minutes walk through the
horrible modern shopping centre which seems to be the main feature of downtown
Kiel, the rest of it having been presumably flattened during the war. </p>
<p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/20140721_183000_v1.jpg" width="218px"
><!--http://louburnard.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/20140721_183000_v1.jpg?w=218--></graphic>
<head>Burgomeister and friend</head>
</figure>
</p>
<p> Bags having been dumped (second floor no lift, but a nice big bed, and good
wifi) , we walked across town, following the indications of the handy tourist
information leaflet. This being Germany, the tourist information board knew
exactly what we wanted to see: lots of European shops, weird statues of former
notables (notably former burgermeister Asmus Bremer), and a lovingly re-created
alter markt with its own brewery, the renowned Kieler Brauerei. At which place, 
(this being Germany), I felt obliged to consume beer, along with matjes herrings
and potatos but Lilette had more sense. And so to bed.</p>
<trailer>
<hi rend="italic">Part Two is published on <ref
target="https://medium.com/@louBurnard/an-expedition-to-the-grand-duchy-of-lithuania-2-6ffbee8d5fdc"
>my new Medium blog</ref>
</hi>
</trailer>
</div>

<div>
<head>Day 3 (22 July 2014)</head>
<p>At last, a decent breakfast at a reasonable time. The tourist brochure
suggests that we might like to explore Kiel’s famous multicultural Turkish Town
since we were so snotty about the shopping centre. Down the hill, back past the
station, across the long bridge over the harbour neck (apparently this is the
biggest folding bridge in European. Did you know that folding bridges existed?
No me neither), and up the hill on the other side. It’s Monday morning, but it’s
holiday time too, so everyone is outside sunning themselves and their kids.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*rh7V4u1dsEUEO5XGdfBRjA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>The cycle path back from Turkish Town</head>
</figure>
<p> Turkish Town is pleasingly similar to the Cowley Road, with a few minor
adjustments, like the pound shop is a euro shop (which is a bargain) and there
are people selling mysterious herbs and spices from baskets in the middle of the
square.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*7So_6OpgVo53cZxVq9waGg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*d3rZBLtJR-VBFcrvdkbeFQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p> There are also ladies in pink, implausibly luxurious golden bedding for
sale, and adverts for a large variety of milk-derived products.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*HmU-HYtwyusjS5839j9yjQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>We have coffee, we watch the old ladies selling strange leaves, and relax
till it’s time to head back and catch a taxi out to a suburb of Kiel, called
Ostufer, where DFDS have had to build their nice new terminal, all the space in
the existing one having been swallowed up by Stena Line.</p>
<p>The check in process is complicated, involving much waiting and paper work,
but eventually we are cleared for departure in a little bus out to the ship
herself: currently being loaded with assorted huge lorries, as well as a
scattering of lightweight foot passengers like us. It’s a ship, people.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*k5axN0TtfP_aoyL2s9OpYQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>So that’s what the back end of a ship looks like</head>
</figure>
<p>A great big floating metal object you can drive a dozen huge trucks onto,
with four decks full of nice little cabins, a massive restaurant, a couple of
bars, and a helicopter landing pad on top. There’s a strange mixture of
passengers: Russian lorry drivers, who are already glugging down serious amounts
of Lithuanian beer, German holiday-making families, and retired couples cruising
the Baltic. We explore the corridors and public areas, testing the limits of
where we are allowed to wander outside our nice little cabins. There’s a
darkened mysterious room full of reclining chairs. There’s a few cyclists
sitting out on deck. Everyone is enjoying the view as suddenly without fuss this
enormous metal object starts moving out of the long narrow channel of Kiel
harbour, past the unlovely tower and the nice beach which marks its entrance,
and into the Baltic. Out on deck a few furtive smokers celebrate with smelly
cigarettes in front of the No Smoking sign. The engine noise is detectable, but
the boat moves serenely and smoothly, with none of the distressing friskiness
underfoot of a cross channel ferry, and land remains reassuringly in sight for
most of the journey. Plus, since we have tickets for the enormous buffet dinner
now being served, it’s time to stuff our faces again. Which we do, before
retiring to our nice little cabin for a good night’s sleep. All in all, very
satisfying.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Day 4 (23 July 24)</head>
<p>We wake, still on the ocean wave, but now a lot further East. Otherwise,
nothing much seems to have changed. The buffet for dinner is now a buffet for
breakfast. The man who impressed Lilette by taking twelve biscuits with his
dinner last night is taking another twelve with his breakfast. The Russian lorry
drivers have now sobered up enough to start drinking beer again. The sea is,
momentarily choppy enough to remind us we’re not on dry land, then calms down
again as we skirt Kaliningrad, and start our approach to the <ref
target="http://www.lithuanianhotels.com/site/neringa">Curonian Spit</ref> at the
very end of which lies the narrow entrance into the enormous (Soviet-built)
Klaipeda dockyards. Birds swirl about overhead and the sun continues to shine.
Up on deck, as the ship proceeds inexorably, we can now see tankers, maritime
buildings, other lesser craft, clear signs we are arriving.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*i5Ntu_vHT8qtb1f9qHPdOA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Klaipeda dockside complete with serious crane</head>
</figure>
<p>It all seems a little anti-climactic and too simple, after 21 hours, just to
pick up our cases and trundle them off the ship the way we came, to an obscure
corner of the dock, where we have to wait for a little bus to trundle us back to
the terminal building. And here is my friend Tania come to whisk us away to our
next hotel, in a taxi!</p>
<p>Tania is now head of conservation at the University Library in Vilnius, but
she grew up in <ref
target="http://www.truelithuania.com/topics/cities-of-lithuania/klaipeda"
>Klaipeda</ref> and says she’s grateful to us for giving her an excuse to return
and guide us around its high spots. These include a range of nice old buildings,
plenty of places to eat ice cream, some parks, and a lot of really rather
strange public sculpture, including a red dragon which doubles as a drain pipe
and apparently relates to one of the founding myths of the city, a rather
winsome small boy waving his hat to greet arriving ships, and a decidedly spooky
ghost hanging over the harbour wall.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*ILGyfEIcukp2zMG36y_3YQ.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">“ A steel sculpture “Dragon” was created appealing to one of
the legends retelling emergence of Klaipėda. One of them tells about two
brothers who sought a place for a city; one of them disappeared, another found
only a traces of the undone and a horrific foot. Author imagined that a terribly
huge footmark could be only of a dragon. A 145 kg weight, over three meter long
dragon hangs on the wall not without reason, but fulfills a function of a rain
pipe. During rain, one may admire water splashing out of the jaws of the dragon.
(Author Vytautas Karčiauskas).”</hi></p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*M3nDOfEwR647EKDDgYJT4Q.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>
<hi rend="italic">A sculpture design — little boy with a dog waving with his
hat, emerged on the terminal in summer 2007. Sculpture mission is direct — “to
meet and see off” the cruise ships which call in the terminal. And also, delight
those walking the quay. In one word, nobody shall leave the terminal without
escort. (Sculpture authors — Svajūnas Jurkus and Vytautas Paulionis).</hi></p>
<p>Amongst other architectural pleasure, the old town of Klaipeda boats a fine
18th c Theatre and a remarkable (and still functioning) art nouveau post office
from the 1920s. We dined at an Armenian restaurant, (good fish, good wine) and
retired to sleep the sleep of the well-travelled.</p>
</div>
<div>
<head>Day 5 (24 July 2014)</head>
<p>We have the best part of a day to spend before taking the train for the last
part of our journey to Vilnius, so Tania proposes an excursion by hired
bicycles. We walk through the heat across the silent University campus and out
to the ring road where bicycles are to be hired. Then we head off across the
park, pass Girulių station, pause for ice cream, and follow the <hi
rend="italic">Turistų</hi> trail into the woods, and down to the beach.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*Jkb2WbM24EFrqpnJVOYxAw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>Is there anything more pleasant on a hot day than riding a bike along a
peaceful trail through a peaceful forest of pine trees? I think not. We arrived
eventually at a place called <hi rend="italic">Olando kepurė (</hi>or, don’t ask
why, Dutchman’s hat) which to my untutored eye looks like a sandy cliff but
which Wikipedia informs me is actually “a parabolic dune created by Aeolian
processes on a moraine ridge” overlooking the Baltic, and stretching for miles
to the North. On the sand below the cliff, a sprinkling of holiday makers.</p>
<figure>
<graphic
url="media/1*UuIcnlW2NTJU4TumYTC6Lg.jpeg"
rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>No commercial clutter, and the only sign of officialdom two young women
energetically cleaning the informative notice placed to mark this particular
vantage point as an official touristic attraction.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*ON9JVWdPwEX53ga6K3gUXA.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>We take photos, of course, and enjoy the view before cycling back into town
and head for the station to buy our train tickets. Klaipeda station has gained a
rather impressive erection since it was first built.</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*2PqldhXD3WPY4g3FfoJuMg.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
</figure>
<p>We contemplate this from the other side of the road, where we are pausing for
a rather late but very tasty lunch</p>
<figure>
<graphic url="media/1*GLCdMKVM1YJGIqdFM7WEmw.jpeg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>

<head>Lithanian take on shopska salata. With pumpkin seeds</head>
</figure>
<p>It takes about five hours to get from Klaipeda to Vilnius by train. Tania is
taking the bus, (which is about an hour quicker), but I have, as we say in
France, <hi rend="italic">une faiblesse</hi> for trains. Therefore it is a
relief to find that the train is both long and capacious, with reasonably
comfortable seats, which is good news for those still full of lunch. It stops at
numerous strangely named stations (Kretinga, Plungė, Kaišiadorys …) , most of
them quite modern, though we see quite a lot of unspoilt countryside and forest,
with the occasional farmstead , collective farm, and factory. There are also a
few old-fashioned stations (notably Jonava) unchanged since the line was built
in the 1870s.</p>
<p> Arriving into Vilnius, we have time for a quick bite to eat at the pizza
joint across the road from the station, and then Tania takes us to the little
flat she has reserved for us in the Old Town. I am tired and ungracious on
account of having to give a talk tomorrow which is not quite ready. No change
there then.</p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
